<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2016">
  <identification id="alpines" isproject="true">
    <shortname>ALPINES</shortname>
    <projectName>Algorithms and parallel tools for integrated numerical simulations</projectName>
    <theme-de-recherche>Distributed and High Performance Computing</theme-de-recherche>
    <domaine-de-recherche>Networks, Systems and Services, Distributed Computing</domaine-de-recherche>
    <urlTeam>http://team.inria.fr/alpines</urlTeam>
    <structure_exterieure type="Labs">
      <libelle>Laboratoire Jacques-Louis Lions (LJLL)</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>CNRS</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>Université Pierre et Marie Curie (Paris 6)</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <header_dates_team>Creation of the Team: 2013 January 01, updated into Project-Team: 2014 July 01</header_dates_team>
    <LeTypeProjet>Project-Team</LeTypeProjet>
    <keywordsSdN>
      <term>6.1.1. - Continuous Modeling (PDE, ODE)</term>
      <term>6.1.4. - Multiscale modeling</term>
      <term>6.1.5. - Multiphysics modeling</term>
      <term>6.2.1. - Numerical analysis of PDE and ODE</term>
      <term>6.2.5. - Numerical Linear Algebra</term>
      <term>6.2.7. - High performance computing</term>
      <term>6.3. - Computation-data interaction</term>
      <term>6.3.1. - Inverse problems</term>
      <term>7.1. - Parallel and distributed algorithms</term>
    </keywordsSdN>
    <keywordsSecteurs>
      <term>3.3.1. - Earth and subsoil</term>
      <term>9.4.2. - Mathematics</term>
      <term>9.4.3. - Physics</term>
    </keywordsSecteurs>
    <UR name="Paris"/>
  </identification>
  <team id="uid1">
    <person key="alpines-2014-idm28288">
      <firstname>Laura</firstname>
      <lastname>Grigori</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2014-idp65112">
      <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
      <lastname>Nataf</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>CNRS, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
      <firstname>Xavier</firstname>
      <lastname>Claeys</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Paris VI, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2014-idm26800">
      <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
      <lastname>Hecht</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Paris VI, Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2015-idp67824">
      <firstname>Simplice</firstname>
      <lastname>Donfack</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2015-idp69096">
      <firstname>Ange</firstname>
      <lastname>Toulougoussou</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2015-idp70344">
      <firstname>Hussam</firstname>
      <lastname>Al Daas</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2015-idp71584">
      <firstname>Alan</firstname>
      <lastname>Ayala Obregon</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by FP7 H NLAFET project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2014-idp73952">
      <firstname>Sebastien</firstname>
      <lastname>Cayrols</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2014-idp75224">
      <firstname>Mohamed Ryadh</firstname>
      <lastname>Haferssas</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Paris VI, until Sep 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2016-idp135072">
      <firstname>Zakariae</firstname>
      <lastname>Jorti</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>IFP Energies nouvelles, from Feb 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="airsea-2015-idp104592">
      <firstname>Pierre</firstname>
      <lastname>Marchand</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="commands-2014-idp75608">
      <firstname>Olivier</firstname>
      <lastname>Tissot</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by FP7 H NLAFET project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2015-idp75360">
      <firstname>Cihui</firstname>
      <lastname>Pan</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until Sep 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2014-idp68864">
      <firstname>Pierre-Henri</firstname>
      <lastname>Tournier</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until Nov 2016, granted by ANR MEDIMAX- project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2016-idp147424">
      <firstname>Maria</firstname>
      <lastname>Barreda Vaya</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Universitat Jaume, Castelló de la Plana (Spain), from Sep 2016 until Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="alpines-2016-idp150064">
      <firstname>Amanda</firstname>
      <lastname>Bienz</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Paris</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>UIUC, USA, from Apr 2016 until Jul 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
  </team>
  <presentation id="uid2">
    <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid3" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Introduction</bodyTitle>
      <p>The focus of our research is on the development of novel parallel numerical
algorithms and tools appropriate for state-of-the-art mathematical models
used in complex scientific applications, and in particular numerical simulations.
The proposed research program is by nature multi-disciplinary, interweaving
aspects of applied mathematics, computer science, as well as those of several
specific applications, as porous media flows, elasticity, wave propagation in
multi-scale media.</p>
      <p>Our first objective is to develop numerical methods and tools for complex
scientific and industrial applications, that will enhance their scalable
execution on the emergent heterogeneous hierarchical models of massively
parallel machines. Our second
objective is to integrate the novel numerical algorithms into a
middle-layer that will hide as much as possible the complexity of
massively parallel machines from the users of these machines.</p>
    </subsection>
  </presentation>
  <fondements id="uid4">
    <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid5" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Overview</bodyTitle>
      <p>The research described here is directly relevant to several steps of
the numerical simulation chain. Given a numerical simulation that was
expressed as a set of differential equations, our research focuses on
mesh generation methods for parallel computation, novel numerical
algorithms for linear algebra, as well as algorithms and tools for
their efficient and scalable implementation on high performance
computers. The validation and the exploitation of the results is
performed with collaborators from applications and is based on
the usage of existing tools. In summary, the topics studied in our
group are the following:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid6">
          <p noindent="true">Numerical methods and algorithms</p>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid7">
              <p noindent="true">Mesh generation for parallel computation</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid8">
              <p noindent="true">Solvers for numerical linear algebra</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid9">
              <p noindent="true">Computational kernels for numerical linear algebra</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </li>
        <li id="uid10">
          <p noindent="true">Validation on numerical simulations</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid11" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Domain specific language - parallel FreeFem++</bodyTitle>
      <p>In the engineering, researchers, and teachers communities, there is a
strong demand for simulation frameworks that are simple to install and
use, efficient, sustainable, and that solve efficiently and accurately
complex problems for which there are no dedicated tools or codes
available. In our group we develop FreeFem++ (see <ref xlink:href="http://www.freefem.org/ff++" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>freefem.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>ff++</ref>),
a user dedicated language for solving PDEs. The goal of FreeFem++ is
not to be a substitute for complex numerical codes,
but rather to provide an efficient and relatively generic tool for:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid12">
          <p noindent="true">getting a quick answer to a specific problem,</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid13">
          <p noindent="true">prototyping the resolution of a new complex problem.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p>The current users of FreeFem++ are mathematicians, engineers,
university professors, and students. In general for these users the
installation of public libraries as MPI, MUMPS, Ipopt, Blas, lapack,
OpenGL, fftw, scotch, is a very difficult problem. For this reason,
the authors of FreeFem++ have created a user friendly language, and
over years have enriched its capabilities and provided tools for
compiling FreeFem++ such that the users do not need to have special
knowledge of computer science. This leads to an important work on
porting the software on different emerging architectures.</p>
      <p>Today, the main components of parallel FreeFem++ are:</p>
      <orderedlist>
        <li id="uid14">
          <p noindent="true">definition of a coarse grid,</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid15">
          <p noindent="true">splitting of the coarse grid,</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid16">
          <p noindent="true">mesh generation of all subdomains of the coarse grid, and
construction of parallel datat structures for vectors and sparse
matrices from the mesh of the subdomain,</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid17">
          <p noindent="true">call to a linear solver,</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid18">
          <p noindent="true">analysis of the result.</p>
        </li>
      </orderedlist>
      <p>All these components are parallel, except for point (5) which is not
in the focus of our research. However for the moment, the parallel
mesh generation algorithm is very simple and not sufficient, for
example it addresses only polygonal geometries. Having a better
parallel mesh generation algorithm is one of the goals of our project. In addition, in the current version
of FreeFem++, the parallelism is not hidden from the user, it is done
through direct calls to MPI. Our goal is also to hide all the MPI
calls in the specific language part of FreeFem++.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid19" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Solvers for numerical linear algebra</bodyTitle>
      <p>Iterative methods are widely used in industrial applications, and
preconditioning is the most important research subject here.
Our research considers domain decomposition methods and iterative methods and its goal is to develop
solvers that are suitable for parallelism and that exploit the fact
that the matrices are arising from the discretization of a system of
PDEs on unstructured grids.</p>
      <p>One of the main challenges that we address is the lack of robustness
and scalability of existing methods as incomplete LU factorizations or
Schwarz-based approaches, for which the number of iterations increases
significantly with the problem size or with the number of processors.
This is often due to the presence of several low frequency modes that
hinder the convergence of the iterative method. To address this
problem, we study direction preserving solvers in the context of
multilevel domain decomposition methods with adaptive coarse spaces
and multilevel incomplete decompositions. A judicious choice for
the directions to be preserved through filtering or low rank approximations allows us to
alleviate the effect of low frequency modes on the convergence.</p>
      <p>We also focus on developing boundary integral equation methods that would be adapted to
the simulation of wave propagation in complex physical situations, and that would lend themselves to the use of parallel
architectures, which includes devising adapted domain decomposition approaches. The final objective is to bring the
state of the art on boundary integral equations closer to contemporary industrial needs.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid20" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Computational kernels for numerical linear algebra</bodyTitle>
      <p>The design of new numerical methods that are robust and that have well
proven convergence properties is one of the challenges addressed in Alpines. Another important challenge is the design of parallel
algorithms for the novel numerical methods and the underlying building blocks from numerical linear algebra. The goal is
to enable their efficient execution on a diverse set of node
architectures and their scaling to emerging high-performance clusters
with an increasing number of nodes.</p>
      <p>Increased communication cost is one of the main challenges in high
performance computing that we address in our research by investigating
algorithms that minimize communication, as communication avoiding
algorithms. We propose to integrate the minimization of communication into
the algorithmic design of
numerical linear algebra problems. This is different from previous
approaches where the communication problem was addressed as a
scheduling or as a tuning problem. The communication avoiding
algorithmic design is an aproach originally developed in our group
since 2007 (initially in collaboration with researchers from UC Berkeley
and CU Denver). While at mid term we focus on reducing
communication in numerical linear algebra, at long term we aim at
considering the communication problem one level higher, during the
parallel mesh generation tool described earlier.</p>
    </subsection>
  </fondements>
  <domaine id="uid21">
    <bodyTitle>Application Domains</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid22" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Compositional multiphase Darcy flow in
heterogeneous porous media</bodyTitle>
      <p>We study the simulation of compositional multiphase flow in porous
media with different types of applications, and we focus in
particular on reservoir/bassin modeling, and geological CO2
underground storage. All these simulations are linearized using
Newton approach, and at each time step and each Newton step, a linear
system needs to be solved, which is the most expensive part of the
simulation. This application leads to some of the difficult problems
to be solved by iterative methods. This is because the linear systems
arising in multiphase porous media flow simulations cumulate many
difficulties. These systems are non-symmetric, involve several
unknowns of different nature per grid cell, display strong or very
strong heterogeneities and anisotropies, and change during the
simulation. Many researchers focus on these simulations, and many
innovative techniques for solving linear systems have been introduced
while studying these simulations, as for example the nested
factorization [Appleyard and Cheshire, 1983, SPE Symposium on Reservoir Simulation].</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid23" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Inverse problems</bodyTitle>
      <p>The research of F. Nataf on inverse problems is rather new since this activity was started from scratch in 2007. Since then, several papers were published in international journals and conference proceedings. All our numerical simulations were performed in FreeFem++.</p>
      <p noindent="true">We focus on methods related to time reversal techniques. Since the seminal paper by [M. Fink et al., Imaging through inhomogeneous media using time reversal mirrors. Ultrasonic Imaging, 13(2):199, 1991.], time reversal is a subject of very active research. The main idea is to take advantage of the reversibility of wave propagation phenomena such as it occurs in acoustics, elasticity or electromagnetism in a non-dissipative unknown medium to back-propagate signals to the sources that emitted them. Number of industrial applications have already been developped: touchscreen, medical imaging, non-destructive testing and underwater communications. The principle is to back-propagate signals to the sources that emitted them. The initial experiment, was to refocus, very precisely, a recorded signal after passing through a barrier consisting of randomly distributed metal rods. In [de Rosny and Fink. Overcoming the difraction limit in wave physics using a time-reversal mirror and a novel acoustic sink. Phys. Rev. Lett., 89 (12), 2002], the source that created the signal is time reversed in order to have a perfect time reversal experiment. Since then, numerous applications of this physical principle have been designed, see [Fink, Renversement du temps, ondes et innovation. Ed. Fayard, 2009] or for numerical experiments [Larmat et al., Time-reversal imaging of seismic sources and application to the great sumatra earthquake. Geophys. Res. Lett., 33, 2006] and references therein.
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid24" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Numerical methods for wave propagation in multi-scale media</bodyTitle>
      <p>We are interested in the development of fast numerical methods for the simulation of
electromagnetic waves in multi-scale situations where the geometry of the medium of propagation
may be described through caracteristic lengths that are, in some places, much smaller than the
average wavelength. In this context, we propose to develop numerical algorithms that rely on
simplified models obtained by means of asymptotic analysis applied to the problem
under consideration.</p>
      <p>Here we focus on situations involving boundary layers and <i>localized</i> singular
perturbation problems where wave propagation takes place in media whose geometry or material
caracteristics are submitted to a small scale perturbation localized around a point, or a surface,
or a line, but not distributed over a volumic sub-region of the propagation medium. Although a huge
literature is already available for the study of localized singular perturbations and boundary layer
pheneomena, very few works have proposed efficient numerical methods that rely on asymptotic
modeling. This is due to their natural functional framework that naturally involves singular functions,
which are difficult to handle numerically. The aim of this part of our reasearch is to develop and analyze
numerical methods for singular perturbation methods that are prone to high order numerical approximation,
and robust with respect to the small parameter caracterizing the singular perturbation.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid25" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Data analysis in astrophysics</bodyTitle>
      <p>We focus on computationally intensive numerical algorithms arising in
the data analysis of current and forthcoming Cosmic Microwave
Background (CMB) experiments in astrophysics. This application is
studied in collaboration with researchers from University Paris
Diderot, and the objective is to make available the algorithms to the
astrophysics community, so that they can be used in large experiments.</p>
      <p>In CMB data analysis, astrophysicists produce and analyze
multi-frequency 2D images of the universe when it was 5% of its
current age. The new generation of the CMB experiments observes the
sky with thousands of detectors over many years, producing
overwhelmingly large and complex data sets, which nearly double every
year therefore following Moore's Law. Planck
(<ref xlink:href="http://planck.esa.int/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>planck.<allowbreak/>esa.<allowbreak/>int/</ref>) is a keystone satellite mission which has
been developed under auspices of the European Space Agency
(ESA). Planck has been surveying the sky since 2010, produces
terabytes of data and requires 100 Petaflops per image analysis of
the universe. It is predicted that future experiments will collect
half petabyte of data, and will require 100 Exaflops per analysis as
early as in 2020. This shows that data analysis in this area, as many
other applications, will keep pushing the limit of available
supercomputing power for the years to come.</p>
    </subsection>
  </domaine>
  <highlights id="uid26">
    <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid27" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid28" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Awards</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid29" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>SIAM Siag on Supercomputing Best Paper Prize 2016</bodyTitle>
          <p>for the most outstanding
paper published in 2012-2015 in a journal in the field of high
performance computing. Co-authors are
J. Demmel, L. Grigori, M. Hoemmen, and J. Langou, for the paper
Communication-Optimal Parallel and Sequential QR and LU
Factorizations, published in SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing
2012.</p>
          <p noindent="true">Citation of the jury: <i>This is a cornerstone paper
in Numerical Linear Algebra and Parallel Processing that lays down
both theoretical and practical algorithmic frameworks for
communication-avoiding algorithms. The paper provides powerful
insights and renews attention on communication reduction both of
which will have long-lasting and practical impact in parallel and
distributed computing.</i></p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid30" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Bull-Joseph Fourier 1st Prize 2015 (15 000 euros)</bodyTitle>
          <p>for our work
<i>Imaging of cerebrovascular accident through High Performance Computing</i> by V. Dolean, F. Hecht, P. Jolivet, F. Nataf and P-H. Tournier. This was the sixth edition of this competition which corresponds to the French "Gordon Bell Prize".</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </highlights>
  <logiciels id="uid31">
    <bodyTitle>New Software and Platforms</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid32" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>BFD</bodyTitle>
      <p>Block Filtering Decomposition preconditioner</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Preconditioner - Linear system</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>Iterative methods are used in many industrial and academic applications to solve large sparse linear systems of equations, and preconditioning these methods is often necessary to accelerate their convergence. Several highly used preconditioners as incomplete LU factorizations are known to have scalability problems, often due to the presence of several low frequency modes that hinder the convergence of the iterative method. To address this problem, we work on filtering preconditioners. A judicious choice of the filtering vector allows to alleviate the effect of low frequency modes, and can accelerate significantly the convergence of the iterative method.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid33">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Laura Grigori, Remi Lacroix and Frédéric Nataf</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid34">
          <p noindent="true">Partners: CNRS - UPMC</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid35">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Laura Grigori</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid36">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://who.rocq.inria.fr/Laura.Grigori/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>who.<allowbreak/>rocq.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>Laura.<allowbreak/>Grigori/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid37" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>CALU : communication optimal algorithms for linear algebra</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Communication avoiding - Linear algebra</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>CALU solves linear systems of equations Ax=b using Communication Avoiding LU.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid38">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Laura Grigori</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid39">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://who.rocq.inria.fr/Laura.Grigori/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>who.<allowbreak/>rocq.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>Laura.<allowbreak/>Grigori/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid40" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>DPREPack</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keyword:</span> Large scale</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>This library solves linear systems on parallel computers from PCs based on multicore processors to large scale computers.
It implements recent parallel algorithms issued from domain decomposition methods and parallel approximate factorizations.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid41">
          <p noindent="true">Partners: CNRS - UPMC</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid42">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Laura Grigori</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid43">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://team.inria.fr/alpines/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>team.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>alpines/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid44" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>FreeFem++</bodyTitle>
      <p>FeeFrem++</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Scientific Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>FreeFem++ is a partial differential equation solver. It has its own language. freefem scripts can solve multiphysics non linear systems in 2D and 3D.</p>
      <p>Problems involving PDE (2d, 3d) from several branches of physics such as fluid-structure interactions require interpolations of data on several meshes and their manipulation within one program. FreeFem++ includes a fast <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mn>2</mn><mi>d</mi></msup></math></formula>-tree-based interpolation algorithm and a language for the manipulation of data on multiple meshes (as a follow up of bamg (now a part of FreeFem++ ).</p>
      <p>FreeFem++ is written in C++ and the FreeFem++ language is a C++ idiom. It runs on Macs, Windows, Unix machines. FreeFem++ replaces the older freefem and freefem+.</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>FreeFem++ is a PDE (partial differential equation) solver based on a flexible language that allows a large number of problems to be expressed (elasticity, fluids, etc) with different finite element approximations on different meshes.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid45">
          <p noindent="true">Partner: UPMC</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid46">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Frédéric Hecht</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid47">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://www.freefem.org/ff++/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>freefem.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>ff++/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid48" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>HPDDM</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Scientific Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>HPDDM is an efficient implementation of various domain decomposition methods (DDM) such as one- and two-level Restricted Additive Schwarz methods, the Finite Element Tearing and Interconnecting (FETI) method, and the Balancing Domain Decomposition (BDD) method.
This code has been proven to be efficient for solving various elliptic problems such as scalar diffusion equations, the system of linear elasticity, but also frequency domain problems like the Helmholtz equation. A comparison with modern multigrid methods can be found in the thesis of Pierre Jolivet.</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>HPDDM is an efficient implementation of various domain decomposition methods (DDM) such as one- and two-level Restricted Additive Schwarz methods, the Finite Element Tearing and Interconnecting (FETI) method, and the Balancing Domain Decomposition (BDD) method.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid49">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Pierre Jolivet and Frédéric Nataf</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid50">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Pierre Jolivet</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid51">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/hpddm" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>hpddm</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid52" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>LORASC</bodyTitle>
      <p>LORASC preconditioner</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keyword:</span> Preconditioner</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid53">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Laura Grigori and Remi Lacroix</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid54">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Laura Grigori</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid55">
          <p noindent="true">URL: not available</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid56" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>NFF</bodyTitle>
      <p>NFF Nested Filtering Factorization</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Preconditioner - Interactive method - Linear system</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid57">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Laura Grigori, Frédéric Nataf and Long Qu</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid58">
          <p noindent="true">Partners: Université Paris-Sud - UPMC</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid59">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Laura Grigori</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid60">
          <p noindent="true">URL: not available</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid61" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>SparseToolbox</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Preconditioner - Interactive method - Linear system</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid62">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Laura Grigori and Remi Lacroix</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid63">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Laura Grigori</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid64">
          <p noindent="true">URL: not available</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </logiciels>
  <resultats id="uid65">
    <bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid66" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Communication avoiding algorithms</bodyTitle>
      <p>Our group continues to work on algorithms for dense and sparse linear algebra operations that minimize communication. During this year we focused on communication avoiding iterative methods and designing algorithms for computing rank revealing and low rank approximations of dense and sparse matrices.</p>
      <p>In <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we discuss sparse matrix-matrix multiplication (or SpGEMM), which is an important operation
for many algorithms in scientific computing. In our previous work we have identified lower bounds on
communication for this operation, which is the limiting factor of SpGEMM. Even though 3D (or 2.5D) algorithms have been proposed and theoretically analyzed in the flat MPI model on Erdos–Renyi matrices, those algorithms had not been implemented in practice and their complexities had not been analyzed for the general case. In this work, we present the first implementation of the 3D SpGEMM formulation that exploits multiple (intranode and internode) levels of parallelism, achieving significant speedups over the state-of-the-art publicly available codes at all levels of concurrencies. We extensively evaluate our implementation and identify bottlenecks that should be subject to further research.</p>
      <p>In <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> we discuss algorithms that not only aim at minimizing communication, but they also aim at reducing the number of writes to secondary storage. Most of the prior work does not distinguish between loads and stores,
i.e., between reads and writes to a particular memory unit. But in
fact there are some current and emerging nonvolatile memory
technologies (NVM) where writes can be much more
expensive (in time and energy) than reads. NVM technologies are being
considered for scientific applications on extreme scale computers and for cluster computing platforms, in addition to commodity computers.</p>
      <p>This motivates us to first refine prior work on communication lower bounds of algorithms which did not distinguish between loads and
stores to derive new lower bounds on writes to different levels of a memory hierarchy. When these
new lower bounds on writes are asymptotically smaller than the
previous bounds on the total number of loads and stores, we ask
whether there are algorithms that attain them. We call such
algorithms, that both minimize the total number of loads and stores
(i.e., are CA), and also do asymptotically fewer writes than reads,
<i>write-avoiding (WA)</i>. In this paper, we identify several classes
of problems where either sequential or parallel WA algorithms exist,
or provably cannot.</p>
      <p>In <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> we introduce a new approach for reducing communication in Krylov subspace methods that consists of enlarging the Krylov subspace by a maximum of <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>t</mi></math></formula> vectors per iteration, based on the domain decomposition of the graph of <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>A</mi></math></formula>.We show in this paper that the enlarged Krylov projection subspace methods lead to faster convergence in terms of iterations and parallelizable algorithms with less communication, with respect to Krylov methods.</p>
      <p>In this paper we focus on Conjugate Gradient (CG), a Krylov projection method for symmetric (Hermitian) positive definite matrices.
We discuss two new versions of Conjugate Gradient. The first method, multiple search direction with orthogonalization CG (MSDO-CG),
is an adapted version of MSD-CG with the A-orthonormalization of the search directions to obtain a projection method that guarentees
convergence at least as fast as CG. The second projection method that we propose here, long recurrence enlarged CG (LRE-CG), is similar
to GMRES in that we build an orthonormal basis for the enlarged Krylov subspace rather than finding search directions. Then, we use the
whole basis to update the solution and the residual. We compare the convergence behavior of both methods using different A-orthonormalization
and orthonormalization methods and then we compare the most stable versions with CG and other related methods. Both methods converge
faster than CG in terms of iterations, but LRE-CG converges faster than MSDO-CG since it uses the whole basis to update the solution rather
than only <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>t</mi></math></formula> search directions. And the more subdomains are introduced or the larger <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>t</mi></math></formula> is, the faster is the convergence of both methods
with respect to CG in terms of iterations. For example, for <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>t</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>64</mn></mrow></math></formula> the MSDO-CG and LRE-CG methods converge in <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mn>75</mn><mo>%</mo></mrow></math></formula> up to 98 less iteration
with respect to CG for the different test matrices.</p>
      <p>In <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> we present an algorithm for computing a low rank
approximation of a sparse matrix based on a truncated LU factorization
with column and row permutations. We present various approaches for
determining the column and row permutations that show a trade-off
between speed versus deterministic/probabilistic accuracy. We show
that if the permutations are chosen by using tournament pivoting based
on QR factorization, then the obtained truncated LU factorization with
column/row tournament pivoting, LU_CRTP, satisfies bounds on the
singular values which have similarities with the ones obtained by a
communication avoiding rank revealing QR factorization. Experiments
on challenging matrices show that LU_CRTP provides a good low rank
approximation of the input matrix and it is less expensive than the
rank revealing QR factorization in terms of computational and memory
usage costs, while also minimizing the communication cost. We also
compare the computational complexity of our algorithm with randomized
algorithms and show that for sparse matrices and high enough but still
modest accuracies, our approach is faster.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid67" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Integral equation based domain decomposition</bodyTitle>
      <p>We kept on studying the convergence of classical domain decomposition strategies applied to multi-trace formulations (MTF).
In the contribution <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we present a gentle introduction to multi-trace formalism aimed at the domain decomposition community
as well as analytical calculations in simple geometrical configuration where a full analysis of block-Jacoobi applied to MTF is
possible. We only consider transmission problems in 1D with one or two interfaces. In <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we generalize this analysis to
arbitrary 2D or 3D transmission problems with arbitrary subdomain partitionning, only assuming that there is no junction point.
The analysis holds mainly for completely homogeneous media with no material constrast, and in such a case we determine the
spectrum of the multi-trace operator, as well as the spectrum of the Jacobi operator. We show that this spectrum only consists
in a finite number of point values. In the more general case where the propagation medium is piecewise constant, this analysis
still yields the location of the essential spectrum of the MTF and the Jacobi operator.</p>
      <p>This analysis also led to an explicit expression for the inverse of the MTF operators for transmission problems in the case of
perfectly homogeneous media. This was studied during the intership of Alan Ayala, and was described and tested numerically in
3D in the proceedings.</p>
      <p>The analysis presented in <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> also shows that, in the case of purely homogeneous media, a block Jacobi strategy converges in a number
of steps that exactly corresponds to the depth of the adjacency graph of the subdomain partition under consideration, which suggests
a close relationship with Optimized Schwarz Methods (OSM), following the ideas of <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. We investigated this point during the internship
of Pierre Marchand, and we exhibited fully explicitely the exact relationship between block-Jacobi-MTF and OSM. Besides, we also
generalized the analysis presented in <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> to the case of a competely heterogeneous problem, which involves abstract boundary integral
operators that are not easily computable.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid68" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Multi-subdomain integral equations</bodyTitle>
      <p>In the context of boundary integral equations adapted to wave scattering
in piecewise constant media in harmonic regime, we also made
significant progress in the study of the single trace boundary integral
formulation (STF) of the second kind originally introduced in
<ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
This work was achieved in collaboration with Ralf Hiptmair and Elke
Spindler (ETH Zürich). First of all, we proposed a version of this
formulation for the solution to Maxwell's equations whereas, so far, it
had been studied only in the context of scalar wave scattering
(Helmholtz equation). In this direction, we conducted numerical
experiments which confirmed the attractive properties of the matrices
obtained when discretising such formulations (good accuracy, and good
conditionning independent of discretisation parameters). For Maxwell's
equations, we also established elementary theoretical results of STF 2nd
kind such as Fredholmness of the corresponding integral operator.</p>
      <p>So far, second kind STF had been stuudied for wave scatering problems
where material contrasts only enter in the compact part of the
partial differential operator, which is harmless regarding the
Fredholmness of the corresponding boundary integral operator. Thus, in
<ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>,
we investigated the case where material contrasts come into play in the
principal part of the operator, considering a pure
diffusion-transmission problem. In this case, we have been able to
establish well-posedness (hence Fredholmness). A rather naive approach
leads to choose Sobolev spaces of fractionnal order (half-integer) as
main functional setting for this formulation. We showed that this
formulation
can be extended so as to make sense in the space of square integrable
trace functions. This is much more handy a functional setting that
allows in particular discontinuous Galerkin discretisations of the
corresponding boundary integral equations.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid69" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Asymptotics for a semi-linear convex problem with small inclusion</bodyTitle>
      <p>In <ref xlink:href="#alpines-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, in collaboration with Lucas Chesnel (Inria Defi) and Sergei Nazarov (Saint-Petersbourg University),
we recently investigated the asymptotics of the solution to a semi-linear problem in 2D with Dirichlet boundary condition.
The partial differential operator under consideration was <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mo>-</mo><mi>Δ</mi><mi>u</mi><mo>+</mo><msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi>u</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>p</mi><mo>+</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></msup></mrow></math></formula> where <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>p</mi></math></formula> is a positive integer.
The computational domain is assumed to contain a small Dirichlet
obstacle of size <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo>&gt;</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow></math></formula>. Using the method of matched
asymptotic expansions, we compute an asymptotic expansion of the
solution as <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>δ</mi></math></formula> tends to zero. Its relevance was justified
by proving a rigorous error estimate. Then we construct an approximate
model, based on an equation set in the limit domain without
the small obstacle, which provides a good approximation of the far
field of the solution of the original problem. The interest of
this approximate model lies in the fact that it leads to a variational
formulation which is very simple to discretize. We obtained
numerical experiments to illustrate the analysis.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid70" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Time-dependent wave splitting and source separation</bodyTitle>
      <p>Starting from classical absorbing boundary conditions, we (M. Grote, M. Kray, F. Nataf and F. Assous) propose a method for the separation of time-dependent scattered wave fields due to multiple sources or obstacles. More precisely, we propose a method to determine the separate outgoing components of the incident and scattered wave fields for time-dependent scattering problems. In the case of two superposed wave fields, our method applies to the following three typical configurations: two distinct localized sources with unknown time history each, a single (unknown) localized source with a nearby scatterer, or two separate scatterers illuminated by a known incident wave field. In all three cases, our method permits to recover the individual outgoing components from measurements of the total scattered field at a distance. In doing so, the particular nature of the scatterer, be it an im- penetrable well-defined obstacle or a penetrable localized inhomogeneity, is immaterial; only the purely outgoing character of the individual wave fields matters.
In contrast to previous work, our approach is local in space and time, deterministic, and also avoids any a priori assumptions on the frequency spectrum of the signal. Numerical simulations in FreeFem++ in two space dimensions illustrate the usefulness of wave splitting for time-dependent scattering problems. This work was presented to several international conferences and was published in J. Comput. Phys. (2016).
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid71" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>SORAS GenEO-2</bodyTitle>
      <p>Optimized Schwarz methods (OSM) are very popular methods which were introduced by P.L. Lions (1989) for elliptic problems and by B. Després (1990) for propagative wave phenomena. We (R. Haferssas, P. Jolivet and F. Nataf) give here a theory for Lions' algorithm that is the genuine counterpart of the theory developed over the years for the Schwarz algorithm. The first step is to introduce a new symmetric variant of the ORAS (Optimized Restricted Additive Schwarz) algorithm that is suitable for the analysis of a two-level method. Then we build a coarse space for which the convergence rate of the two-level method is guaranteed regardless of the regularity of the coefficients. We show scalability results for thousands of cores for nearly incompressible elasticity and the Stokes systems with a continuous discretization of the pressure.
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid72" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Numerical modeling and high speed parallel computing: new
perspectives for tomographic microwave imaging for brain stroke
detection and monitoring</bodyTitle>
      <p>These works deals with microwave tomography for brain stroke imaging using state-of-the-art numerical modeling and massively parallel computing. Iterative microwave tomographic imaging requires the solution of an inverse problem based on a minimization algorithm (e.g. gradient based) with successive solutions of a direct problem such as the accurate modeling of a whole-microwave measurement system. Moreover, a sufficiently high number of unknowns is required to accurately represent the solution. As the system will be used for detecting the brain stroke (ischemic or hemorrhagic) as well as for monitoring during the treatment, running times for the reconstructions should be reasonable. The method used is based on high-order finite elements, parallel preconditioners from the Domain Decomposition method and Domain Specific Language with open source FreeFem++ solver. This work, for which we got the Joseph Fourier-Bull prize, is supported by ANR grant MEDIMAX (ANR-13-MONU-0012) and was granted access to the HPC resources of TGCC@CEA under the allocations 2016-067519 and 2016- 067730 made by GENCI.
</p>
    </subsection>
  </resultats>
  <contrats id="uid73">
    <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid74" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <descriptionlist>
        <li id="uid75">
          <p noindent="true">Contract with Total, February 2015 - February 2018, that funds the PhD thesis of Hussam Al Daas on enlarged Krylov subspace methods for oil reservoir and seismic imaging applications. Supervisor L. Grigori.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid76">
          <p noindent="true">Contract with IFPen, February 2016 - February 2019, that funds the Phd thesis of Zakariae Jorti on adaptive preconditioners using a posteriori error estimators. Supervisor L. Grigori.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid77">
          <p noindent="true">Contract with IFPen, October 2016 - October 2019, that funds the Phd thesis of Julien Coulet on the virtual element method (VEM). Supervisor F. Nataf and V. Girault.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid78">
          <p noindent="true">Contract with MentorGraphics, March 2016, that funds the internship of T. Freiman on circuit simulations. Supervisor F. Nataf.</p>
        </li>
      </descriptionlist>
    </subsection>
  </contrats>
  <partenariat id="uid79">
    <bodyTitle>Partnerships and Cooperations</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid80" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>National Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid81" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ANR</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid82" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Medimax</bodyTitle>
          <p>ANR-MN (Modèles Numériques) October 2013 - September 2017</p>
          <p>The main goal is the methodological and numerical development of a new robust inversion tool, associated with the numerical solution
of the electromagnetic forward problem, including the benchmarking of different other existing approaches (Time Reverse Absorbing Condition,
Method of Small-Volume Expansions, Level Set Method). This project involves the development of a general parallel open source simulation code,
based on the high-level integrated development environment of FreeFem++, for modeling an electromagnetic direct problem, the scattering of
arbitrary electromagnetic waves in highly heterogeneous media, over a wide frequency range in the microwave domain. The first applications
considered here will be medical applications: microwave tomographic images of brain stroke, brain injuries, from both synthetic and experimental
data in collaboration with EMTensor GmbH, Vienna (Austria), an Electromagnetic Medical Imaging company.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid83" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>ANR Cine-Para</bodyTitle>
          <p>October 2015 - September 2019, Laura Grigori is
Principal Coordinator for Inria Paris. Funding for Inria Paris is
145 Keuros. The funding for Inria is to combine Krylov subspace
methods with parallel in time methods. Partners: University Pierre
and Marie Curie, J. L. Lions Laboratory (PI Y. Maday), CEA, Paris
Dauphine University, Paris 13 University.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid84" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Non-local DD</bodyTitle>
          <p>ANR appel à projet générique October 2015 - September 2020</p>
          <p>This project in scientific computing aims at developing new domain decomposition methods for massively parallel simulation of electromagnetic waves
in harmonic regime. The specificity of the approach that we propose lies in the use of integral operators not only for solutions local to each subdomain,
but for coupling subdomains as well. The novelty of this project consists, on the one hand, in exploiting multi-trace formalism for domain
decomposition and, on the other hand, considering optimized Schwarz methods relying on Robin type transmission conditions involving quasi-local
integral operators.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid85" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Soil<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>μ</mi></math></formula>-3D</bodyTitle>
          <p>ANR appel à projet générique October 2015 - September 2020</p>
          <p>In spite of decades of work on the modeling of greenhouse gas emission such as CO2 and N2O and on the feedback effects of temperature and water content on soil carbon and nitrogen transformations, there is no agreement on how these processes should be described, and models are widely conflicting in their predictions. Models need improvements to obtain more accurate and robust predictions), especially in the context of climate change, which will affect soil moisture regime.</p>
          <p>The goal of this new project is now to go further using the models developed in MEPSOM to upscale heterogeneities identified at the scale of microbial habitats and to produce macroscopic factors for biogeochemical models running at the field scale.</p>
          <p>To achieve this aim, it will be necessary to work at different scales: the micro-scale of pores (μm) where the microbial habitats are localized, the meso-scale of cores at which laboratory measurements on CO2 and N2O fluxes can be performed, and the macro-scale of the soil profile at which outputs are expected to predict greenhouse gas emission. The aims of the project are to (i) develop new descriptors of the micro-scale 3D soil architecture that explain the fluxes measured at the macro-scale, (ii) Improve the performance of our 3D pore scale models to simulate both micro-and meso- scales at the same time. Upscaling methods like “homogeneization” would help to simulate centimeter samples which cannot be achieved now. The reduction of the computational time used to solve the diffusion equations and increase the number of computational units, (iii) develop new macro-functions describing the soil micro-heterogeneity and integrate these features into the field scale models.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid86" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>European Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid87" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>FP7 &amp; H2020 Projects</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid88" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>NLAFET</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid89">
              <p noindent="true">Title: Parallel Numerical Linear Algebra for Future Extreme-Scale Systems</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid90">
              <p noindent="true">Programm: H2020</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid91">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: November 2015 - November 2018</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid92">
              <p noindent="true">Coordinator: UMEÅUniversitet</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid93">
              <p noindent="true">Partners:</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid94">
                  <p noindent="true">Science and Technology Facilities Council (United Kingdom)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid95">
                  <p noindent="true">Computer Science Department, UmeåUniversitet (Sweden)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid96">
                  <p noindent="true">Mathematics Department, The University of Manchester (United Kingdom)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid97">
              <p noindent="true">Inria contact: Laura Grigori</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid98">
              <p noindent="true">The NLAFET proposal is a direct response to the demands for new mathematical and algorithmic approaches for applications on extreme scale systems, as identified in the FETHPC work programme and call. This project will enable a radical improvement in the performance and scalability of a wide range of real-world applications relying on linear algebra software, by developing novel architecture-aware algorithms and software libraries, and the supporting runtime capabilities to achieve scalable performance and resilience on heterogeneous architectures. The focus is on a critical set of fundamental linear algebra operations including direct and iterative solvers for dense and sparse linear systems of equations and eigenvalue problems. Achieving this requires a co-design effort due to the characteristics and overwhelming complexity and immense scale of such systems. Recognized experts in algorithm design and theory, parallelism, and auto-tuning will work together to explore and negotiate the necessary tradeoffs. The main research objectives are: (i) development of novel algorithms that expose as much parallelism as possible, exploit heterogeneity, avoid communication bottlenecks, respond to escalating fault rates, and help meet emerging power constraints; (ii) exploration of advanced scheduling strategies and runtime systems focusing on the extreme scale and strong scalability in multi/many-core and hybrid environments; (iii) design and evaluation of novel strategies and software support for both offline and online auto-tuning. The validation and dissemination of results will be done by integrating new software solutions into challenging scientific applications in materials science, power systems, study of energy solutions, and data analysis in astrophysics. The deliverables also include a sustainable set of methods and tools for cross-cutting issues such as scheduling, auto-tuning, and algorithm-based fault tolerance packaged into open-source library modules.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid99" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>EXA2CT</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid100">
              <p noindent="true">Title: EXascale Algorithms and Advanced Computational Techniques</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid101">
              <p noindent="true">Programm: FP7</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid102">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: September 2013 - August 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid103">
              <p noindent="true">Coordinator: IMEC</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid104">
              <p noindent="true">Partners:</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid105">
                  <p noindent="true">Fraunhofer-Gesellschaft Zur Foerderung Der Angewandten Forschung E.V (Germany)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid106">
                  <p noindent="true">Interuniversitair Micro-Electronica Centrum Vzw (Belgium)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid107">
                  <p noindent="true">Intel Corporations (France)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid108">
                  <p noindent="true">Numerical Algorithms Group Ltd (United Kingdom)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid109">
                  <p noindent="true">T-Systems Solutions for Research (Germany)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid110">
                  <p noindent="true">Universiteit Antwerpen (Belgium)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid111">
                  <p noindent="true">Universita della Svizzera italiana (Switzerland)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid112">
                  <p noindent="true">Université de Versailles Saint-Quentin-En-Yvelines. (France)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid113">
                  <p noindent="true">Vysoka Skola Banska - Technicka Univerzita Ostrava (Czech Republic)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid114">
              <p noindent="true">Inria contact: Luc Giraud</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid115">
              <p noindent="true">Numerical simulation is a crucial part of science and industry in Europe. The advancement of simulation as a discipline relies on increasingly compute intensive models that require more computational resources to run. This is the driver for the evolution to exascale. Due to limits in the increase in single processor performance, exascale machines will rely on massive parallelism on and off chip, with a complex hierarchy of resources. The large number of components and the machine complexity introduce severe problems for reliability and programmability. The former of these will require novel fault-aware algorithms and support software. In addition, the scale of the numerical models exacerbates the difficulties by making the use of more complex simulation algorithms necessary, for numerical stability reasons. A key example of this is increased reliance on solvers. Such solvers require global communication, which impacts scalability, and are often used with preconditioners, increasing complexity again. Unless there is a major rethink of the design of solver algorithms, their components and software structure, a large class of important numerical simulations will not scale beyond petascale. This in turn will hold back the development of European science and industry which will fail to reap the benefits from exascale. The EXA2CT project brings together experts at the cutting edge of the development of solvers, related algorithmic techniques, and HPC software architects for programming models and communication. It will take a revolutionary approach to exascale solvers and programming models, rather than the incremental approach of other projects. We will produce modular open source proto-applications that demonstrate the algorithms and programming techniques developed in the project, to help boot-strap the creation of genuine exascale codes.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid116" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid117" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria International Partners</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid118" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Informal International Partners</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid119">
              <p noindent="true">J. Demmel, UC Berkeley, USA</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid120">
              <p noindent="true">R. Hipmair, ETH Zurich</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid121">
              <p noindent="true">M. Grote (Université de Bâle, Suisse)</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid122">
              <p noindent="true">F. Assous (Israel)</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid123" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Research Visitors</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid124" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits to International Teams</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid125" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Research Stays Abroad</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid126">
              <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori has spent 5 months at UC Berkeley, from January 2016 to May 2016, as a visiting Professor/Researcher.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </partenariat>
  <diffusion id="uid127">
    <bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid128" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Promoting Scientific Activities</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid129" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Organisation</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid130" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>General Chair, Scientific Chair</bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid131">
              <p noindent="true">SIAM Conference on Parallel Processing and Scientific
Computing 2016 <ref xlink:href="http://www.siam.org/meetings/pp16/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>siam.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>meetings/<allowbreak/>pp16/</ref>, Paris. Co-chairs L. Grigori and R. Vuduc. The team Alpines as well as other members of Inria Paris and UPMC, were in charge of the local organization of this conference. There were a record number of 500 participants, 88 minisymposia sessions and 44 contributed talks.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid132">
              <p noindent="true">Frederic Hecht: Organizing the 8th FreeFem++ days (December 2016, Paris)</p>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid133" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Organizing Committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid134">
              <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Member of Program Committee of IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium, IPDPS 2016.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid135">
              <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Member of Program Committee of HiPC 2016, IEEE Int'l Conference on High Performance Computing.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid136">
              <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Member of Program Committee of IEEE Cluster 2016.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid137">
              <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Member of Organizing Committee of 5th SIAM Workshop on
Combinatorial Scientific Computing (CSC) 2016.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid138" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Journal</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid139" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Editorial Boards</bodyTitle>
          <subsection id="uid140" level="4">
            <bodyTitle>Laura Grigori</bodyTitle>
            <descriptionlist>
              <li id="uid141">
                <p noindent="true">March 2014 – current. Member of the editorial board for the SIAM book series Software,
Environments and Tools. See
<ref xlink:href="http://bookstore.siam.org/software-environments-and-tools/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>bookstore.<allowbreak/>siam.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>software-environments-and-tools/</ref>.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid142">
                <p noindent="true">June 2013 – current. Area editor for Parallel Computing
Journal, Elsevier</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid143">
                <p noindent="true">January 2016 – current. Associate Editor, SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid144">
                <p noindent="true">January 2016 – current. Editorial board, Numerical linear algebra with applications
Journal, Wiley.</p>
              </li>
            </descriptionlist>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="uid145" level="4">
            <bodyTitle>Frédéric Nataf</bodyTitle>
            <descriptionlist>
              <li id="uid146">
                <p noindent="true">2014 – current. Associate Editor, Journal of Numerical Mathematics, de Gruyter.</p>
              </li>
            </descriptionlist>
          </subsection>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid147" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Invited Talks</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid148">
            <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Invited plenary speaker, Fifth IMA Conference on Numerical
Linear Algebra and Optimization, Birmingham, (<ref xlink:href="http://www.ima.org.uk/conferences/conferences_calendar/5th_ima_conference_on_numerical_linear_algebra_and_optimisation.cfm.html" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>ima.<allowbreak/>org.<allowbreak/>uk/<allowbreak/>conferences/<allowbreak/>conferences_calendar/<allowbreak/>5th_ima_conference_on_numerical_linear_algebra_and_optimisation.<allowbreak/>cfm.<allowbreak/>html</ref>, September 7-9, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid149">
            <p noindent="true">Frederic Hecht: tutorial with FreeFem++, CEMRACS 2016 CIRM, Luminy, Marseille, july 18-22, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid150">
            <p noindent="true">Frederic Hecht: Graduate Course: An introduction to scientific computing using free software FreeFem++ , The Fields Institute for Research in Mathematical Sciences , Toronto, Canada , 7-17 March . 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid151">
            <p noindent="true">Frederic Nataf: tutorial on Domain Decomposition Methods, CEMRACS 2016 CIRM, Luminy, Marseille, july 18-22, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid152">
            <p noindent="true">Frederic Nataf: Invited plenary speaker, Franco-Scottish Seminar 2016:
Linear Algebra and Parallel Computing at the Heart of Scientific Computing.
21 September 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid153" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Leadership within the Scientific Community</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid154">
            <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Chair of the SIAM SIAG on Supercomputing (SIAM
special interest group on supercomputing), January 2016 - December
2017. Nominated by a Committee and elected by the members of this
SIAG.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid155">
            <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Member of the PRACE (Partnership for Advanced Computing in Europe, <ref xlink:href="http://www.prace-ri.eu/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>prace-ri.<allowbreak/>eu/</ref>) Scientific Steering Committee, September 2016 - current.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid156">
            <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: Steering committee member, Challenge 7: Information and
communication society, ANR (Comité de Pilotage , Défi 7), since
November 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid157" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Expertise</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid158">
            <p noindent="true">Laura Grigori: November 2015 - current, expert to the Scientific Commission of
IFPEN (French Petroleum Institute). Evaluation of research
programs, PhD theses, work representing a total of 5 days per year.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid159">
            <p noindent="true">Xavier Claeys: Member of the hiring committee for the position of maître de conférence 26 MCF 4346 at Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1, Spring 2016</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid160" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Research Administration</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid161" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Xavier Claeys</bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid162">
              <p noindent="true">Correspondent of the Association pour les Mathématiques en Interactions avec les Entreprises
et la Société (AMIES) for Laboratoire Jacques-Louis Lions</p>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid163" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Laura Grigori</bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid164">
              <p noindent="true">Member of the Director Committee (Comité Directeur) of GIS
Geosciences franciliennes, since November 2015.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid165">
              <p noindent="true">Member (nominated by Inria) of the Scientific Committee of the
Mathematics Department of UPMC</p>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid166" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Frédéric Hecht </bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid167">
              <p noindent="true">Assistant Director of Fédération de Recherche en Mathématiques de Paris Centre, Fédération de Recherche en Mathématiques de Paris Centre, Since 2010</p>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid168" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Teaching - Supervision - Juries</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid169" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Teaching</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid170" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Xavier Claeys</bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid171">
              <p noindent="true">Academic year 2015-2016, total number of course hours: 192 hrs</p>
              <simplelist>
                <li id="uid172">
                  <p noindent="true">Licence 1: Calculus, 12hrs, UPMC</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid173">
                  <p noindent="true">Licence 2: Orientation and Professional Insertion, 40 hrs, UPMC</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid174">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 1: Basic computing, 72 hrs of practical works in C++, UPMC</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid175">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 1: Scientific computing, 44 hrs of lectures, UPMC</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid176">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 2: Solving PDEs by using finite element methods, 18 hrs of practical works in C++, UPMC</p>
                </li>
              </simplelist>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid177" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Laura Grigori</bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid178">
              <p noindent="true">Spring 2016, UC Berkeley: Co-teaching a class with J. Demmel on
Communication Avoiding Algorithms
<ref xlink:href="https://who.rocq.inria.fr/Laura.Grigori/TeachingDocs/CS-294_Spr2016/CS-294_CA_Spr2016.html" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>who.<allowbreak/>rocq.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>Laura.<allowbreak/>Grigori/<allowbreak/>TeachingDocs/<allowbreak/>CS-294_Spr2016/<allowbreak/>CS-294_CA_Spr2016.<allowbreak/>html</ref>. The
class is available for mathematics students as a <i>Hot Topics
Course in Mathematics</i>, and for Computer Science students as a
<i>Special Topics</i> class. It was mainly designed for graduate
students.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid179">
              <p noindent="true">4-hour lecture at the XVII Jacques-Louis Lions Spanish-French School on Numerical Simulation in Physics and Engineering, June 2016, Gijon, Spain.</p>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid180" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Frédéric Hecht</bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid181">
              <p noindent="true">Academic year 2015-2016, total number of course hours: 192 hrs</p>
              <simplelist>
                <li id="uid182">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 1: Initiation au C++, 24hrs, M1, Université Pierre-et-Marie Curie Paris 6, France</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid183">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 2: Des EDP à leur résolution par la méthode des éléments finis (MEF), 24hrs, M2, Université Pierre-et-Marie Curie Paris 6, France</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid184">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 2: Numerical methods for fluid mechanics, 10hrs, M2, Université Pierre-et-Marie Curie Paris 6, France</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid185">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 2: Calcul scientifique 3 / projet industriel FreeFem++, 28hrs, M2, Université Pierre-et-Marie Curie Paris 6, France</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid186">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 2: Ingénierie 1 / Logiciel pour la simulation (FreeFem++), 21hrs, M2, Université Pierre-et-Marie Curie Paris 6, France</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid187">
                  <p noindent="true">Master 2: Ingénierie 2 / Projet collaboratif, 21hrs, M2, Université Pierre-et-Marie Curie Paris 6, France</p>
                </li>
              </simplelist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid188">
              <p noindent="true">CEMRACS 2016 : Calcul scientifique à haute performance, 3h course on Tutorial with FreeFem++. The slides are available on F. Hecht website, and videos can be
found here
<ref xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NQy2kZQGBbg" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>youtube.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>watch?v=NQy2kZQGBbg</ref>.</p>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid189" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Frédéric Nataf</bodyTitle>
          <descriptionlist>
            <li id="uid190">
              <p noindent="true">CEMRACS 2016 : Calcul scientifique à haute performance, 3h course on Domain decomposition methods The slides are available on F. Nataf's website, videos can be
found here
<ref xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=10672&amp;v=t-rgIFcN6w4" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>youtube.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>watch?time_continue=10672&amp;v=t-rgIFcN6w4</ref>.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid191">
              <p noindent="true">Spring 2016: Course on <i>Domain Decomposition Methods</i>, Master 2nd year
Mathematics &amp; Applications, University Pierre and Marie Curie</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid192">
              <p noindent="true">Winter 2016: Course on <i>Domain Decomposition Methods</i>, Master 2nd year,
Mathematics &amp; Applications, ENSTA and UVSQ</p>
            </li>
          </descriptionlist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid193" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Supervision</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid194">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Alan Ayala, since October 2015 (funded by NLAFET H2020 project), co-advisors Xavier Claeys and Laura Grigori.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid195">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress : Sebastien Cayrols, since October 2013 (funded by Maison de la simulation), adivsor Laura Grigori.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid196">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Hussam Al Daas, since February 2015 (funded by contract with Total), advisor Laura Grigori.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid197">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Olivier Tissot, since October 2015 (funded by NLAFET H2020 project), advisor Laura Grigori.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid198">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Pierre Marchand, since October 2016 (funded by ANR NonLocalDD project), advisors Xavier Claeys et Frédéric Nataf.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid199">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Zakariae Jorti, since February 2016 (funded by IFPen), advisor Laura Grigori.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid200">
            <p noindent="true">PhD : Ryadh Haferssas, defended december 2016 (funded by Ecole Doctorale, UPMC), advisor F. Nataf</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid201">
            <p noindent="true">PhD : Mireille El-HAddad, defended december 2016(t UPMC), advisors F. Hecht and T. Sayah.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid202">
            <p noindent="true">HDR: X. CLAEYS, Boundary integral equations of time harmonic wave scattering at complex structures,
Accreditation to supervise research, (UPMC Paris 6), February 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid203" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Popularization</bodyTitle>
      <descriptionlist>
        <li id="uid204">
          <p noindent="true">2 Conferences on being a mathematicien: <b>Applied Mathematics, Research...</b>,
in the high school Viollet le Duc - Villiers-Saint-Frédéric, France for 200 high school students in 11th and 12th grade, april 2016.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid205">
          <p noindent="true">Part of the teaching duty of Xavier Claeys (around 70 hours total) has been dedicated to "orientation and
insertion professionnelle". This has consisted in familiarizing young students (2nd year bachelor) with
potential curricula, professionnal activities and networks related to mathematics.</p>
        </li>
      </descriptionlist>
    </subsection>
  </diffusion>
  <biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" numero="10" titre="Bibliography">
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid18" type="hdrthesis" rend="year" n="cite:claeys:tel-01357729">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="tel-01357729"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Boundary integral equations of time harmonic wave scattering at complex structures</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>Xavier</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Université Pierre et Marie Curie (UPMC Paris 6)</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.upmc.fr/tel-01357729" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>upmc.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>tel-01357729</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Habilitation à diriger des recherches</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid0" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:azad:hal-01426294">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01426294"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Exploiting Multiple Levels of Parallelism in Sparse Matrix-Matrix Multiplication</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>ariful</foreName>
            <surname>azad</surname>
            <initial>a.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Grey</foreName>
            <surname>Ballard</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Aydin</foreName>
            <surname>Buluc</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>James W.</foreName>
            <surname>Demmel</surname>
            <initial>J. W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm28288">
            <foreName>Laura</foreName>
            <surname>Grigori</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Oded</foreName>
            <surname>Schwartz</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sivan</foreName>
            <surname>Toledo</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01736">
        <idno type="issn">0895-4798</idno>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">38</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">27</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01426294" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01426294</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid13" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:bajc:hal-01360423">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.jcp.2016.02.072"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01360423"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A mesh adaptivity scheme on the Landau–de Gennes functional minimization case in 3D, and its driving efficiency</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Iztok</foreName>
            <surname>Bajc</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm26800">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Hecht</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Slobodan</foreName>
            <surname>Žumer</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01098">
        <idno type="issn">0021-9991</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Computational Physics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">321</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">981–996</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.upmc.fr/hal-01360423" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>upmc.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01360423</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid11" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:chesnel:hal-01109552">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01109552"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A numerical approach for the Poisson equation in a planar domain with a small inclusion</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="defi-2014-idp71760">
            <foreName>Lucas</foreName>
            <surname>Chesnel</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>Xavier</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00211">
        <idno type="issn">0006-3835</idno>
        <title level="j">BIT Numerical Mathematics</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01109552" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01109552</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid16" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:claeys:hal-01120422">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01120422"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Asymptotics of the eigenvalues of the Dirichlet-Laplace problem in a domain with thin tube excluded</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>Xavier</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01649">
        <idno type="issn">0033-569X</idno>
        <title level="j">Quarterly of Applied Mathematics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">74</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">595-605</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01120422" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01120422</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid5" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:claeys:hal-01251212">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01251212"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Essential spectrum of local multi-trace boundary integral operators</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>Xavier</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00781">
        <idno type="issn">0272-4960</idno>
        <title level="j">IMA Journal of Applied Mathematics</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01251212" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01251212</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid19" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:claeys:hal-01251236">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00020-015-2242-5"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01251236"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Integral Equations for Electromagnetic Scattering at Multi-Screens</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>Xavier</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ralf</foreName>
            <surname>Hiptmair</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00828">
        <idno type="issn">0378-620X</idno>
        <title level="j">Integral Equations and Operator Theory</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">84</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">36</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01251236" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01251236</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid2" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:grigori:hal-01357899">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1137/140989492"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01357899"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Enlarged Krylov Subspace Conjugate Gradient Methods for Reducing Communication</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm28288">
            <foreName>Laura</foreName>
            <surname>Grigori</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp77688">
            <foreName>Sophie</foreName>
            <surname>Moufawad</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp65112">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Nataf</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01736">
        <idno type="issn">0895-4798</idno>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">37</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">744–773</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01357899" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01357899</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid14" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:grote:hal-01216117">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01216117"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Time-dependent wave splitting and source separation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Marcus J.</foreName>
            <surname>Grote</surname>
            <initial>M. J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Marie</foreName>
            <surname>Kray</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp65112">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Nataf</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Franck</foreName>
            <surname>Assous</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01098">
        <idno type="issn">0021-9991</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Computational Physics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">330</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2017</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">981–996</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01216117" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01216117</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid1" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:erin:hal-01248678">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01248678"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Write-Avoiding Algorithms</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Carson</foreName>
            <surname>Erin</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>James W.</foreName>
            <surname>Demmel</surname>
            <initial>J. W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm28288">
            <foreName>Laura</foreName>
            <surname>Grigori</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Knight</foreName>
            <surname>Nick</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Koanantakool</foreName>
            <surname>Penporn</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Oded</foreName>
            <surname>Schwartz</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vardhan</foreName>
            <surname>Harsha</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE International Parallel &amp; Distributed Processing Symposium, IPDPS 2016</title>
        <loc>Chicago, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01248678" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01248678</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid87817">
          <title>IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium</title>
          <num>30</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IPDPS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">Short version of the technical report available at http://www.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2015/EECS-2015-163.pdf as Technical Report No. UCB/EECS-2015-163</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid17" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:jolivet:hal-01357998">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01357998"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Block Iterative Methods and Recycling for Improved Scalability of Linear Solvers</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp76456">
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Jolivet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp68864">
            <foreName>Pierre-Henri</foreName>
            <surname>Tournier</surname>
            <initial>P.-H.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">SC16 - International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis</title>
        <loc>Salt Lake City, Utah, United States</loc>
        <title level="s">Proceedings of SC16: International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01357998" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01357998</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid107949">
          <title>International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid3" type="techreport" rend="year" n="cite:grigori:hal-01313856">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01313856"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Low rank approximation of a sparse matrix based on LU factorization with column and row tournament pivoting</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm28288">
            <foreName>Laura</foreName>
            <surname>Grigori</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp73952">
            <foreName>Sebastien</foreName>
            <surname>Cayrols</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>James W.</foreName>
            <surname>Demmel</surname>
            <initial>J. W.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">RR-8910</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">inria</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">35</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01313856" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01313856</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Research Report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid12" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:dib:hal-01416505">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416505"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Finite element method for Darcy's problem coupled with the heat equation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Séréna</foreName>
            <surname>Dib</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Toni</foreName>
            <surname>Sayah</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vivette</foreName>
            <surname>Girault</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Murat</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christine</foreName>
            <surname>Bernardi</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm26800">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Hecht</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.upmc.fr/hal-01416505" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>upmc.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416505</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid15" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:elhaddad:hal-01217940">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01217940"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Interface transport scheme of a two-phase flow by the method of characteristics</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mireille</foreName>
            <surname>El-Haddad</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm26800">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Hecht</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Toni</foreName>
            <surname>Sayah</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.upmc.fr/hal-01217940" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>upmc.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01217940</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid10" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:vergez:hal-01277660">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01277660"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">A finite-element toolbox for the stationary Gross-Pitaevskii equation with rotation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Guillaume</foreName>
            <surname>Vergez</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ionut</foreName>
            <surname>Danaila</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sylvain</foreName>
            <surname>Auliac</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idm26800">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Hecht</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.upmc.fr/hal-01277660" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>upmc.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01277660</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid9" type="unpublished" rend="foot" n="footcite:ClaeysChesnelNonLinear">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Small obstacle asymptotics for a 2D semi-linear convex problem</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="defi-2014-idp71760">
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Chesnel</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>X.</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint/>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">accepted in Applicable Analysis, Oct. 2016.</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid7" type="techreport" rend="foot" n="footcite:C11_144">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">A single trace integral formulation of the second kind for acoustic scattering</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>X.</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">2011-14</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Seminar for Applied Mathematics, ETH Zürich<address><addrLine>Switzerland</addrLine></address></orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://www.sam.math.ethz.ch/sam_reports/reports_final/reports2011/2011-14.pdf" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>sam.<allowbreak/>math.<allowbreak/>ethz.<allowbreak/>ch/<allowbreak/>sam_reports/<allowbreak/>reports_final/<allowbreak/>reports2011/<allowbreak/>2011-14.<allowbreak/>pdf</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Technical report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid4" type="unpublished" rend="foot" n="footcite:claeys:hal-01207193">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01207193"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">An introduction to Multitrace Formulations and Associated Domain Decomposition Solvers</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>Xavier</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Victorita</foreName>
            <surname>Dolean</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Martin J.</foreName>
            <surname>Gander</surname>
            <initial>M. J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01207193" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01207193</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid8" type="techreport" rend="foot" n="footcite:CHS16_681">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Second Kind Boundary Integral Equation for Multi-Subdomain Diffusion Problems</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp66352">
            <foreName>X.</foreName>
            <surname>Claeys</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Hiptmair</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>E.</foreName>
            <surname>Spindler</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">2016-44</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Seminar for Applied Mathematics, ETH Zürich<address><addrLine>Switzerland</addrLine></address></orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://www.sam.math.ethz.ch/sam_reports/reports_final/reports2016/2016-44.pdf" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>sam.<allowbreak/>math.<allowbreak/>ethz.<allowbreak/>ch/<allowbreak/>sam_reports/<allowbreak/>reports_final/<allowbreak/>reports2016/<allowbreak/>2016-44.<allowbreak/>pdf</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Technical report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="alpines-2016-bid6" type="techreport" rend="foot" n="footcite:NatafRogierSturler">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Optimal interface conditions for domain decomposition methods</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="alpines-2014-idp65112">
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Nataf</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Rogier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>E.</foreName>
            <surname>de Sturler</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">CMAP, Ecole Polytechnique</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1994</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Technical report</note>
    </biblStruct>
  </biblio>
</raweb>
