<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2016">
  <identification id="coast" isproject="true">
    <shortname>COAST</shortname>
    <projectName>Web Scale Trustworthy Collaborative Service Systems</projectName>
    <theme-de-recherche>Distributed Systems and middleware</theme-de-recherche>
    <domaine-de-recherche>Networks, Systems and Services, Distributed Computing</domaine-de-recherche>
    <urlTeam>http://team.inria.fr/coast</urlTeam>
    <structure_exterieure type="Labs">
      <libelle>Laboratoire lorrain de recherche en informatique et ses applications (LORIA)</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>CNRS</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>Université de Lorraine</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <header_dates_team>Creation of the Team: 2014 July 01, updated into Project-Team: 2015 July 01</header_dates_team>
    <LeTypeProjet>Project-Team</LeTypeProjet>
    <keywordsSdN>
      <term>1.1.6. - Cloud</term>
      <term>1.1.7. - Peer to peer</term>
      <term>1.3. - Distributed Systems</term>
      <term>2.5.1. - Software Architecture &amp; Design</term>
      <term>2.6.2. - Middleware</term>
      <term>3.1.3. - Distributed data</term>
      <term>3.1.5. - Control access, privacy</term>
      <term>5.1.1. - Engineering of interactive systems</term>
      <term>5.1.2. - Evaluation of interactive systems</term>
      <term>7.1. - Parallel and distributed algorithms</term>
    </keywordsSdN>
    <keywordsSecteurs>
      <term>6.1.1. - Software engineering</term>
      <term>6.3.1. - Web</term>
      <term>6.5. - Information systems</term>
      <term>8.4. - Security and personal assistance</term>
      <term>8.4.1. - Crisis management</term>
      <term>9.1.1. - E-learning, MOOC</term>
      <term>9.5.1. - Psychology</term>
      <term>9.6. - Reproducibility</term>
      <term>9.8. - Privacy</term>
    </keywordsSecteurs>
    <UR name="Nancy"/>
  </identification>
  <team id="uid1">
    <person key="coast-2014-idm30768">
      <firstname>François</firstname>
      <lastname>Charoy</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Univ. Lorraine, Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2015-idm27216">
      <firstname>Claudia-Lavinia</firstname>
      <lastname>Ignat</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idm28040">
      <firstname>Khalid</firstname>
      <lastname>Benali</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idm26592">
      <firstname>Gérôme</firstname>
      <lastname>Canals</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp65304">
      <firstname>Claude</firstname>
      <lastname>Godart</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp66744">
      <firstname>Gérald</firstname>
      <lastname>Oster</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp68008">
      <firstname>Olivier</firstname>
      <lastname>Perrin</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp69448">
      <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
      <lastname>Urso</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp70704">
      <firstname>Samir</firstname>
      <lastname>Youcef</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="carte-2016-idp160160">
      <firstname>Jean-Philippe</firstname>
      <lastname>Eisenbarth</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, from Nov 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="algorille-2014-idp112960">
      <firstname>Phillippe</firstname>
      <lastname>Kalitine</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="algorille-2014-idp116736">
      <firstname>Matthieu</firstname>
      <lastname>Nicolas</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp75664">
      <firstname>Amina</firstname>
      <lastname>Ahmed Nacer</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Bejaia</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp79360">
      <firstname>Ahmed</firstname>
      <lastname>Bouchami</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp80584">
      <firstname>Quang Vinh</firstname>
      <lastname>Dang</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maia-2014-idp96584">
      <firstname>Victorien</firstname>
      <lastname>Elvinger</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp81824">
      <firstname>Elio</firstname>
      <lastname>Goettelmann</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>CRP Henri Tudor, until Jan 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2016-idp153072">
      <firstname>Abir</firstname>
      <lastname>Ismaili-Alaoui</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, from Sep 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2016-idp155520">
      <firstname>Quentin</firstname>
      <lastname>Laporte Chabasse</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, from Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp83048">
      <firstname>Jordi</firstname>
      <lastname>Martori Adrian</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2015-idp83728">
      <firstname>Hoai Le</firstname>
      <lastname>Nguyen</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2015-idp84968">
      <firstname>Hoang Long</firstname>
      <lastname>Nguyen</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp78120">
      <firstname>Luc</firstname>
      <lastname>André</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, until May 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2014-idp84272">
      <firstname>Guillaume</firstname>
      <lastname>Rosinosky</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Bonitasoft, granted by CIFRE</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2016-idp170208">
      <firstname>Mohammed Riyadh</firstname>
      <lastname>Abdmeziem</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, from Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2016-idp172688">
      <firstname>Kahina</firstname>
      <lastname>Bessai Ep. Youcef</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine,</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2016-idp175152">
      <firstname>Marc</firstname>
      <lastname>Delpech</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Internship, from Jun 2016 until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2016-idp177664">
      <firstname>Thomas</firstname>
      <lastname>Le Saux</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Internship, from Jun 2016 until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="coast-2016-idp180176">
      <firstname>Bruno</firstname>
      <lastname>Sinteff</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Internship, from May 2016 until Jul 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp99584">
      <firstname>Sophie</firstname>
      <lastname>Drouot</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="carte-2014-idp103352">
      <firstname>Delphine</firstname>
      <lastname>Hubert</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="carte-2014-idp104592">
      <firstname>Martine</firstname>
      <lastname>Kuhlmann</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>CNRS</moreinfo>
    </person>
  </team>
  <presentation id="uid2">
    <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid3" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
      <p>The advent of the Cloud, of smart mobile
devices and of service-based architecture has opened a field of possibilities
wide as the invention of the Web 25 years ago. Software companies now deliver
applications and services using the Web as a platform. From text to video editing, from data analytics to process management,
they distribute business applications to users within their web browser
or on some mobile appliance <footnote id="uid4" id-text="1">See
<ref xlink:href="http://blog.programmableweb.com/2011/09/16/open-api-growth-a-visualization/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>blog.<allowbreak/>programmableweb.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>2011/<allowbreak/>09/<allowbreak/>16/<allowbreak/>open-api-growth-a-visualization/</ref></footnote>.
These services are
deployed on sophisticated infrastructures that can cope
with very demanding loads. The Software as a Service approach (SaaS) highlights their cooperative nature, by enabling the storage of data in cloud infrastructures that can be easily shared among users.
Thus, clients consume applications through service API (web services),
available on delivery platforms, called stores or markets.
This approach of the distribution of software outstrips the
traditional software distribution channels, in both scale and opportunity. Scale has different dimensions : the number of users (communities rather than groups), the size of data produced
and managed (billions of documents), the number of services and of
organizations (tens of thousands). Opportunity refers to the infinite number
of combinations between these services and the many ways to consume and use them.</p>
      <p>This fast-paced evolution challenges research because the creation of applications from the
composition of services must incorporate new content and context based constraints.
From a socio-technical perspective, the behaviour of users is
evolving constantly as they get acculturated to new services and ways to cooperate. Mere enhancement of current
existing solutions to cope with these challenges is likely insufficient. We conduct a
dedicated research effort to tackle the problems arising from the
evolution of contemporary technologies and of those we can anticipate.</p>
      <p>For this purpose, we explore three directions: large scale collaborative data
management, data centred service composition and above all, a foundation for the construction of trustworthy collaborative systems.</p>
      <p><b>Large scale collaborative data management</b> concerns mostly the problem of allowing people to collaborate on shared data, synchronously or not, on a central server or on a peer to peer network. Although this research has a long history referring back to <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, new challenges arise regarding needs that are occurring with the acculturation of users to collaboration like the number of participants to a collaboration (a crowd), sharing among different organisations and the nature of documents that are shared and produced. The problem here is to design new algorithms and to evaluate them under different usage conditions and constraints and for different kinds of data.</p>
      <p><b>Data centred service composition</b> deals with the challenge of creating applications by composing services from different providers. Service composition has been studied for some time now but the technical evolution and the growing availability of public API oblige us to reconsider the problem  <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Our goal here is, taking into account this evolution, like the advent of the Cloud, the availability at a large scale of public API based on the REST <footnote id="uid5" id-text="2">representational state transfer</footnote> architectural style, to design models, methods and tools to help developers to compose these services in a safe and effective way.</p>
      <p>Based on the work that we do in the two first topics, our main research direction aims at providing support to build <b>trustworthy collaborative applications</b> based on the knowledge that we can gather from the underlying algorithms, from the composition of services and from the quality of services that can be deduced and monitored. The complexity of the context in which applications are executed does not allow to provide proven guarantees. Our goal is to base our work on a contractual and monitored approach to provide users with confidence in the service they use. It is very surprising to see to what extent people rely today on services with very little knowledge about the amount of confidence they put in these services. As soon as these services are based on composition of other unknown services, it becomes very difficult to understand the consequences of the failure of a component of the composition for instance.</p>
      <p>We follow a path that portrays a ruptured continuum, to underscore both the endurance of the common questions along with the challenge of accommodating a new scale. We regard collaborative systems as a combination of
supportive services, encompassing safe data
management and data sharing. Trustworthy data centred services are an essential support for collaboration at the scale of communities and organisations. We see there that we aim at combining our results and expertise to achieve a new leap forward toward the understanding and the mastering of methods and techniques that allow the engineering and the use of large scale collaborative systems.</p>
    </subsection>
  </presentation>
  <fondements id="uid6">
    <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid7" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Introduction</bodyTitle>
      <p>Our scientific foundations are grounded on distributed collaborative systems supported by sophisticated data sharing mechanisms and on service oriented computing with an emphasis on orchestration and on non-functional properties.</p>
      <p>Distributed collaborative systems enable distributed group work supported by computer technologies. Designing such systems requires an expertise in Distributed Systems and in Computer-supported collaborative Work research area. Besides theoretical and technical aspects of distributed systems, the design of distributed collaborative systems must take into account the human factor to offer solutions suitable for users and groups.
The Coast team vision is to move away from a centralized authority based collaboration towards a decentralized collaboration where users have full control over their data that they can store locally and decide with whom to share them. The Coast team investigates the issues related to the management of distributed shared data and coordination between users and groups.</p>
      <p>Service oriented Computing  <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> is an established domain on which the ECOO, Score and now the Coast teams have been contributing for a long time. It refers to the general discipline that studies the development of computer applications on the web.
A service is an independent software program with a specific functional context and capabilities published as a service contract (or more traditionally an API). A service composition aggregates a set of services and coordinates their interactions. The scale, the autonomy of services, the heterogeneity and some design principles underlying Service Oriented Computing open new research questions that are at the basis of our research. They span the disciplines of <b>distributed computing</b>, <b>software engineering</b> and <b>computer supported collaborative work</b> (CSCW).
Our approach to contribute to the general vision of Service Oriented Computing and more generally to the emerging discipline of Service Science has been and is still to focus on the issue of the efficient and flexible construction of reliable and secure high level services through the coordination/orchestration/composition of other services provided by distributed organizations or people.
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid8" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Consistency Models for Distributed Collaborative Systems</bodyTitle>
      <p>Collaborative systems are distributed systems that allow users to
share data. One important issue is to manage consistency of shared
data according to concurrent access. Traditional consistency criteria
such as serializability, linearizability are not adequate for
collaborative systems.</p>
      <p>Causality, Convergence and Intention preservation
(CCI) <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> are more suitable for developing middleware
for collaborative applications.</p>
      <p>We develop algorithms for ensuring CCI properties on collaborative
distributed systems. Constraints on the algorithms are different
according to the kind of distributed system and to the data structure. The
distributed system can be centralized, decentralized or
peer-to-peer. The type of data can include strings, growable
arrays, ordered trees, semantic graphs and multimedia data.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid9" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Optimistic Replication</bodyTitle>
      <p>Replication of data among different nodes of a network allows
improving reliability, fault-tolerance, and availability. When
data are mutable, consistency among the different replicas must be
ensured. Pessimistic replication is based on the principle of
single-copy consistency while optimistic replication allows the
replicas to diverge during a short time period. The consistency model
for optimistic replication <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> is called
eventual consistency, meaning that replicas are guaranteed to converge
to the same value when the system is idle.</p>
      <p>Our research focuses on the two most promising families of optimistic
replication algorithms for ensuring CCI:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid10">
          <p noindent="true">the operational transformation (OT) algorithms
<ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid11">
          <p noindent="true">the algorithms based on commutative replicated data types (CRDT)
<ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p>Operational transformation algorithms are based on the application of
a transformation function when a remote modification is integrated
into the local document. Integration algorithms are generic, being
parametrized by operational transformation functions which depend on
replicated document types. The advantage of these algorithms is their
genericity. These algorithms can be applied to any data type and they
can merge heterogeneous data in a uniform manner.</p>
      <p>Commutative replicated data types is a new class of algorithms
initiated by <span class="smallcap" align="left">woot</span> <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> a first algorithm designed WithOut Operational Transformations. They ensure
consistency of highly dynamic content on peer-to-peer networks. Unlike
traditional optimistic replication algorithms, they can ensure
consistency without concurrency control. CRDT algorithms rely on
natively commutative operations defined on abstract data types such as
lists or ordered trees. Thus, they do not require a merge algorithm or
an integration procedure.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid12" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Process Orchestration and Management</bodyTitle>
      <p>Process Orchestration and Management is considered as a core discipline behind Service Management and Computing. It includes the analysis, the modelling, the execution, the monitoring and the continuous improvement of enterprise processes and is for us a central domain of studies.</p>
      <p>Much efforts have been devoted in the past years to establish standard business process models founded on well grounded theories (e.g. Petri Nets) that meet the needs of both business analysts but also of software engineers and software integrators. This has lead to heated debate in the BPM community as the two points of view are very difficult to reconcile. On one side, the business people in general require models that are easy to use and understand and that can be quickly adapted to exceptional situations. On the other side, IT people need models with an operational semantic in order to be able transform them into executable artefacts. Part of our work has been an attempt to reconcile these point of views. It resulted in the development of the Bonita Business process management system and more recently on our work in crisis management where the same people are designing, executing and monitoring the process as it executes. But more generally, and at a larger scale, we have been considering the problem of processes spanning the barriers of organisations and thus more general problem of service composition as a way to coordinate inter organisational construction of applications providing value based on the composition of lower level services <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid13" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Service Composition</bodyTitle>
      <p>We are considering processes as pieces of software whose execution traverse the boundaries of organisations. This is especially true with service oriented computing where processes compose services produced by many organisations. We tackle this problem from very different perspectives, trying to find the best compromise between the need for privacy of internal processes from organisations and the necessity to publicize large part of them, proposing to distribute the execution and the orchestration of processes among the organisations themselves, and attempting to ensure non-functional properties in this distributed setting  <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      <p>Non-functional aspects of service composition relate to all the properties and service agreements that one wants to ensure and that are orthogonal to the actual business but that are important when a service is selected and integrated in a composition. This includes transactional context, security, privacy, and quality of service in general.
Defining and orchestrating services on a large scale while providing the stakeholders with some strong guarantees on their execution is a first class problem for us. For a long time, we have proposed models and solutions to ensure that some properties (e.g. transactional properties) were guaranteed on process execution, either through design or through the definition of some protocols. Our work has also been extended to the problems of security, privacy and service level agreement among partners. These questions are still central in our work.
One major problem of current approaches is to monitor the execution of the compositions, integrating the distributed dimension. This problem can be tackled using event-based algorithms and techniques. Using our event oriented composition framework DISC, we have obtained new results dedicated to the runtime verification of violations in service choreographies. </p>
    </subsection>
  </fondements>
  <logiciels id="uid14">
    <bodyTitle>New Software and Platforms</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid15" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>MUTE</bodyTitle>
      <p>Multi-User Text Editor</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>MUTE (Multi-User Text Editor) is a web-based text editing tool that allows users to edit documents collaboratively in real-time. It implements our recent work on collaborative editing algorithms and more specifically the LogootSplit+ approach. Compared to existing web-based collaborative text editing tool this editor does not require a powerful central server since the server is not performing any computation and acts as a simple broadcast server. Our editor offers support for working offline while still being able to reconnect at a later time.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid16">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Gérald Oster, François Charoy, Claudia-Lavinia Ignat, Phillippe Kalitine, Matthieu Nicolas and Victorien Elvinger</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid17">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Gérald Oster</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid18">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/coast-team/mute/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>coast-team/<allowbreak/>mute/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid19" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>NetFlux</bodyTitle>
      <p>Peer-to-Peer Network Library over WebRTC</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>NetFlux is a Nodejs library that allows users to deploy a peer-to-peer network between web browsers using the WebRTC technology.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid20">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Gérald Oster, Phillippe Kalitine, Matthieu Nicolas.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid21">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Gérald Oster</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid22">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/coast-team/netflux" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>coast-team/<allowbreak/>netflux</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid23" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>MUTE-structs</bodyTitle>
      <p>Peer-to-Peer Network Library over WebRTC</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>MUTE-structs is a Nodejs module that provides an implementation of the LogootSplit CRDT algorithm. It is an optimistic replication algorithm that ensures eventual consistency on replicated text sequences. It is used in the MUTE real-time collaborative text editor.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid24">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Gérald Oster, Claudia-Lavinia Ignat, Phillippe Kalitine, Matthieu Nicolas and Victorien Elvinger</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid25">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Gérald Oster</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid26">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/coast-team/mute-structs" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>coast-team/<allowbreak/>mute-structs</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid27" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Replication Benchmarker</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>The Replication Benchmarker is a performance evaluation framework for optimistic replication mechanisms used in collaborative applications. It contains a library of implementation of several CRDT (Commutative Replicated Data Type) and OT (Operational Transformation) algorithms for different data types: text, set, trees. The framework is able to evaluate the performance of comparable algorithms on different corpus of event traces. These event traces can be produced randomly according to different parameters, can be extracted from actual real-time editing session that have been recorded, or can be automatically extracted from distributed version control repositories such as the one produced with Git. Performances of the algorithms are measured in terms of execution time, memory footprint and quality of merge result (compared to manual merge history stored in git repositories).</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid28">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Pascal Urso and Gérald Oster</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid29">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Pascal Urso</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid30">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/score-team/replication-benchmarker/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>score-team/<allowbreak/>replication-benchmarker/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid31" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Rivage</bodyTitle>
      <p>Real-tIme Vector grAphic Group Editor</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>Rivage is a real-time collaborative graphical editor. Several users can edit at the same time and in real-time a graphical document, user changes being immediately seen by the other users. The editor relies on a peer-to-peer architecture where users can join and leave the group at any time. Each user has a copy of the shared document and user changes on the document copies are merged in real-time by using a CRDT (Commutative Replicated Data Type) algorithm.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid32">
          <p noindent="true">Participant: Claudia-Lavinia Ignat</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid33">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Claudia-Lavinia Ignat</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid34">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/stephanemartin/rivage/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>stephanemartin/<allowbreak/>rivage/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </logiciels>
  <resultats id="uid35">
    <bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid36" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Evaluation and Design of Consistency Maintenance Algorithms for Complex Data</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp78120">
          <firstname>Luc</firstname>
          <lastname>André</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp80584">
          <firstname>Quang Vinh</firstname>
          <lastname>Dang</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2015-idm27216">
          <firstname>Claudia-Lavinia</firstname>
          <lastname>Ignat</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp66744">
          <firstname>Gérald</firstname>
          <lastname>Oster</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp69448">
          <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
          <lastname>Urso</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>Since the Web 2.0 era, the Internet is a huge content
editing place on which users collaborate. Such shared content can be edited by thousands of
people. However, current consistency maintenance algorithms
seem not to be adapted to massive collaborative updating involving
large amounts of contributors and a high velocity of changes. This year
we continued our work on the evaluation of existing collaborative editing
approaches and on the design of new algorithms that overcome limitations of
state of the art ones. We designed new optimistic replication algorithms for maintaining
consistency for complex data such as wikis and strings and we evaluated existing algorithms
in large scale settings.</p>
      <p>Wikis are one of the most important tools of Web 2.0 allowing users to easily edit shared data. However, wikis offer limited support for merging concurrent contributions on the same pages. Users have to manually merge concurrent changes and there is no support for an automatic merging. Real-time collaborative editing reduces the number of conflicts as the time frame for concurrent work is very short. We proposed extending wiki systems with real-time collaboration and designed an automatic merging solution adapted for rich content wikis <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Our merging solution is based on an operational transformation approach for which we defined operations with high-level semantics capturing user intentions when editing wiki content such as move, merge and split. Our solution is the first one that deals with high level operations, existing approaches being limited to operations of insert, delete and update on textual documents.</p>
      <p>Over the last years we designed a CRDT-based consistency maintenance algorithm for strings  <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid10" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> for peer-to-peer large scale collaboration that is used by our MUTE collaborative editor which will be integrated in the virtual desktop of the OpenPaaS::NG project. This algorithm called LogootSplit can be seen as an extension for variable-sized elements (e.g. strings) of one of the first basic CRDT algorithms for unit elements (e.g. characters) proposed by our team called Logoot  <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Its principles are general and can be applied to other basic CRDT algorithms. This year we proposed another algorithm for strings based on the RGA algorithm <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      <p>By means of simulations we measured the delays in popular real-time collaborative editing systems such as GoogleDocs and Etherpad <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> in terms of the number of users that edit a shared document and their typing frequency. Delays exist between the execution of one user’s modification and the visibility of this modification
to the other users. Such delays are in part fundamental to the network, as well as arising
from the consistency maintenance algorithms and underlying architecture of collaborative
editors. Results of this study support our team assertion that
delay associated with conventional consistency maintenance algorithms will impede group performance.
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid37" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Probabilistic Partial Orderings</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp83048">
          <firstname>Jordi</firstname>
          <lastname>Martori Adrian</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp69448">
          <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
          <lastname>Urso</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>Ensuring reliable and ordered communication between computers usually
requires acknowledgment messages. In systems with a high rate of
broadcast communication, the cost of such acknowledgment messages can
be large. We propose to use the causal ordering information required
by some applications to detect and request missing messages. To
circumscribe the number of unnecessary requests we combine local
awareness and probabilistic methods. Our model allows us to obtain
reliable communication within a latency equivalent to unordered
communication and lower network usage than acknowledgment systems
<ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid38" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Computational Trust based on User Behavior</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp80584">
          <firstname>Quang Vinh</firstname>
          <lastname>Dang</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2015-idm27216">
          <firstname>Claudia-Lavinia</firstname>
          <lastname>Ignat</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>We continued our investigation on computing a trust score for each user according to their behaviour during a collaborative task. Previously we proposed a contract-based collaboration model <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid15" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> where trust in users is established and adjusted based on their compliance to the contracts specified by the data owners when they share the data.</p>
      <p>We continued this work by proposing an experimental design for testing the proposed trust-based collaboration model. We studied the trust game, a money exchange game that has been widely used in behavioural economics for studying trust and collaboration between humans. In this game, exchange of money is entirely attributable to the existence of trust between users. In the context of the trust game we proposed a trust metric that reflects user behaviours during the collaboration <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. This metric is robust against fluctuating user behaviour. Our trust metric is the first one that was proposed in the context of the trust game in order to predict user behaviour.</p>
      <p>In order to compute the trust score of users according to their contributions during a collaborative editing task, we need to evaluate the quality of the document content. As an initial work in this direction we investigated how to automatically assess the quality of Wikipedia articles in order to guide readers towards high quality articles and to suggest to authors which articles need to be improved.
In this context we proposed two automatic assessment methods of the quality of Wikipedia articles. In the first approach we introduced readability features for a better prediction of quality <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The second approach is based on a deep-learning mechanism that automatically learns features from document contents rather than manually defining them <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid19" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid39" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>A model to secure collaborative resources within Enterprise Social Networks</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp79360">
          <firstname>Ahmed</firstname>
          <lastname>Bouchami</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp68008">
          <firstname>Olivier</firstname>
          <lastname>Perrin</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>Enterprise social networks (ESN) are collaborative environments that raise major challenges to secure them. In his thesis <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid20" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, Ahmed Bouchami addressed the problem of authentication of digital identities within collaborative communities. He proposed an interoperable architecture for managing federated authentication, thus allowing each enterprise to preserve its (own) authentication mechanism and each principal to perform a single sign on authentication regarding different enterprises. He also proposed access control management. His flexible access control model is based on a set of identity attributes, and a formal language based on temporal logic. This model allows for checking the consistency of the policies defined. with the model.</p>
      <p>Last, the access control system offers the ability to control the user-centric sharing policies through policies based on a risk management mechanism, which makes the access control mechanism dynamic. The risk mechanism is based on the NIST’s risk definition with an alignment with a set of parameters that include access control in the ESN context. More precisely, the dynamic risk management includes, the collaborative resource’s importance, the authentication system’s vulnerabilities and trust level reflected through the behavior of each collaborative actor. On this latter aspect of trust, a reputation score is computed using the history of collaborative interactions of each subject of the collaborative environment. Finally, a prototype is available and was demonstrated within the OpenPaaS ESN project.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid40" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Risk management for the deployment of a business process in a multi-cloud context</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp75664">
          <firstname>Amina</firstname>
          <lastname>Ahmed Nacer</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp65304">
          <firstname>Claude</firstname>
          <lastname>Godart</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp81824">
          <firstname>Elio</firstname>
          <lastname>Goettelmann</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp70704">
          <firstname>Samir</firstname>
          <lastname>Youcef</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>The lack of trust in cloud organizations is often seen as obstacle to SaaS developments. This work proposes an approach which supports a trust model and a business process model in order to allow the orchestration of trusted business process components in the cloud.</p>
      <p>The contribution is threefold and consists in a method, a model and a framework. The method categorizes techniques to transform an existing business process into a risk-aware process model that takes into account security risks related to cloud environments. These techniques are partially described in the form of constraints to automatically support process transformation. The model formalizes the relations and the responsibilities between the different actors of the cloud. This allows
to identify the different information required to assess and quantify security risks in cloud environments.</p>
      <p>The framework is a comprehensive approach that decomposes a business process into fragments that can automatically be deployed on multiple clouds. The framework also integrates a selection algorithm that combines the security information of cloud offers and of the process with other quality of service criteria to generate an optimized configuration. It is implemented in a tool to assess cloud providers and decompose processes.</p>
      <p>Rooted in past years work, we are contributing this year at the methodological and framework levels in two directions:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid41">
          <p noindent="true">At the methodological level, while our risk computing model rested previously only on data provided by cloud providers (provider-side risk model), we are developing a risk model integrating client-side knowledge (client-side risk model).</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid42">
          <p noindent="true">At the framework level, we have integrated the ability to integrate fake BP fragments in the objective to increase the obfuscation of a deployed BP logic <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid21" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid43" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Cloud Provisioning for Elastic BPM</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="coast-2014-idm30768">
          <firstname>François</firstname>
          <lastname>Charoy</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp70704">
          <firstname>Samir</firstname>
          <lastname>Youcef</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="coast-2014-idp84272">
          <firstname>Guillaume</firstname>
          <lastname>Rosinosky</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>Even though the cloud computing paradigm has proven benefits, it faces a serious problem that can compromise its commercial success. It concerns the lack of an efficient approach for using optimally the available resources. For this, several approaches have been proposed <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid22" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. However, they suffer from several shortcomings. Often only one objective is taken into account, expressing all operations in terms of cost. Furthermore, business processes should be insured with elasticity and multi-tenancy mechanism while adjusting the available resources to the dynamic load distribution. We proposed to optimize two conflicting objectives, namely the number of migrations of tenants and the cost incurred using a set of resources. Our approach allows to take into account the multi-tenancy property and the Cloud computing elasticity, and is efficient as shown by an extensive experimentation based on real data from Bonita BPM customers <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid23" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In order to secure the scientific value of our findings we have set up a experimentation infrastructure for making repeatable experiments on the Cloud <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid44" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Orchestration of crowdsourcing activities</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="coast-2014-idm30768">
          <firstname>François</firstname>
          <lastname>Charoy</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="PASUSERID">
          <firstname>Kahina</firstname>
          <lastname>Bessai</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>Crowdsourcing is an important paradigm in human problem solving using the Web. When they face a workload outburst, businesses may choose to outsource some or all of their process tasks to the crowd in order to maintain the quality of service promised for their customers. This may occur in situations like crisis management, when organizations are overloaded by a sudden event breakout. These tasks are generally difficult to implement as solution based on software service only. So, the use of crowdsourcing platform seems enticing. To ensure efficient and wise use of resources, methods assisting decision making need to be developed whose aim is to assist businesses in choosing the most knowledgeable workers. We addressed the resource allocation problem in crisis context by defining a delegation approach based on crowdsourcing as resource provider. We introduce a mathematical model for business process execution in crowd-sourcing context and an exact optimization algorithm. As the problem addressed is NP-complete, we proposed a more efficient algorithm that we validated through simulation <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Furthermore, to overcome the limitations of existing works we take into account the fact that business process tasks are ordered while optimizing the overall execution time of a given business process instance under budget constraint. We used a synthetic crowd model or valitation. We have also defined a model to validate our work for geo-crowdsourcing activities <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid26" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
    </subsection>
  </resultats>
  <contrats id="uid45">
    <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid46" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid47" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Industrial funding Groupe Open (2016–2019)</bodyTitle>
        <p>Groupe Open is a leading french company specialised in digital services and operations. The goal of the project is to propose an industrial composition model for APIs that takes into account the new constraints imposed by this new way to distribute and operate software. It will be based on a formal API contract along with trust and reputation attributes in order to allow consumers to anticipate risks regarding the quality and the safety of services. A PhD student is under recruitment for this project.
Coast funding : 237,000 €</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid48" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid49" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>CIFRE Grant with Bonitasoft</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <firstname>François</firstname>
            <lastname>Charoy</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2014-idp70704">
            <firstname>Samir</firstname>
            <lastname>Youcef</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2014-idp84272">
            <firstname>Guillaume</firstname>
            <lastname>Rosinosky</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>Bonitasoft is a leading software company in the domain of open source
Business Process Management Systems. The objective of this grant is to
help Bonitasoft to support effective elastic BPM operation in the
Cloud by leveraging the business knowledge, the process models
and the execution history of process instances and correlate them with
cloud resource consumption. Guillaume Rosinosky has been recruited as
a PhD Student to work on this project. We will define models that will
be validated based on a detailed analysis of existing use cases that
we have started to collect from Bonitasoft and its clients.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </contrats>
  <partenariat id="uid50">
    <bodyTitle>Partnerships and Cooperations</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid51" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Regional Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid52" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Region Lorraine TV Paint (2016–2017)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <firstname>Claudia-Lavinia</firstname>
            <lastname>Ignat</lastname>
            <moreinfo>contact</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2014-idp66744">
            <firstname>Gérald</firstname>
            <lastname>Oster</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2014-idp80584">
            <firstname>Quang Vinh</firstname>
            <lastname>Dang</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="algorille-2014-idp116736">
            <firstname>Matthieu</firstname>
            <lastname>Nicolas</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <descriptionlist>
          <label>Partners:</label>
          <li id="uid53">
            <p noindent="true">TVPaint Development, Inria COAST project-team</p>
          </li>
          <label>Website:</label>
          <li id="uid54">
            <p noindent="true">
              <ref xlink:href="https://www.tvpaint.com/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>tvpaint.<allowbreak/>com/</ref>
            </p>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
        <p>This is a project in collaboration with TVPaint Development financed by Region Lorraine. The goal is to contribute to the creation of a collaborative system dedicated to animation movies, that allows to manipulate high quantities of digital artifacts in a collaborative way.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid55" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>National Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid56" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>OpenPaas NG (2015–2018)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <firstname>Claudia-Lavinia</firstname>
            <lastname>Ignat</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <firstname>François</firstname>
            <lastname>Charoy</lastname>
            <moreinfo>contact</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2014-idp66744">
            <firstname>Gérald</firstname>
            <lastname>Oster</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2014-idp68008">
            <firstname>Olivier</firstname>
            <lastname>Perrin</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="carte-2016-idp160160">
            <firstname>Jean-Philippe</firstname>
            <lastname>Eisenbarth</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="algorille-2014-idp112960">
            <firstname>Phillippe</firstname>
            <lastname>Kalitine</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="algorille-2014-idp116736">
            <firstname>Matthieu</firstname>
            <lastname>Nicolas</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2016-idp170208">
            <firstname>Mohammed Riyadh</firstname>
            <lastname>Abdmeziem</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Kahina</firstname>
            <lastname>Bessai</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maia-2014-idp96584">
            <firstname>Victorien</firstname>
            <lastname>Elvinger</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2016-idp155520">
            <firstname>Quentin</firstname>
            <lastname>Laporte Chabasse</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2015-idp83728">
            <firstname>Hoai Le</firstname>
            <lastname>Nguyen</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="coast-2015-idp84968">
            <firstname>Hoang Long</firstname>
            <lastname>Nguyen</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <descriptionlist>
          <label>Partners:</label>
          <li id="uid57">
            <p noindent="true">Linagora, XWiki SAS, Nexedi, COAST project-team (Université de Lorraine, LORIA), DaScim team (LIX).</p>
          </li>
          <label>Website:</label>
          <li id="uid58">
            <p noindent="true">
              <ref xlink:href="http://www.open-paas.org/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>open-paas.<allowbreak/>org/</ref>
            </p>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
        <p>This project is financed by BpiFrance and involves French industrial leaders in open-source software development (Linagora, Nexedi, XWiki)
and academic partners in collaborative work (COAST team) and
recommender systems (DaScim team, LIX). The goal of the project is to
develop next generation cloud enabled virtual desktop based on an
Enterprise Social Network to provide advanced collaborative
and recommendation services. COAST team is responsible of the work
package dedicated to the design of the peer-to-peer collaborative
middleware. In this context, we bring our expertise on data
replication for collaborative data in peer-to-peer environments and on
trust and access control and identity management in distributed
collaborative information systems.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid59" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria ADT PLM (2014-2016)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="coast-2014-idp66744">
            <firstname>Gérald</firstname>
            <lastname>Oster</lastname>
            <moreinfo>contact</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="algorille-2014-idp116736">
            <firstname>Matthieu</firstname>
            <lastname>Nicolas</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <descriptionlist>
          <label>Partners:</label>
          <li id="uid60">
            <p noindent="true">COAST project-team, MYRIADS project-team.</p>
          </li>
          <label>Website:</label>
          <li id="uid61">
            <p noindent="true">
              <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/BuggleInc/plm/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>BuggleInc/<allowbreak/>plm/</ref>
            </p>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
        <p>This work is performed jointly with Martin Quison (previously member of
project-team VERIDIS, now Professor at ENS Rennes).</p>
        <p>The Programmer's Learning Machine (PLM) is a software platform
dedicated to computer programming education. This generic platform
offers support to teachers for creating programming microworlds
suitable to teaching courses. It features an integrated and graphical
environment, providing a short feedback loop to students in order to
improve the effectiveness of the autonomous learning process.</p>
        <p>This project aims at establishing an experimental platform for
studying the teaching of basic programming and a research instrument
to design new collaborative learning environments.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid62" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>European Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid63" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>FP7 &amp; H2020 Projects</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid64" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>SyncFree (2013-2016)</bodyTitle>
          <participants>
            <person key="coast-2014-idp69448">
              <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
              <lastname>Urso</lastname>
              <moreinfo>contact</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="coast-2014-idp83048">
              <firstname>Jordi</firstname>
              <lastname>Martori Adrian</lastname>
            </person>
          </participants>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid65">
              <p noindent="true">Program: FP7-ICT-2013-10</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid66">
              <p noindent="true">Project acronym: SyncFree</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid67">
              <p noindent="true">Project title: Large-scale computation without synchronisation</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid68">
              <p noindent="true">Duration : October 2013 - September 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid69">
              <p noindent="true">Coordinator: Marc Shapiro, Inria</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid70">
              <p noindent="true">Other Partners: REGAL project-team (Inria Paris - Rocquencourt /
LIP6, coordinator), Basho Technologies Limited (United Kingdom),
Trifork AS (Denmark), Rovio Entertaiment OY (Finland), Faculdade de
Ciências e Tecnologia (Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Portugal),
Université Catholique de Louvain (Belgium), Ko c University
(Turkey), Technische Universität Kaiserslautern (Germany) and COAST
project-team.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid71">
              <p noindent="true">Large-scale on-line services including social networks
and multiplayer games handle huge quantities of frequently changing
shared data. Maintaining their consistency is relatively simple in a
centralised cloud, but no longer possible due to increased
scalability requirements. Instead, data must be replicated across
several distributed data centres, requiring new principled
approaches to consistency that have been explored by the SyncFree
project. <ref xlink:href="http://syncfree.lip6.fr/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>syncfree.<allowbreak/>lip6.<allowbreak/>fr/</ref></p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid72" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid73" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria Associate Teams Not Involved in an Inria International Labs</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid74" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>
            <ref xlink:href="http://uscoast.loria.fr" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">USCOAST2</ref>
          </bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid75">
              <p noindent="true">Title: User Studies on Trustworthy Collaborative Systems</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid76">
              <p noindent="true">International Partner (Institution - Laboratory - Researcher):</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid77">
                  <p noindent="true">Wright State University (United States)
- Department of Psychology, Knoesis - Valerie Shalin</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid78">
              <p noindent="true">Start year: 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid79">
              <p noindent="true">See also: <ref xlink:href="http://uscoast.loria.fr" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>uscoast.<allowbreak/>loria.<allowbreak/>fr</ref></p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid80">
              <p noindent="true">The proposed project addresses the perception of trust by users, the appropriateness of a trust-based security approach and the role of trust metrics in the management of distributed work. The main challenge of this project is how to measure trust based on user behaviour and to verify by means of experimental studies with users that the trust-based mechanism is acceptable by users. We plan to apply this trust-based mechanism for two types of applications. The first one is collaborative editing where user trust will be computed based on the quality of user contributions for a document or project. The second type of application is in the management of work over a large group of people in order to conduct efficient, high-yield, high-density real time crowdsourcing activities.</p>
              <p>Partners of USCOAST2 project have complementary expertise. Coast provides expertise in collaborative methods, systems and related technologies. Coast will propose algorithms that track and manipulate trust metrics. Kno.e.sis provides expertise on the analysis of human work-related behavior, including methods of data collection and data analysis, as well as a theoretical foundation for the evaluation of human performance. Knoesis will analyse trust from a psychological phenomenon point of view.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid81" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Research Visitors</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid82" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits to International Teams</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid83" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Research Stays Abroad</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid84">
              <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat visited the Department of Computer Science &amp; Knoesis, Wright State University for 1 month in the period June–July 2016 in the context of the associated team USCOAST2</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid85">
              <p noindent="true">Gérald Oster visited the Department of Computer Science &amp; Knoesis, Wright State University for 1 month in the period June–July 2016 in the context of the associated team USCOAST2</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </partenariat>
  <diffusion id="uid86">
    <bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid87" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Promoting Scientific Activities</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid88" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Organisation</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid89" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Organizing Committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid90">
              <p noindent="true">François Charoy was co-chair of the PhD Forum for ICSOC 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid91">
              <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat is in the organisation committee of The Fifteenth International Workshop on Collaborative Editing Systems in conjunction with CSCW 2017</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid92" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Selection</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid93" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the conference program committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid94">
              <p noindent="true">Claude Godart was PC member of the conference program committee of BPMDS (Business Process Modeling,
Development and Support), EDOC (The enterprise computing conference), ICSOC (International Conference on Services Oriented
Computing), IEEE CLOUD Computing, ICWS (IEEE International Conference on Web Services), SCC (IEEE International
Conference on Services Computing), S2 ICIOT (S2 International Conference on Internet of Things), IEEE/WIC/ACM WI
(Web Intelligence conference), WISE (Web Information Systems Engineering) conferences.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid95">
              <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat was PC member of CSCW
(International Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative
Work and Social Computing) 2016, CDVE (International
Conference on Cooperative Design, Visualization and
Engineering) 2016, ICEBE (International Conference on
e-Business Engineering) 2016 and The First IFIP Internet of People Workshop (IoP-W'16) in conjunction with Networking 2016 conference</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid96">
              <p noindent="true">Olivier Perrin was PC Member of ICSOC 2016, I3E 2016 (15th
IFIP Conference on e-Business, e-Services and e-Society), VECOS
2016 (10th International Workshop on Verification and Evaluation
of Computer and Communication Systems), and some workshops.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid97">
              <p noindent="true">François Charoy was PC Member of ICEBE (International
Conference on Business Engineering) 2016, CTS 2016
(International Symposium on Collaborative Technologies and
Systems), DG.O (International Conference on Digital Government
Research) 2016, IEEE WETICE 2016, ICSOC 2016, IEEE International Conference on Business
Information Systems and of several workshops.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid98">
              <p noindent="true">Khalid Benali was PC Member of WorldCIST’16 (World Conference on Information Systems and Technologies),
I-ESA’2016 (Interoperability of Enterprise Software and Applications),
AFIN 2016 (International Conference on Advances in Future Internet),
I3E 2016 (IFIP Conference on e-Business, e-Services and e-Society),
ICICS 2016 (7th International Conference on Information and Communication Systems),
MEDES 2016 (8th International Conference on Management of Digital EcoSystems),
SYSCO’16 (third international conference on collaborative systems) and
SoEA4EE‘2016 (The 8th Workshop on Service oriented Enterprise Architecture for Enterprise Engineering).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid99">
              <p noindent="true">Gérald Oster was a PC member of CoopIS 2016
(International Conference on Cooperative Information Systems).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid100" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Journal</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid101" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the editorial boards</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid102">
              <p noindent="true">Claude Godart is member of the editorial board of IEEE Transactions on Service Computing, International Journal of Services Computing, and member of the review board of the International Journal of Next Generation Computing.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid103">
              <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat is member of the editorial board of
Journal of CSCW (Computer Supported Cooperative Work).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid104">
              <p noindent="true">François Charoy is member of the editorial board of
Service Oriented Computing and Applications Journal
(Springer).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid105" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Reviewer - Reviewing activities</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid106">
              <p noindent="true">In 2016, Olivier Perrin reviewed papers for IEEE
Transactions on Services Computing journal, IEEE Transactions
on Parallel and Distributed Systems and Journal of Systems and Software.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid107">
              <p noindent="true">In 2016, Claudia-Lavinia Ignat reviewed papers for Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, World Wide Web Journal, CHI 2016 and CSCW 2017.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid108">
              <p noindent="true">In 2016, Gérald Oster reviewed papers for Computer Supported Cooperative Work Journal, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience journal and CSCW 2017.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid109" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Invited talks</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid110">
            <p noindent="true">François Charoy has been invited as a keynote Speaker at the
IEEE WETICE Conference in Paris <ref xlink:href="#coast-2016-bid27" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> on
Collaborative Networks and Crisis Management.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid111">
            <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat gave an invited lecture in May 2016 at SOAMED Graduate School in Berlin on Replicated Data Consistency</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid112">
            <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat gave an invited talk in June 2016 at the Department of Psychology, Wright State University,
on Large-scale trust-based collaboration</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid113">
            <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat gave an invited talk in July 2016 at the Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Ohio Center of Excellence in Knowledge-enabled Computing (Kno.e.sis), Wright State University on Large-scale trust-based collaboration</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid114">
            <p noindent="true">Gérald Oster gave an invited talk in July 2016 at the Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Ohio Center of Excellence in Knowledge-enabled Computing (Kno.e.sis), Wright State University on Distributed real-time collaborative editing</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid115" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Teaching - Supervision - Juries</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid116" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Teaching</bodyTitle>
        <p>Permanent members of the COAST project-team are leading teachers in
their respective institutions. They are responsible of lectures in
disciplines like software engineering, database systems, object
oriented programming and design, distributed systems, service
computing and more advanced topics at all levels and in different
of departments in the University. Most of the PhD Students have also
teaching duties in the same institutions. As a whole, the COAST team
accounts for more than 2500 hours of teaching. Members of the COAST
team are also deeply involved in the pedagogical and administrative
life of their departments.</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid117">
            <p noindent="true">Gérôme Canals was the head of the Computer science department of
the Nancy-Charlemagne University Institute of Technology (IUT Nancy Charlemagne) since September 2010 and until August 2016, and is responsible for the professional licence degree “Web application programming” since sept. 2001.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid118">
            <p noindent="true">Claude Godart is responsible for the Computer Science
department of the engineering school ESSTIN.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid119">
            <p noindent="true">Khalid Benali is responsible for the professional Master degree
speciality “Distributed Information Systems” of MIAGE and of its
international branch in Morocco.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid120">
            <p noindent="true">François Charoy is responsible of the Software Engineering
specialisation at the TELECOM Nancy Engineering School of University of Lorraine.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid121">
            <p noindent="true">Pascal Urso is responsible for the “Security, Services,
Systems and Network” track of the master degree in computer
science at University of Lorraine since September 2013.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid122" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Supervision</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid123">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Quang Vinh Dang, Trust-based large scale collaboration, started in 10/2014, Claudia-lavinia Ignat and François Charoy</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid124">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Hoai Le Nguyen, Study of group performance and behavior in collaborative editing, started in 9/2015, Claudia-Lavinia Ignat and François Charoy</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid125">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Hoang Long Nguyen, A Trust Based Authorization Model and Framework for the Cloud, started in 11/2015, Claudia-Lavinia Ignat and Olivier Perrin</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid126">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (defended): Luc André, Replication and Consistency Maintenance in Peer-to-Peer Collaborative Environment, started in 9/2011, François Charoy and Gérald Oster</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid127">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Victorien Elvinger, Secured Replication for Peer-to-Peer Collaborative Infrastructures, started in 10/2015, François Charoy and Gérald Oster</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid128">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (defended): Ahmed Bouchami , Sécurité des données collaboratives d'une plateforme PaaS, started in 11/2012, Olivier Perrin</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid129">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Jordi Martori i Adrian, Data constraints for large-scale collaboration, started in 10/2013, François Charoy and Pascal Urso</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid130">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Guillaume Rosinoski, Elastic BPM and the Cloud, started in 10/2014, François Charoy and Samir Youssef</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid131">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Quentin Laporte-Chabasse, Federation of Organisations over Peer to Peer Collaborative Network, started in 10/2016, François Charoy and Gérald Oster</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid132">
            <p noindent="true">PhD (in progress): Béatrice Linot, Trust in cooperative systems, Jérome Dinet et François Charoy, started 11/2016</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid133" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Juries</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid134">
            <p noindent="true">François Charoy was head of the Selection committee at TELECOM Nancy, Université de Lorraine</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p>COAST members were members of the following PhD and HdR defense committees:</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid135">
            <p noindent="true">Mondi Ravi, PhD, Université de Grenoble, January 2016 (François Charoy)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid136">
            <p noindent="true">Tomasz Buchert, PhD, Université de Lorraine, January 2016 (François Charoy)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid137">
            <p noindent="true">Luc André, PhD, Université de Lorraine, May 2016 (François Charoy and Gérald Oster)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid138">
            <p noindent="true">Adrian Shatte, PhD, James Cook University, Cairns, Australia, September 2016 (François Charoy)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid139">
            <p noindent="true">Wassim Derguech, PhD, National University of Ireland, Galway, Ireland, December 2016 (François Charoy)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid140">
            <p noindent="true">Philippe Dirix, PhD, Université de Lille, July 2016 (Khalid Benali)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid141">
            <p noindent="true">Bouchra El Idrissi, PhD, Université Mohammed V de Rabat, Maroc, September 2016 (Khalid Benali)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid142">
            <p noindent="true">Ghada Gharbi, PhD, Université de Toulouse 3, November 2016 (Claude Godart)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid143">
            <p noindent="true">Hind Benfenatki, PhD, Université de Lyon 1, December 2016 (Claude Godart)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid144">
            <p noindent="true">Brice Nedelec, PhD, Université de Nantes, October 2016 (Gérald Oster)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid145">
            <p noindent="true">Anthéa Mayzaud, PhD, Université de Lorraine, October 2016 (Olivier Perrin)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid146">
            <p noindent="true">Noran Azmy, PhD, Universität des Saarlandes and Université de Lorraine, November 2016 (Olivier Perrin)</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid147" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Popularization</bodyTitle>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid148">
          <p noindent="true">In March 2016 members of the team (François Charoy and Phillippe Kalitine) participated to the “Rencontres Université Entreprise” in Paris to demonstrate the collaborative editor MUTE (<ref xlink:href="http://www.rue-aef.com" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>rue-aef.<allowbreak/>com</ref>)</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid149">
          <p noindent="true">In January 2016 Claudia-Lavinia Ignat presented Coast research activities to the first year students at Ecole de Mines de Nancy</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid150">
          <p noindent="true">In May 2016 Claudia-Lavinia Ignat gave a lecture on Replicated Data Consistency at SOAMED Graduate School in Berlin</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid151">
          <p noindent="true">In May 2016 Claudia-Lavinia Ignat organised the meeting Research@Inria at Inria Nancy-Grand Est for presenting to internship students, PhD students and postdocs various Inria programs and the main research topics at Inria with a focus on activities of research teams at Inria Nancy-Grand Est. She also presented the main activities of a researcher and briefly described her research work.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid152">
          <p noindent="true">In November 2016 members of the team (François Charoy and Matthieu Nicolas) participated to the “Rencontre Inria-Industrie” (RII) on the topic - Interactions avec les objets et services numériques” in Lille to demonstrate MUTE collaborative editor</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid153">
          <p noindent="true">In December 2016 members of the team (Claudia-Lavinia Ignat, Gérald Oster, Matthieu Nicolas and Phillippe Kalitine) participated to the “Rencontre Inria-Industrie” (RII) on the topic - Nouvelles technologies pour la protection des données et des systèmes numériques” in Nancy to demonstrate collaborative editor MUTE</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid154">
          <p noindent="true">In December 2016 members of the team (Gérald Oster, Matthieu Nicolas and Phillippe Kalitine) demonstrated the collaborative editor MUTE during the visit of the Rectors of the Mexican Technological Universities at LORIA in the context of the bilateral MEXPROTEC program.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid155" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Institutional commitment</bodyTitle>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid156">
          <p noindent="true">Claudia-Lavinia Ignat is in charge of European affairs for
Inria Nancy Grand-Est. She is the Delegate of International
Relations for Inria Nancy-Grand Est and member of COST-GTRI commission. She is member of the Inria
Nancy-Grand Est COMIPERS committee. She participated to a working group in charge with the design of a booklet for industrials describing the technological offer of Inria Nancy-Grand Est (she was responsible for the part concerning Large-scale collaborative services and systems). She is responsible with the activity kindergarten at AGOS Inria Nancy-Grand Est.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </diffusion>
  <biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" numero="10" titre="Bibliography">
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid28" type="phdthesis" rend="year" n="cite:andre:tel-01362437">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="tel-01362437"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Intention Preservation and Consistency Maintenance for Real-Time Replicated Data</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp78120">
            <foreName>Luc</foreName>
            <surname>André</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Université de Lorraine (Nancy)</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-01362437" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>tel.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>tel-01362437</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Theses</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid20" type="phdthesis" rend="year" n="cite:bouchami:tel-01402629">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="tel-01402629"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Security of collaborative resources in enterprises social networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp79360">
            <foreName>Ahmed</foreName>
            <surname>Bouchami</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Université de lorraine</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-01402629" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>tel.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>tel-01402629</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Theses</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid30" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:boudjlida:hal-01253436">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01253436"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Conceptual Graphs for Fomally Managing and Discovering Complementary Competences</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nacer</foreName>
            <surname>Boudjlida</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Badrina</foreName>
            <surname>Gasmi Boumezoued</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01340">
        <title level="j">Springer LNAI</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01253436" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01253436</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid19" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:dang:hal-01393227">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/2996442.2996447"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01393227"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Quality Assessment of Wikipedia Articles: A Deep Learning Approach</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp80584">
            <foreName>Quang-Vinh</foreName>
            <surname>Dang</surname>
            <initial>Q.-V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <foreName>Claudia-Lavinia</foreName>
            <surname>Ignat</surname>
            <initial>C.-L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid03085">
        <idno type="issn">1931-1745</idno>
        <title level="j">ACM SIGWEB Newsletter (ACM Digital Library)</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01393227" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01393227</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid9" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:ignat:hal-01404024">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01404024"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Enhancing rich content wikis with real-time collaboration</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <foreName>Claudia-Lavinia</foreName>
            <surname>Ignat</surname>
            <initial>C.-L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp78120">
            <foreName>Luc</foreName>
            <surname>André</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp66744">
            <foreName>Gérald</foreName>
            <surname>Oster</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00435">
        <idno type="issn">1532-0626</idno>
        <title level="j">Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01404024" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01404024</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid25" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bessai:hal-01401246">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401246"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Business process tasks-assignment and resourceallocation in Crowdsourcing context</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idp87464">
            <foreName>Kahina</foreName>
            <surname>Bessai</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Charoy</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE International Conference on Collaboration and Internet Computing</title>
        <loc>Pittsburgh, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01401246" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401246</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625474">
          <title>IEEE International Conference on Collaboration and Internet Computing</title>
          <num>2</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CIC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid26" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bessai:hal-01356053">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01356053"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Optimization of Orchestration of Geocrowdsourcing Activities</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idp87464">
            <foreName>Kahina</foreName>
            <surname>Bessai</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Charoy</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Third International Conference on Information Systems for Crisis Response and Management in Mediterranean Countries (ISCRAM-med 2016)</title>
        <loc>Madrid, Spain</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Business Information Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01356053" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01356053</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid406029">
          <title>International Conference on Information Systems for Crisis Response and Management (ISCRAM)</title>
          <num>3</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISCRAM</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid12" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:briot:hal-01343941">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/2957276.2957300"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01343941"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">High Responsiveness for Group Editing CRDTs</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Loïck</foreName>
            <surname>Briot</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp69448">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Urso</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="regal-2014-idm26336">
            <foreName>Marc</foreName>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">ACM International Conference on Supporting Group Work</title>
        <loc>Sanibel Island, FL, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01343941" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01343941</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625473">
          <title>ACM International Conference on Supporting Group Work</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">GROUP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid27" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:charoy:hal-01342751">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01342751"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Keynote : From group collaboration to large scale social collaboration</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Charoy</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="yes" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">25th IEEE International Conference on Enabling Technologies: Infrastructure for Collaborative Enterprises (WETICE-2016)</title>
        <loc>Paris, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01342751" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01342751</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid91580">
          <title>IEEE International Workshop on Enabling Technologies: Infrastructures for Collaborative Enterprises</title>
          <num>25</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">WETICE</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid16" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:dang:hal-01351250">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01351250"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Computational Trust Model for Repeated Trust Games</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp80584">
            <foreName>Quang-Vinh</foreName>
            <surname>Dang</surname>
            <initial>Q.-V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <foreName>Claudia-Lavinia</foreName>
            <surname>Ignat</surname>
            <initial>C.-L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">The 15th IEEE International Conference on Trust, Security and Privacy in Computing and Communications (TrustCom-16)</title>
        <loc>Tianjin, China</loc>
        <title level="s">Proceedings of the 15th IEEE International Conference on Trust, Security and Privacy in Computing and Communications</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01351250" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01351250</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid624071">
          <title>IEEE International Conference on Trust, Security and Privacy in Computing and Communications</title>
          <num>15</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IEEE TrustCom</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid17" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:dang:hal-01388614">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01388614"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Measuring Quality of Collaboratively Edited Documents: the case of Wikipedia</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp80584">
            <foreName>Quang-Vinh</foreName>
            <surname>Dang</surname>
            <initial>Q.-V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <foreName>Claudia-Lavinia</foreName>
            <surname>Ignat</surname>
            <initial>C.-L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Proceedings of the 2nd IEEE International Conference on Collaboration and Internet Computing (CIC-16)</title>
        <loc>Pittsburgh, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01388614" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01388614</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625474">
          <title>IEEE International Conference on Collaboration and Internet Computing</title>
          <num>2</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CIC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid13" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:dang:hal-01351229">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/IFIPNetworking.2016.7497258"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01351229"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Performance of real-time collaborative editors at large scale: User perspective</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp80584">
            <foreName>Quang-Vinh</foreName>
            <surname>Dang</surname>
            <initial>Q.-V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <foreName>Claudia-Lavinia</foreName>
            <surname>Ignat</surname>
            <initial>C.-L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Internet of People Workshop, 2016 IFIP Networking Conference</title>
        <loc>Vienna, Austria</loc>
        <title level="s">Proceedings of 2016 IFIP Networking Conference, Networking 2016 and Workshops</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">548-553</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01351229" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01351229</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625496">
          <title>IFIP Internet of People workshop</title>
          <num>1</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IoP workshop</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid18" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:dang:hal-01351226">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/2910896.2910917"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01351226"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Quality Assessment of Wikipedia Articles without Feature Engineering</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp80584">
            <foreName>Quang-Vinh</foreName>
            <surname>Dang</surname>
            <initial>Q.-V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <foreName>Claudia-Lavinia</foreName>
            <surname>Ignat</surname>
            <initial>C.-L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Proceedings of the 16th ACM/IEEE-CS on Joint Conference on Digital Libraries</title>
        <loc>Newark, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>ACM</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">27-30</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01351226" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01351226</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625476">
          <title>ACM/IEEE-CS on Joint Conference on Digital Libraries</title>
          <num>16</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">JCDL</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid31" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:gautier:hal-01388703">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01388703"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">artEoz ‐ dynamic program visualization</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Martine</foreName>
            <surname>Gautier</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="magrit-2014-idp67840">
            <foreName>Brigitte</foreName>
            <surname>Wrobel-Dautcourt</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">International Conference on Informatics in Schools: Situation, Evolution, and Perspectives, ISSEP 2016</title>
        <loc>Munster, Germany</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01388703" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01388703</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625475">
          <title>International Conference on Informatics in Schools: Situation, Evolution, and Perspectives</title>
          <num>9</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISSEP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid21" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:nacer:hal-01399380">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/SERVICES.2016.9"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01399380"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Obfuscating a Business Process by Splitting Its Logic with Fake Fragments for Securing a Multi-cloud Deployment</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Amina Ahmed</foreName>
            <surname>Nacer</surname>
            <initial>A. A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp81824">
            <foreName>Elio</foreName>
            <surname>Goettelmann</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp70704">
            <foreName>Samir</foreName>
            <surname>Youcef</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Abdelkamel</foreName>
            <surname>Tari</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp65304">
            <foreName>Claude</foreName>
            <surname>Godart</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE Congress On Services</title>
        <loc>SanFrancisco, United States</loc>
        <title level="s">Services (SERVICES), 2016 IEEE World Congress on</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">18 - 25</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.univ-lorraine.fr/hal-01399380" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>univ-lorraine.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01399380</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid97122">
          <title>IEEE World Congress on Services</title>
          <num>12</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SERVICES</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid24" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:rosinosky:hal-01379167">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01379167"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Framework for BPMS Performance and Cost Evaluation on the Cloud</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp84272">
            <foreName>Guillaume</foreName>
            <surname>Rosinosky</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp70704">
            <foreName>Samir</foreName>
            <surname>Youcef</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Charoy</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Workshop "Business Process Monitoring and Performance Analysis in the Cloud"</title>
        <loc>Luxembourg, Luxembourg</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">IEEE CloudCom</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01379167" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01379167</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625497">
          <title>CloudCom Business Process Monitoring and Performance Analysis in the Cloud Workshop</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CloudBpm</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid23" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:rosinosky:hal-01355125">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01355125"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">An Efficient Approach for Multi-tenant Elastic Business Processes Management in Cloud Computing environment</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp84272">
            <foreName>Guillaume</foreName>
            <surname>Rosinosky</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp70704">
            <foreName>Samir</foreName>
            <surname>Youcef</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Charoy</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">9th IEEE International Conference on Cloud Computing - IEEE Cloud 2016</title>
        <loc>San Francisco, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01355125" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01355125</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid81569">
          <title>IEEE International Conference on Cloud Computing</title>
          <num>9</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CLOUD</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid14" type="techreport" rend="year" n="cite:martori:hal-01405896">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01405896"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Reliable causal delivery with probabilistic design</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jordi</foreName>
            <surname>Martori</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp69448">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Urso</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">RR-8985</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Inria Nancy</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01405896" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01405896</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Research Report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid29" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:rosinosky:hal-01300188">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01300188"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">An Efficient Approach for Multi-tenant Elastic Business Processes Management in Cloud Computing environment</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp84272">
            <foreName>Guillaume</foreName>
            <surname>Rosinosky</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp70704">
            <foreName>Samir</foreName>
            <surname>Youcef</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idm30768">
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Charoy</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01300188" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01300188</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid10" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:andre:hal-00903813">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00903813"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Supporting Adaptable Granularity of Changes for Massive-scale Collaborative Editing</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp78120">
            <foreName>Luc</foreName>
            <surname>André</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="algorille-2014-idp114232">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Martin</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp66744">
            <foreName>Gérald</foreName>
            <surname>Oster</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2015-idm27216">
            <foreName>Claudia-Lavinia</foreName>
            <surname>Ignat</surname>
            <initial>C.-L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes">
        <title level="m">CollaborateCom - 9th IEEE International Conference on Collaborative Computing: Networking, Applications and Worksharing - 2013</title>
        <loc>Austin, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/hal-00903813" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00903813</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid1" type="incollection" rend="foot" n="footcite:casati2013">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-642-36926-1_18"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Promises and Failures of Research in Dynamic Service Composition</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Fabio</foreName>
            <surname>Casati</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Janis</foreName>
            <surname>Bubenko</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>John</foreName>
            <surname>Krogstie</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Oscar</foreName>
            <surname>Pastor</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Barbara</foreName>
            <surname>Pernici</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Colette</foreName>
            <surname>Rolland</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Arne</foreName>
            <surname>Sølvberg</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Seminal Contributions to Information Systems Engineering</title>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">235-239</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-36926-1_18" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>dx.<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1007/<allowbreak/>978-3-642-36926-1_18</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid0" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:EllisSIGMOD89">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/67544.66963"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Concurrency Control in Groupware Systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Clarence A.</foreName>
            <surname>Ellis</surname>
            <initial>C. A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Simon J.</foreName>
            <surname>Gibbs</surname>
            <initial>S. J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM SIGMOD Conference on the Management of Data - SIGMOD 89</title>
        <loc>Portland, Oregon, USA</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>1989</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">399–407</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/67544.66963" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>acm.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1145/<allowbreak/>67544.<allowbreak/>66963</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid2" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:papazoglou2007">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Service-Oriented Computing: State of the Art and Research Challenges</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael P.</foreName>
            <surname>Papazoglou</surname>
            <initial>M. P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Paolo</foreName>
            <surname>Traverso</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Schahram</foreName>
            <surname>Dustdar</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Frank</foreName>
            <surname>Leymann</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Computer</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">40</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2007</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">38-45</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid4" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:SaitoCompSurvey05">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/1057977.1057980"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Optimistic Replication</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yasushi</foreName>
            <surname>Saito</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="regal-2014-idm26336">
            <foreName>Marc</foreName>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Computing Surveys</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">37</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2005</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">42–81</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1057977.1057980" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>acm.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1145/<allowbreak/>1057977.<allowbreak/>1057980</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid22" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Schulte201536">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.future.2014.09.005"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Elastic Business Process Management: State of the art and open challenges for BPM in the cloud</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Stefan</foreName>
            <surname>Schulte</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Janiesch</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Srikumar</foreName>
            <surname>Venugopal</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ingo</foreName>
            <surname>Weber</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Philipp</foreName>
            <surname>Hoenisch</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Future Generation Computer Systems</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">46</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">36 - 50</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167739X1400168X" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>sciencedirect.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>science/<allowbreak/>article/<allowbreak/>pii/<allowbreak/>S0167739X1400168X</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid3" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:SunTOCHI98">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/274444.274447"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Achieving Convergence, Causality Preservation, and Intention Preservation in Real-Time Cooperative Editing Systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Chengzheng</foreName>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Xiaohua</foreName>
            <surname>Jia</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yanchun</foreName>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="fluminance-2014-idp96360">
            <foreName>Yun</foreName>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>David</foreName>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>1998</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">63–108</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/274444.274447" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>acm.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1145/<allowbreak/>274444.<allowbreak/>274447</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid15" type="phdthesis" rend="foot" n="footcite:truong:tel-00769076">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="tel-00769076"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">A Contract-based and Trust-aware Collaboration Model</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Hien Thi Thu</foreName>
            <surname>Truong</surname>
            <initial>H. T. T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Université de Lorraine</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-00769076" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>tel.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>tel-00769076</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Theses</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid11" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:weiss:inria-00432368">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/ICDCS.2009.75"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="inria-00432368"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Logoot: A Scalable Optimistic Replication Algorithm for Collaborative Editing on P2P Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Weiss</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp69448">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Urso</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Molli</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">29th IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems - ICDCS 2009</title>
        <loc>Montreal, Canada</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>IEEE</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">404-412</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/inria-00432368" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>inria-00432368</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid8" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:BHIRI:2008:Inria-00438424:1">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="inria-00438424"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Mining and Improving Composite Web Services Recovery Mechanisms</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sami</foreName>
            <surname>Bhiri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Walid</foreName>
            <surname>Gaaloul</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp65304">
            <foreName>Claude</foreName>
            <surname>Godart</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">International Journal of Web Services Research</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00438424/en/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>inria-00438424/<allowbreak/>en/</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid7" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:BHIRI:2004:Inria-00099953:1">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="inria-00099953"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">An Object-Oriented Metamodel For Inter-Enterprises Cooperative Processes Based on Web Services</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sami</foreName>
            <surname>Bhiri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp68008">
            <foreName>Olivier</foreName>
            <surname>Perrin</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Walid</foreName>
            <surname>Gaaloul</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp65304">
            <foreName>Claude</foreName>
            <surname>Godart</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Journal of Integrated Design and Process Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">8</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2004</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">37–55</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00099953/en/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>inria-00099953/<allowbreak/>en/</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid6" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:OSTER:2006:Inria-00108523:1">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="inria-00108523"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Data Consistency for P2P Collaborative Editing</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp66744">
            <foreName>Gérald</foreName>
            <surname>Oster</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="coast-2014-idp69448">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Urso</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Molli</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="cassis-2014-idp76744">
            <foreName>Abdessamad</foreName>
            <surname>Imine</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-international-audience="yes" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work - CSCW 2006</title>
        <loc>Banff, Alberta, Canada</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>ACM Press</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2006</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">259 - 268</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00108523/en/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>inria-00108523/<allowbreak/>en/</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="coast-2016-bid5" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:PREGUICA:2009:Inria-00445975:1">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/ICDCS.2009.20"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="inria-00445975"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A commutative replicated data type for cooperative editing</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nuno</foreName>
            <surname>Preguiça</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Joan Manuel</foreName>
            <surname>Marquès</surname>
            <initial>J. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="regal-2014-idm26336">
            <foreName>Marc</foreName>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mihai</foreName>
            <surname>Letia</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">29th IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS 2009)</title>
        <loc>Montreal, Québec Canada</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>IEEE Computer Society</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">395-403</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00445975/en/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>inria-00445975/<allowbreak/>en/</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
  </biblio>
</raweb>
