<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2016">
  <identification id="maestro" isproject="true">
    <shortname>MAESTRO</shortname>
    <projectName>Models for the performance analysis and the control of networks</projectName>
    <theme-de-recherche>Networks and Telecommunications</theme-de-recherche>
    <domaine-de-recherche>Networks, Systems and Services, Distributed Computing</domaine-de-recherche>
    <urlTeam>http://team.inria.fr/maestro/</urlTeam>
    <header_dates_team>Creation of the Project-Team: 2003 October 01, end of the Project-Team: 2016 December 31</header_dates_team>
    <LeTypeProjet>Project-Team</LeTypeProjet>
    <keywordsSdN>
      <term>1.2. - Networks</term>
      <term>1.2.4. - QoS, performance evaluation</term>
      <term>1.2.9. - Social Networks</term>
      <term>1.5. - Complex systems</term>
      <term>1.5.2. - Communicating systems</term>
      <term>3.3.3. - Big data analysis</term>
      <term>3.5. - Social networks</term>
      <term>3.5.1. - Analysis of large graphs</term>
      <term>3.5.2. - Recommendation systems</term>
      <term>6. - Modeling, simulation and control</term>
      <term>6.1. - Mathematical Modeling</term>
      <term>6.1.1. - Continuous Modeling (PDE, ODE)</term>
      <term>6.1.2. - Stochastic Modeling (SPDE, SDE)</term>
      <term>6.2.2. - Numerical probability</term>
      <term>6.2.3. - Probabilistic methods</term>
      <term>6.2.6. - Optimization</term>
      <term>6.4.1. - Deterministic control</term>
      <term>6.4.2. - Stochastic control</term>
      <term>7.1. - Parallel and distributed algorithms</term>
      <term>7.2. - Discrete mathematics, combinatorics</term>
      <term>7.3. - Optimization</term>
      <term>7.10. - Network science</term>
      <term>7.11. - Performance evaluation</term>
      <term>7.14. - Game Theory</term>
    </keywordsSdN>
    <keywordsSecteurs>
      <term>3.1. - Sustainable development</term>
      <term>3.1.1. - Resource management</term>
      <term>4. - Energy</term>
      <term>4.3.4. - Solar Energy</term>
      <term>4.4. - Energy delivery</term>
      <term>4.4.1. - Smart grids</term>
      <term>4.5.1. - Green computing</term>
      <term>6.2.1. - Wired technologies</term>
      <term>6.2.2. - Radio technology</term>
      <term>6.3.2. - Network protocols</term>
      <term>6.3.3. - Network Management</term>
      <term>6.3.4. - Social Networks</term>
      <term>8.1. - Smart building/home</term>
      <term>9.2.1. - Music, sound</term>
      <term>9.4.1. - Computer science</term>
      <term>9.4.2. - Mathematics</term>
      <term>9.5.3. - Economy, Finance</term>
      <term>9.5.4. - Management science</term>
      <term>9.5.5. - Sociology</term>
    </keywordsSecteurs>
    <UR name="Sophia"/>
  </identification>
  <team id="uid1">
    <person key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
      <firstname>Alain</firstname>
      <lastname>Jean-Marie</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
      <firstname>Sara</firstname>
      <lastname>Alouf</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
      <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
      <lastname>Altman</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
      <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
      <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idm27080">
      <firstname>Philippe</firstname>
      <lastname>Nain</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Senior Researcher until Mar 2016</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
      <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
      <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="moais-2014-idp91576">
      <firstname>Guillaume</firstname>
      <lastname>Huard</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until May 2016, granted by Nokia Bell Labs</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp74744">
      <firstname>Issam</firstname>
      <lastname>Rabhi</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until May 2016, granted by ANR MARMOTE project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2016-idp161040">
      <firstname>Zaid</firstname>
      <lastname>Allybokus</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Huawei, from Jul 2016, granted by CIFRE</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp82232">
      <firstname>Arun</firstname>
      <lastname>Kadavankandy</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by ANR LABEX UCN@Sophia project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp83496">
      <firstname>Jithin</firstname>
      <lastname>Kazhuthuveettil Sreedharan</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by Nokia Bell Labs</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp84760">
      <firstname>Hlib</firstname>
      <lastname>Mykhailenko</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by ANR LABEX UCN@Sophia project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2016-idp170944">
      <firstname>Dimitra</firstname>
      <lastname>Politaki</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>UNS, granted by ANR LABEX UCN@Sophia project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2016-idp173424">
      <firstname>Nessrine</firstname>
      <lastname>Trabelsi</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until Sep 2016, granted by Nokia Bell Labs</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2016-idp175904">
      <firstname>Dimitra</firstname>
      <lastname>Tsigkari</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, pre-PhD Student, until Nov 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
      <firstname>Alina</firstname>
      <lastname>Tuholukova</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Eurecom, granted by ANR LABEX UCN@Sophia project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2016-idp180864">
      <firstname>Bin</firstname>
      <lastname>Sun</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>China Scholarship Council</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2016-idp183296">
      <firstname>Eleni</firstname>
      <lastname>Vatamidou</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, from Jun 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="maestro-2014-idp92344">
      <firstname>Laurie</firstname>
      <lastname>Vermeersch</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
  </team>
  <presentation id="uid2">
    <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid3" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Presentation of MAESTRO</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> is an Inria project-team whose members are located in
Sophia Antipolis (S. Alouf, K. Avrachenkov, G. Neglia),
at <span class="smallcap" align="left">Lia</span> (Lab. of Informatics of Avignon) in Avignon (E. Altman) and at <span class="smallcap" align="left">Lirmm</span>
(Lab. Informatics, Robotics and Microelectronics of Montpellier) in Montpellier
(A. Jean-Marie). <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> is concerned with the
modeling, performance evaluation, optimization and control of stochastic
Discrete-Event Dynamical Systems (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Deds</span>), with a particular emphasis
on networks and their applications. The scientific contributions are
both theoretical, with the development of new modeling formalisms,
and applied, with: a) the solution of specific problems arising in one of
our application domains, b) the development of software tools for the
performance evaluation of <span class="smallcap" align="left">Deds</span>, and c) the patenting of new methods
jointly with industrial partners.</p>
    </subsection>
  </presentation>
  <fondements id="uid4">
    <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid5" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Research Directions</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>'s research directions belong to five main themes motivated by
direct applications: network science, wireless networks, network
engineering games, green networking and smart grids, content-oriented
systems. These directions are very connected: network engineering
games find applications in many networking fields, from wireless
protocols to applications such as social networks. Green IT studies
are often concerned with wireless networks, etc. The study of these
applications often raises questions of methodological nature, less
close to direct applications; these advances are reported in a
separate section.</p>
      <subsection id="uid6" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Network Science</bodyTitle>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> contributes to this new fast growing research subject.
“Network Science” or “Complex Network Analysis” aims at
understanding the structural properties and the dynamics of a variety
of large-scale networks in telecommunications (e.g. the graph of
autonomous systems, the Web graph), social science (e.g. community of
interest, advertisement, reputation, recommendation systems), bibliometrics
(e.g. citations, co-authors), biology (e.g. spread of an epidemic,
protein-protein interactions), and physics. It has been observed that
the complex networks encountered in these areas share common
properties such as power law degree distribution, small average
distances, community structure, etc. It also appears that many general
questions/applications (e.g. community detection, epidemic spreading,
search, anomaly detection) are common in various disciplines which
study networks. In particular, we aim at understanding the evolution
of complex networks with the help of game theoretical tools in
connection with Network Engineering Games, as described below. We
design efficient tools for measuring specific properties of
large scale complex networks and their dynamics. More specifically, we
work on the problem of distributed optimization in large networks
where nodes cooperatively solve an optimization problem relying only
on local information exchange.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid7" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Wireless Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>The amazing technological advances in wireless devices has led
networks to become heterogeneous and very complex. Many research
groups worldwide investigate performance evaluation of wireless
technologies. <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>'s specificity relies on the use of a large
variety of analytic tools from applied probability, control theory
and distributed optimization to study and improve wireless networks
functionalities. We investigate in particular problems of self-organization,
channel selection and power control, the association problem and others.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid8" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Network Engineering Games</bodyTitle>
        <p>The foundations of <i>Network Engineering Games</i> are currently being laid.
These are games arising in telecommunications engineering at
all the networking layers. This includes considerations from
information and communications theory for dealing with the physical
and link layers, along with cross layer approaches. <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>'s focus
is on three areas: <i>routing games</i>, <i>evolutionary games</i> and <i>epidemic games</i>. In routing games we progress on the theory for costs
that are not additive over links (such as packet losses or call
blocking probabilities). We pursue their research in the
stochastic extension of evolutionary game theory, namely the
“anonymous sequential games” in which we study the total
expected costs and the average cost. Within epidemic games they
study epidemics that compete against each other. We apply this
to social networks, considering in particular the coupling between various
social networks (e.g. propagation strategies that combine Twitter,
FaceBook and other social networks).</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid9" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Green Networking and Smart Grids</bodyTitle>
        <p>The ICT (Information and Communications Technology) sector is becoming
one of the main energy consumers worldwide. There is awareness that
networks should have a reduced environmental footprint. Our objective
is to have a systematically “green” approach when solving
optimization problems. The energy cost and the environmental impact
should be considered in optimization functions along with traditional
performance metrics such as throughput, fairness or delay. We aim at
contributing to the design and the analysis of future green networks, in
particular those using renewable energy.</p>
        <p>Researchers envision that future electricity distribution network will
be “smart”, with a large number of small generators (due to an
extensive use of renewable energies) and of consumer devices able to
adapt their energy needs to a time-varying offer. Generators and
devices will be able to locally communicate through the electrical
grid itself (or more traditional communication networks), in order to
optimize production, transport and use of the energy. This is
definitely a new application scenario for <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>, to which we hope
to be able to contribute with our expertise on analytic models and
performance evaluation.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid10" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Content-Oriented Systems</bodyTitle>
        <p>We generally study problems related with the placement and the retrieval
of data in communication networks.</p>
        <p>We are particularly interested in In-network caching, a widely adopted
technique to provide an efficient access to data or resources on a
world-wide deployed system while ensuring scalability and
availability. For instance, caches are integral components of the
Domain Name System, the World Wide Web, Content Distribution Networks,
or the recently proposed Information-Centric Network (ICN)
architectures. We analyze network of caches, study their optimal
placement in the network and optimize data placement in
caches/servers.</p>
        <p>We also study other aspects related to replication and placement of
data: how much to replicate it and on which servers to place it?
Finally, we study optimal ways of retrieving the data through prefetching.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid11" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Advances in Methodological Tools</bodyTitle>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> has a methodological activity that aims at advancing the
state of the art in the tools used for the general
performance evaluation and control of systems. We contribute to
such fields as perturbation analysis, Markov processes, queueing
theory, control theory and game theory. Another objective is to
enhance our activity on general-purpose modeling algorithms and
software for controlled and uncontrolled stochastic systems.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid12" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Scientific Foundations</bodyTitle>
      <p>The main mathematical tools and formalisms used in <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> include:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid13">
          <p noindent="true">theory of stochastic processes: Markov process, renewal process, branching process,
point process, Palm measure, large deviations, mean-field approximation, fluid
approximation;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid14">
          <p noindent="true">theory of dynamical discrete-event systems: queues, pathwise and stochastic
comparisons, random matrix theory;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid15">
          <p noindent="true">theory of control and scheduling: dynamic programming, Markov decision
process, game theory, deterministic and stochastic scheduling;
stochastic approximation algorithms;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid16">
          <p noindent="true">theory of singular perturbations.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </fondements>
  <domaine id="uid17">
    <bodyTitle>Application Domains</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid18" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Main Application Domains</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>'s main application area is networking, to which we apply
modeling, performance evaluation, optimization and control.
Our primary focus is on
protocols and network architectures, and recent evolutions include
the study of the Web and social networks, as well as models
for Green IT.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid19">
          <p noindent="true">Wireless (cellular, ad hoc, sensor) networks: <span class="smallcap" align="left">Wlan</span>,
WiMAX, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Umts</span>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Lte</span>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Hspa</span>, delay tolerant networks (DTN), power control,
medium access control, transmission rate control, redundancy in source
coding, mobility models, coverage, routing, green base stations,</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid20">
          <p noindent="true">Internet applications: social networks,
content distribution systems, peer-to-peer systems, overlay
networks, multimedia traffic, video-on-demand, multicast;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid21">
          <p noindent="true">Information-Centric Networking (ICN) architectures:
Content-Centric Network (CCN, also called Content-Oriented Networks);</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid22">
          <p noindent="true">Internet infrastructure: TCP, high speed congestion control,
voice over IP, service differentiation, quality of service, web
caches, proxy caches.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </domaine>
  <highlights id="uid23">
    <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid24" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid25" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Awards</bodyTitle>
        <best>
          <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
        </best>
        <p>The paper “Access-time Aware cache Algorithms”
by Giovanni Neglia; Damiano Carra; Mingdong Feng; Vaishnav Janardhan; Pietro Michiardi and Dimitra Tsigkari
got the Best Paper Award at ITC 28 in Würzburg.</p>
        <best>
          <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
        </best>
        <p>The article “Sonorous Cartography for Sighted and Blind People”
by Didier Josselin, Andelbery Saidi, Dorian Roussel, Said Boularouk, Olivier Bonin, Eitan Altman, Driss Matrouf
got the Best Short Paper Award at the conference 19th AGILE International on Geographic Information Science, Helsinki, Finland, June 14-17, 2016.</p>
        <p>S. Alouf has received a “Recognition of Service Award” from the ACM in September 2016.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </highlights>
  <logiciels id="uid26">
    <bodyTitle>New Software and Platforms</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid27" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>marmoteCore</bodyTitle>
      <p>Markov Modeling Tools and Environments - the Core</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Modeling - Stochastic models - Markov model</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>marmoteCore is a C++ environment for modeling with Markov chains.
It consists in a reduced set of high-level abstractions for constructing
state spaces, transition structures and Markov chains (discrete-time and
continuous-time). It provides the ability of constructing hierarchies of Markov
models, from the most general to the particular, and equip each level with
specifically optimized solution methods.</p>
      <p>This software is developed within the ANR MARMOTE project: ANR-12-MONU-00019.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid28">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Alain Jean-Marie, Issam Rabhi</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid29">
          <p noindent="true">Partner: UVSQ (Univ. Versailles Saint-Quentin)</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid30">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Alain Jean-Marie</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid31">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://marmotecore.gforge.inria.fr/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>marmotecore.<allowbreak/>gforge.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid32" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>ns-3</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Simulation - Communication networks</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>ns-3 is a discrete-event network simulator for Internet systems, targeted primarily for research and educational use.</p>
      <p>In the framework of the research project with <span class="smallcap" align="left">Alstom</span> Transport (see §<ref xlink:href="#uid91" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>),
we have extensively validated several modules of ns-3, related to the
PHY and the MAC layers. We have implemented a directional antenna
using 3-dimensional data for the radiation diagram. Modules related to
the Automatic Train Protection function used in train systems have
been implemented and validated. We have also developed a generator of
video traffic and objects that allow to generate easily simulation
scenarios.</p>
      <p>We have made available the code related to the communication based
train control and the one generating video traffic. Some of our
contribution to the ns-3 simulator and selected results illustrating
some of the issues that can be addressed using our contribution are
presented and discussed in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid33">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Sara Alouf, Giovanni Neglia and Alina Tuholukova</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid34">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Alina Tuholukova</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid35">
          <p noindent="true">ns-3 codereview issue of the cbtc module: <ref xlink:href="https://codereview.appspot.com/289110043" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>codereview.<allowbreak/>appspot.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>289110043</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid36">
          <p noindent="true">ns-3 codereview issue of the video generator: <ref xlink:href="https://codereview.appspot.com/286160043" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>codereview.<allowbreak/>appspot.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>286160043</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </logiciels>
  <resultats id="uid37">
    <bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid38" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Network Science</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
          <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
          <lastname>Altman</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
          <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
          <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp82232">
          <firstname>Arun</firstname>
          <lastname>Kadavankandy</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp83496">
          <firstname>Jithin</firstname>
          <lastname>Kazhuthuveettil Sreedharan</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp84760">
          <firstname>Hlib</firstname>
          <lastname>Mykhailenko</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
          <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
          <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
          <firstname>Alina</firstname>
          <lastname>Tuholukova</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid39" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Computation on Large Graphs</bodyTitle>
        <p>The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> team has been working on how to partition large graphs in distributed computation frameworks in order to speed up the execution time.</p>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, H. Mykhailenko and G.
Neglia in collaboration with F. Huet (Univ. Côte d'Azur, CNRS,
I3S), provide an overview of existing edge partitioning algorithms.
However, based only on published work, it is not possible to draw a
clear conclusion about the relative performances of these
partitioners. For this reason, the authors compare all the edge
partitioners currently available for the widely-used framework for
graph processing Apache GraphX. Preliminary results suggest that
the Hybrid-Cut partitioner provides the best performance.</p>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, H. Mykhailenko and G.
Neglia in collaboration with F. Huet (Univ. Côte d'Azur, CNRS,
I3S), focus on vertex-cut graph partitioning and they investigate how
it is possible to evaluate the quality of a partition before running
the computation. To this purpose the authors scrutinize a set of
metrics proposed in literature. They carry experiments with Apache
GraphX and they perform an accurate statistical analysis. Preliminary
experimental results show that communication metrics like vertex-cut
and communication cost are effective predictors on most of the cases.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid40" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Network centrality measures</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, K. Avrachenkov in collaboration with
V. Mazalov (Karelian Institute of Applied Mathematical Research, Russia),
L. Trukhina (Baikal State Univ. of Economics and Law, Russia) and B. Tsynguev
(Transbaikal State Univ., Russia) worked on network centrality measures based on
game-theoretic concepts. The betweenness centrality is one of the basic concepts in the analysis of the social networks. Initial definition for the betweenness of a node in the graph is based on the fraction of the number of geodesics (shortest paths) between any two nodes that given node lies on, to the total number of the shortest paths connecting these nodes. This method has polynomial complexity. We propose a new concept of the betweenness centrality for weighted graphs using the methods of cooperative game theory. The characteristic function is determined by special way for different coalitions (subsets of the graph). Two approaches are used to determine the characteristic function. In the first approach the characteristic function is determined via the number of direct and indirect weighted connecting paths in the coalition. In the second approach the coalition is considered as an electric network and the characteristic function is determined as a total current in this network. We use Kirchhoff’s law. After that the betweenness centrality is determined as the Myerson value. The results of computer simulations for some examples of networks, in particular, for the popular social network “VKontakte”, as well as the comparing with the PageRank method are presented.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid41" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Sampling and Inference of Complex Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov, G. Neglia and A. Tuholukova
study chain-referral methods for sampling in social networks.
These methods rely on subjects of the study recruiting other
participants among their set of connections. This approach gives us the
possibility to perform sampling when the other methods, that imply the
knowledge of the whole network or its global characteristics, fail. Chain-
referral methods can be implemented with random walks or crawling in
the case of online social networks. However, the estimations made on the
collected samples can have high variance, especially with small sample
size. The other drawback is the potential bias due to the way the samples
are collected. We suggest and analyze a subsampling technique, where
some users are requested only to recruit other users but do not participate
to the study. Assuming that the referral has lower cost than actual
participation, this technique takes advantage of exploring a larger variety
of population, thus decreasing significantly the variance of the estimator.
We test the method on real social networks and on synthetic ones.
As by-product, we propose a Gibbs-like method for generating synthetic
networks with desired properties.</p>
        <p>Function estimation on Online Social Networks (OSN) is an
important field of study in complex network analysis. An efficient way to
do function estimation on large networks is to use random walks. We can
then defer to the extensive theory of Markov chains to do error analysis
of these estimators. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, K. Avrachenkov,
A. Kadavankandy and J.K. Sreedharan in collaboration with V. Borkar (IIT Bombay,
India) compare two existing techniques,
Metropolis-Hastings MCMC and Respondent-Driven Sampling, that use
random walks to do function estimation and compare them with a new
reinforcement learning based technique. We provide both theoretical and
empirical analyses for the estimators we consider.</p>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov and J.K. Sreedharan
in collaboration with B. Ribeiro (Purdue Univ., USA) develop random
walk based methods for inference in Online Social Networks (OSNs) to answer
questions like are OSN users more likely to
form friendships with those with similar attributes?
Do users at an OSN A score content more favorably than OSN B
users? Such questions frequently arise in the context of Social Network Analysis (SNA)
but often crawling an OSN network via its Application Programming Interface (API) is the
only way to gather data from a third party. To date, these
partial API crawls are the majority of public datasets and
the synonym of lack of statistical guarantees in incomplete-data
comparisons, severely limiting SNA research progress.
Using regenerative properties of the random walks, we propose
estimation techniques based on short crawls that have
proven statistical guarantees. Moreover, our short crawls
can be implemented in massively distributed algorithms. We
also provide an adaptive crawler that makes our method
parameter-free, significantly improving our statistical guarantees.
We then derive the Bayesian approximation of the
posterior of the estimates, and in addition, obtain an estimator
for the expected value of node and edge statistics in an
equivalent configuration model or Chung-Lu random graph
model of the given network (where nodes are connected randomly)
and use it as a basis for testing null hypotheses.
The theoretical results are supported with simulations on a
variety of real-world networks.</p>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov in collaboration with
L. Iskhakov and M. Mironov (Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Russia)
consider pairwise Markov random fields which have a
number of important applications in statistical physics, image processing
and machine learning such as Ising model and labeling problem to name
a couple. Our own motivation comes from the need to produce synthetic
models for social networks with attributes. First, we give conditions for
rapid mixing of the associated Glauber dynamics and consider
interesting particular cases. Then, for pairwise Markov random
fields with submodular energy functions we construct monotone
perfect simulation.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid42" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Distributed algorithms for complex network analysis</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid10" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov and J.K. Sreedharan
in collaboration with P. Jacquet (Nokia Bell Labs, France) address
the problem of finding top-k eigenvalues and corresponding
eigenvectors of symmetric
graph matrices in networks in a distributed way. We propose
a novel idea called complex power iterations in order to decompose
the eigenvalues and eigenvectors at node level, analogous to
time-frequency analysis in signal processing. At each node, eigenvalues
correspond to the frequencies of spectral peaks and respective
eigenvector components are the amplitudes at those points. Based
on complex power iterations and motivated from fluid diffusion
processes in networks, we devise distributed algorithms with
different orders of approximation. We also introduce a Monte
Carlo technique with gossiping which substantially reduces the
computational overhead. An equivalent parallel random walk
algorithm is also presented. We validate the algorithms with
simulations on real-world networks. Our formulation of the spectral
decomposition can be easily adapted to a simple algorithm
based on quantum random walks. With the advent of quantum
computing, the proposed quantum algorithm will be extremely
useful.</p>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov in collaboration with
V. Borkar and K. Saboo (IIT Bombay, India)
propose two asynchronously distributed approaches for
graph-based semi-supervised learning. The first approach is based on
stochastic approximation, whereas the second approach is based on
randomized Kaczmarz algorithm. In addition to the possibility of distributed
implementation, both approaches can be naturally applied online to
streaming data. We analyse both approaches theoretically and by experiments.
It appears that there is no clear winner and we provide indications
about cases of superiority for each approach.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid43" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Random Matrix Theory for Complex Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> A. Kadavankandy and K. Avrachenkov
in collaboration with L. Cottatellucci (Eurecom, France) describe
a test statistic based on the L1-norm of the eigenvectors of a
modularity matrix to detect the presence of an embedded
Erdos-Renyi (ER) subgraph inside a larger ER random graph.
An embedded subgraph may model a
hidden community in a large network such as a social network
or a computer network. We make use of the properties
of the asymptotic distribution of eigenvectors of random graphs
to derive the distribution of the test statistic under certain
conditions on the subgraph size and edge probabilities. We show
that the distributions differ sufficiently for well defined ranges
of subgraph sizes and edge probabilities of the background
graph and the subgraph. This method can have applications
where it is sufficient to know whether there is an anomaly in a
given graph without the need to infer its location. The results we
derive on the distribution of the components of the eigenvector
may also be useful to detect the subgraph nodes.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid44" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Network Growth Models</bodyTitle>
        <p>Network growth and evolution is a fundamental theme that has puzzled
scientists for the past decades. A number of models have been proposed
to capture important properties of real networks. In an attempt to
better describe reality, more recent growth models embody local rules
of attachment, however they still require a primitive to randomly
select an existing network node and then some kind of global knowledge
about the network (at least the set of nodes and how to reach
them). In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> G. Neglia, in collaboration with
B. Amorim, D. Figueiredo and G. Iacobelli (Federal Univ. of Rio de
Janeiro, Brazil), proposes a purely local network growth model that
makes no use of global sampling across the nodes. The model is based
on a continuously moving random walk that after s steps connects a new
node to its current location, but never restarts. Through extensive
simulations and theoretical arguments, they analyze the behavior of
the model finding a fundamental dependency on the parity of s, where
networks with either exponential or a conditional power law degree
distribution can emerge. As s increases parity dependency diminishes
and the model recovers the degree distribution of Barabási-Albert
preferential attachment model. The proposed purely local model
indicates that networks can grow to exhibit interesting properties
even in the absence of any global rule, such as global node sampling.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid45" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Competition over popularity in online social networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
E. Altman in collaboration with A. Jain and Y. Hayel (UAPV)
consider a stochastic game that describes competition through advertisement over the popularity of their content. They show that the equilibrium may or may not be unique, depending on the system's parameters. They identify structural properties of the equilibria. In particular, they show that a finite improvement property holds on the best response pure policies which implies the existence of pure equilibria. They further show that all pure equilibria are fully ordered in the performance they provide to the players and propose a procedure to obtain the best equilibrium.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid46" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Trend detection in social networks using Hawkes processes</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid15" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>,
J. C. Louzada Pinto and T. Chahed from Telecom SudParis
in collaboration with E. Altman propose
a general Hawkes-based framework to model information diffusion in social networks. The proposed framework takes into consideration the hidden interactions between users as well as the interactions between contents and social networks, and can also accommodate dynamic social networks and various temporal effects of the diffusion, which provides a complete analysis of the hidden influences in social networks. This framework can be combined with topic modeling, for which modified collapsed Gibbs sampling and variational Bayes techniques are derived. We provide an estimation algorithm based on nonnegative tensor factorization techniques, which together with a dimensionality reduction argument are able to discover the latent community structure of the social network. We provide numerical examples from real-life networks: a Game of Thrones and a MemeTracker datasets.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid47" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Potential Game approach to defense against
virus attacks in networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>The Susceptible-Infected-Susceptible (SIS) model is a classical epidemic model where agents
alternate between a sane (susceptible) and an infected state.
SIS epidemic non-zero sum games have been recently used to analyse virus protection in networks. A potential game approach was proposed for solving the game for the case of a fully connected network. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, F.-X. Legenvre and Y. Hayel (UAPV) in collaboration with E. Altman extend this result to an arbitrary topology by showing that the general topology game is a generalized ordinal potential game. We apply this result to study numerically some examples.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid48" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Wireless Networks</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
          <firstname>Sara</firstname>
          <lastname>Alouf</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
          <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
          <lastname>Altman</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
          <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
          <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
          <firstname>Alina</firstname>
          <lastname>Tuholukova</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid49" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Control of Delay–Tolerant Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> E. Altman and G. Neglia, in collaboration with F. De Pellegrini (Create-Net, Italy) and D. Miorandi (U-Hopper, Italy), study optimal stochastic control of delay tolerant networks. First, the structure of optimal two-hop forwarding policies is derived. In order to be implemented, such policies require knowledge of certain global system parameters such as the number of mobiles or the rate of contacts between mobiles. But, such parameters could be unknown at system design time or may even change over time. In order to address this problem, adaptive policies are designed that combine estimation and control: based on stochastic approximation techniques, such policies are proved to achieve optimal performance in spite of lack of global information. Furthermore, the paper studies interactions that may occur in the presence of several DTNs which compete for the access to a gateway node. The latter problem is formulated as a cost-coupled stochastic game and a unique Nash equilibrium is found. Such equilibrium corresponds to the system configuration in which each DTN adopts the optimal forwarding policy determined for the single network problem.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid50" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Performance Evaluation of Train Moving-Block Control</bodyTitle>
        <p>In moving block systems for railway transportation a central
controller periodically communicates to the train how far it can
safely advance. On-board automatic protection mechanisms stop the
train if no message is received during a given time window. In
<ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid19" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> G. Neglia, S. Alouf,
and A. Tuholukova in collaboration with A. Dandoush (SME Sudria,
France, formerly engineer with <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>) and S. Simoens, P. Dersin,
J. Billion and P. Derouet (all from <span class="smallcap" align="left">Alstom</span> Transport) consider as
reference a typical implementation of moving-block control for metro
and quantify the rate of spurious Emergency Brakes (EBs), i.e. of
train stops due to communication losses and not to an actual risk of
collision. Such unexpected EBs can happen at any point on the track
and are a major service disturbance.</p>
        <p>The general formula for the EB rate found in
<ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> requires a probabilistic characterization
of losses and delays. Calculations are surprisingly simple in the case
of homogeneous and independent packet losses. More complex loss
scenarios are studied in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid20" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The approach is
computationally efficient even when emergency brakes are very rare (as
they should be) and can no longer be estimated via discrete-event
simulations.</p>
        <p>The analytical models have also been validated using ns-3 simulations
<ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid51" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Speed estimation</bodyTitle>
        <p>After several years of cooperation with Nokia (formerly Alcatel-Lucent) Bell Labs
in developing tools for
speed estimation from measurement of the radio channel, we have
now started to publish our joint patented work. This includes
the work on mobility state estimation in LTE by
D.-G. Herculea, V. Capdevielle, C. S. Chen,
N. Ben Rached and F. Ratovelomanana from Nokia-Bell Labs
in collaboration with E. Altman and
M. Haddad (UAPV), see <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid21" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid52" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Sonorous cartography for sighted and blind people</bodyTitle>
        <p>E. Altman has been invited by D. Josselin from UMR Espace in
UAPV to co-advise a Master project and later a thesis financed by the
CNRS on Sonorous cartography. Other persons with whom we collaborate
are D. Roussel, S. Boularouk, A. Saidi, M. Driss
(from UAPV) and O. Bonin (Laboratoire Ville, Mobilité,
Transport) all coauthors of <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> which won the
best short paper award in the AGILE conference. In this article, we
test the usability of a cartographic tool mixing maps and sounds. This
tool is developed within QuantumGIS as a plugin prototype. We first
present some theoretical reflections about synesthesia. Secondly, we
explain the way we “sonificate” the images, by associating colors
and recorded chords and sounds. Then we present the results of several
usability tests in France with different users, including blind
people.</p>
        <p>To help blind people compensate visual perception and to better
understand their outdoor environment, S. Boularouk and D. Josselin
from UAPV in collaboration with E. Altman, proposed in
<ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid22" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> a method using human-computer
interaction via Text-to-Speach. It helps visually impaired people to
know surrounding places from OpenStreetMap data by hearing. The
principal idea is to convey spatial information by voice synthesis and
receive requests from blind people by voice recognition.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid53" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scheduling for mobile users with non-stationary mobility</bodyTitle>
        <p>H. Zaaraoui and Z. Altman from Orange Labs in collaboration with
T. Jiménez (UAPV) and E. Altman have studied scheduling in
an environment with non-stationary mobility (cars are moving on a road
and may have to stop at red lights).
They propose scheduling schemes for such mobility patterns
and study their performance in
in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid23" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid54" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>User Association in Multi-user MIMO Small Cell Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>Dense Networks and large MIMO are two key enablers to achieve high
data rates towards next generation 5G networks. In this context,
S. Ramanath (Lekha Wireless Solutions and IIT Mumbai) and M. Debbah
(Huawei) in collaboration with E. Altman study in
<ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> user association in an interference
limited Multiuser MIMO Small Cell Network. Extending on previous
findings, they derive explicit expressions for the optimal ratio of
the number of antennas at the base station to the number of users that
can associate to a base station in such a Network. The expressions are
used to compute the actual number of users that can associate for a
given interference level and other system parameters. Simulation
results and numerical examples are provided to support our theoretical
findings.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid55" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Network Engineering Games</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
          <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
          <lastname>Altman</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
          <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
          <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
          <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
          <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2016-idp173424">
          <firstname>Nessrine</firstname>
          <lastname>Trabelsi</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid56" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Network formation games</bodyTitle>
        <p>Network formation games have been proposed as a tool to explain
the topological characteristics of existing networks. They assume
that each node is an autonomous decision-maker, ignoring that in many
cases different nodes are under the control of the same authority
(e.g. an Autonomous System) and then they operate as a team.
In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid26" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov and G. Neglia in
collaboration with V.V. Singh (LRI, Univ. Paris-Sud, France)
introduce the concept of network formation games for teams of nodes
and show how very different network structures can arise also for
some simple games studied in the literature. Beside extending
the usual definition of pairwise stable networks to this new setting,
we define a more general concept of stability toward deviations from
a specific set C of teams’ coalitions (C-stability). We study then a
trembling-hand dynamics, where at each time a coalition of teams can
create or sever links in order to reduce its cost, but it can also take
wrong decisions with some small probability. We show that this stochastic
dynamics selects C-stable networks or networks from closed cycles in the
long run as the error probability vanishes.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid57" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Routing Games</bodyTitle>
        <p>A central question in routing games has been to establish conditions for uniqueness of the equilibrium, in terms of network topology or of costs. This question is well understood in two classes of routing games. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid27" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, E. Altman and C. Touati (Inria Grenoble - Rhône-Alpes) study two other frameworks of routing games in which each of several players has an integer number of connections (which are population of packets) to route and where there is a constraint that a connection cannot be split. Through a particular game with a simple three link topology, we identify various novel and surprising properties of games within these frameworks. We show in particular that equilibria are non unique even in the potential game setting of Rosenthal with strictly convex link costs.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid58" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Game theory applied to the Internet and social networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid28" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> E. Altman, A. Jain (UAPV) and C. Touati (Inria Grenoble - Rhône-Alpes) in
collaboration with N. Shimkin (Technion), present an overview of the
use of dynamic games for analyzing competition in the Internet and in
on-line social networks. A special emphasis is put on identifying
phenomena and tools that are novel with respet to game theory applied
to other types of networks.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid59" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Resilience of Routing in Parallel Link Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>E. Altman, C. Touati and A. Singhal (Inria Grenoble - Rhône-Alpes), in collaboration with J. Li (Tsukuba Univ. Japan),
use a game approach in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid29" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> to
study the resilience problem of routing traffic in a parallel link network with a malicious player. They consider two players: the first wishes to split its traffic so as to minimize its average delay, which the second player, i.e., the malicious player, tries to maximize. The first player has a demand constraint on the total traffic it routes. The second player controls the link capacities: it can decrease by some amount the capacity of each link under a constraint on the sum of capacity degradation. We first show that the average delay function is convex both in traffic and in capacity degradation over the parallel links and thus does not have a saddle point. We identify best responses strategies of each player and compute both the max-min and the min-max values of the game.
We provide stable algorithms for computing both max-min and min-max strategies as well as for best responses.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid60" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>A game theoretic solution for Resource
Allocation in LTE Cellular Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>Due to Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiple Access (OFDMA) mechanism adopted in LTE cellular networks, intra-cell interference is nearly absent. Yet, as these networks are designed for a frequency reuse factor of 1 to maximize the utilization of the licensed bandwidth, inter-cell interference coordination remains an important challenge. In both homogeneous and heterogeneous cellular networks, there is a need for scheduling coordination techniques to efficiently distribute the resources and mitigate inter-cell interference. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid30" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, N. Trabelsi and E. Altman in collaboration with
C. S. Chen, L. Roullet from Nokia Bell Labs and with
R. El-Azouzi from UAPV propose a dynamic solution of inter-cell interference coordination performing an optimization of frequency sub-band reuse and transmission power in order to maximize the overall network utility. The proposed framework, based on game theory, permits to dynamically define frequency and transmission power patterns for each cell in the coordinated cluster.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid61" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Green Networking and Smart Grids</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
          <firstname>Sara</firstname>
          <lastname>Alouf</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
          <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
          <lastname>Altman</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
          <firstname>Alain</firstname>
          <lastname>Jean-Marie</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
          <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
          <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2016-idp170944">
          <firstname>Dimitra</firstname>
          <lastname>Politaki</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid62" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Power Demand Control</bodyTitle>
        <p>Demand-Response (DR) programs, whereby users of an electricity network are encouraged by economic incentives to rearrange their consumption in order to reduce production costs, are envisioned to be a key feature of the smart grid paradigm. Several recent works proposed DR mechanisms and used analytical models to derive optimal incentives. Most of these works, however, rely on a macroscopic description of the population that does not model individual choices of users. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid31" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid32" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> G. Neglia and A. Benegiamo (PhD student in <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> at the submission time), in collaboration with P. Loiseau, conduct a detailed analysis of those models and argue that the macroscopic descriptions hide important assumptions that can jeopardize the mechanisms' implementation (such as the ability to make personalized offers and to perfectly estimate the demand that is moved from a timeslot to another). Then, they start from a microscopic description that explicitly models each user's decision. They introduce four DR mechanisms with various assumptions on the provider's capabilities.
Contrarily to previous studies, they find that the optimization problems that result from these mechanisms are not convex. Local optimizers can be found numerically through a heuristic. The authors present numerical simulations that compare the different mechanisms and their sensitivity to forecast errors. At a high level, their results show that the performance of DR mechanisms under reasonable assumptions on the provider's capabilities are significantly lower than those suggested by previous studies, but that the gap reduces when the population's flexibility increases.</p>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid33" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> A. Jean-Marie and G. Neglia in collaboration with I. Tinnirello, L. Giarré, M. Ippolito (Univ. of Palermo, Italy) and G. Di Bella (Telecom Italia, Italy) investigate a realistic and low-cost deployment of large scale direct control of inelastic home appliances whose energy demand cannot be shaped, but simply deferred. The idea is to exploit 1) some simple actuators to be placed on the electric plugs for connecting or disconnecting appliances with heterogeneous control interfaces, including non-smart appliances, and 2) the Internet connections of customers for transporting the activation requests from the actuators to a centralized controller. The solution requires no interaction with home users: in particular, it does not require them to express their energy demand in advance. A queuing theory model is derived to quantify how many users should adopt this solution in order to control a significant aggregated power load without significantly impairing their quality of service.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid63" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Geographical Load Balancing across Green Datacenters</bodyTitle>
        <p>“Geographic Load Balancing” is a strategy for reducing the energy cost of data centers spreading across different terrestrial locations.
In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid34" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> G. Neglia, in collaboration with M. Sereno (Univ. of Torino, Italy) and G. Bianchi (Univ. of Roma “Tor Vergata”, Italy), focuses on load balancing among micro-datacenters powered by renewable energy sources. They model via a Markov Chain the problem of scheduling jobs by prioritizing datacenters where renewable energy is currently available. Not finding a convenient closed form solution for the resulting chain, they use mean field techniques to derive an asymptotic approximate model which instead is shown to have an extremely simple and intuitive steady state solution. After proving, using both theoretical and discrete event simulation results, that the system performance converges to the asymptotic model for an increasing number of datacenters, they exploit the simple closed form model's solution to investigate relationships and trade-offs among the various system parameters.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid64" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Stochastic models for solar energy</bodyTitle>
        <p>The recent popularization of renewable energy sources makes it urgent to have realistic and practical models for the renewable energy harvested by photovoltaic panels for instance. Solar radiation is intrinsically stochastic and exhibits fluctuations at several time scales. Due to the sun's position during the day with respect to a given point on Earth, there is a periodic day-night pattern that is observed on top of which short-time burstiness occurs due to fluctuating weather conditions. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid35" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, D. Politaki and S. Alouf propose a stochastic model for the global solar radiation. They introduce a multiplicative factor that is the ratio between the actual global solar radiation and the idealized clear sky global radiation. The latter is obtained using known astronomical models and captures the day-night pattern of the solar radiation at any given point on Earth. On the other hand, the multiplicative factor captures the short-time burstiness caused by cloudiness. A semi-Markov model is proposed for the latter such that most of the time correlation found in measured data can be reproduced in synthetic traces.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid65" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Content-Oriented Systems</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
          <firstname>Sara</firstname>
          <lastname>Alouf</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
          <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
          <lastname>Altman</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
          <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
          <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idm27080">
          <firstname>Philippe</firstname>
          <lastname>Nain</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
          <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
          <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2016-idp175904">
          <firstname>Dimitra</firstname>
          <lastname>Tsigkari</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid66" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Modeling modern DNS caches</bodyTitle>
        <p>In-network caching is a widely adopted technique to provide an efficient access to data or resources on a world-wide deployed system while ensuring scalability and availability. In previous years, S. Alouf and N. Choungmo Fofack (former PhD student at <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>, currently at Ingima) have focused on hierarchical systems that rely on expiration-based policies to manage their caches. Each cache in the system maintains for each item a timer that indicates its duration of validity. The Domain Name System (DNS) is a valid application case. The objective was to assess the performance of a polytree of caches. This work has now been published in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid36" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid67" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Caching policies</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid37" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, G. Neglia and D. Tsigkari, in collaboration with D. Carra (Univ. of Verona), M. Feng (Akamai Technologies), V. Janardhan (Akamai Technologies) and P. Michiardi (Eurecom), present a new cache replacement policy that takes advantage of a hierarchical caching architecture, and, in particular, of access-time difference between memory and hard disk. They prove that the proposed policy is optimal when requests follow the independent reference model, and significantly reduces the hard-disk load, as they show through their realistic trace-driven evaluation.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid68" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Analyzing Caching and Shaping Timeline Networks</bodyTitle>
        <p>Cache networks are one of the building blocks of information centric networks (ICNs). Most of the recent work on cache networks has focused on networks of request driven caches, which are populated based on users requests for content generated by publishers. However, user generated content still poses the most pressing challenges. For such content timelines are the de facto sharing solution. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid38" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, A. Reiffers-Masson (PhD student in <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> at the time of submission) and E. Altman in collaboration with E. Hargreaves, W. Caarls and D. Sadoc Menasché from UFRJ (Brazil) establish a connection between timelines and publisher-driven caches. We propose simple models and metrics to analyze publisher-driven caches, allowing for variable-sized objects. Then, we design two efficient algorithms for timeline workload shaping, leveraging admission and price control in order, for instance, to aid service providers to attain prescribed service level agreements.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid69" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Cooperative view on Caching</bodyTitle>
        <p>The non-cooperative nature of relations between
economic actors in todays networks may lead to inefficiencies and
may not provide incentives for investing in deploying new technologies.
In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid39" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> E. Altman in cooperation with
V. Douros and S. Elayoubi (Orange Labs) in collaboration with
Y. Hayel (UAPV) have studied
the question of how to split costs for deploying caches
between Content Providers and Internet Service Providers.
They have designed the cost sharing by casting the problem into
a coalition game which they solved using the Shapely value concept.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid70" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Streaming optimization</bodyTitle>
        <p>The Quality of Experience (QoE) of streaming service is often degraded by frequent play-back interruptions. To mitigate the interruptions, the media player prefetches streaming contents before starting playback, at a cost of initial delay.
In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid40" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, Y. Yu and Y. Yu from Fudan Univ. in collaboration with S. Elayoubi (Orange Labs) R. El-Azouzi (UAPV) and E. Altman, study the QoE of streaming from the perspective of flow dynamics. Firstly, a framework is developed for QoE when streaming users join the network randomly and leave after downloading completion. We model the distribution of prefetching delay using partial differential equations (PDEs), and the probability generating function of playout buffer starvations using ordinary differential equations (ODEs) for constant bit-rate (CBR) streaming. Explicit form starvation probabilities and mean start-up delay are obtained. Secondly, we extend our framework to characterize the throughput variation caused by opportunistic scheduling at the base station, and the playback variation of variable bit-rate (VBR) streaming. Our study reveals that the flow dynamics is the fundamental reason of playback starvation. The QoE of streaming service is dominated by the first moments such as the average throughput of opportunistic scheduling and the mean playback rate. While the variances of throughput and playback rate have very limited impact on starvation behavior in practice.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid71" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Advances in Methodological Tools</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
          <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
          <lastname>Altman</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
          <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
          <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
          <firstname>Alain</firstname>
          <lastname>Jean-Marie</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid72" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Control theory</bodyTitle>
        <p>Linear programming formulations for the discounted and long-run
average Markov Decision Processes have evolved along separate
trajectories. In 2006, E. Altman conjectured that the linear
programming formulations of these two models are, most likely, a
manifestation of general properties of singularly perturbed linear
programs. In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid41" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov in
collaboration with J. Filar and A. Stillman (Flinders Univ.,
Australia) and V. Gaitsgory (Macquarie Univ., Australia) demonstrate
that this is, indeed, the case.</p>
        <p>A. Jean-Marie, together with E. Hyon (Univ. Paris-Ouest Nanterre
La Défense), completed the analysis of optimal admission control in
a single-server queue with impatience. In the presence of a
server startup cost, linear holding costs for the queue and individual
costs for departures due to impatience, the optimal policy is to either
serve customers whenever some are present, or never serve any customer.
The situation is decided by a simple criterion comparing the cost of
starting the server to a combination of the other parameters. Proving
the optimality of such a simple policy is more difficult than expected,
and involves the propagation of properties through the dynamic programming
operator of a suitably approximated sequence of problems, following
methods and results of Blok, Bhulai and Spieksma.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid73" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Game theory</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid74" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Uniqueness of equilibrium</bodyTitle>
          <p>E. Altman in cooperation with M. Kumar (IIT Mumbai) and R.
Sundaresan (IICs) have derived in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid42" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> a new sufficient
condition for uniqueness of equilibrium which extends
the Diagonal Strict Concavity condition of Rosen.
They further apply the condition to various networking examples.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid75" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Hybrid games</bodyTitle>
          <p>In collaboration with V. Gaitsgory, I. Brunetti (former member of
<span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span>) and E. Altman have studied in <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid43" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> a
non-zero sum game in which there are two components of the state
space: one is a finite (controlled) Markov chain and the other is a
vector of real numbers. Only the Markov chain is controlled; the
other part of the state space evolves according to some differential
equations whose parameters are the state and actions of the Markov
chain. The authors have shown the existence of an asymptotic
stationary equilibrium. They show how to derive epsilon equilibria
policies for the original problem based on policies that are
asymptotically equilibria.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid76" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Finite games</bodyTitle>
          <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid44" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov in collaboration with V.V. Singh (LRI,
Univ. Paris-Sud 11, France) consider coalition formation among players in an
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>n</mi></math></formula>-player finite strategic game over infinite horizon. At each time a randomly formed
coalition makes a joint deviation from a current action profile such that at new action
profile all the players from the coalition are strictly benefited.
Such deviations define a coalitional better-response (CBR) dynamics that is in general stochastic.
The CBR dynamics either converges to a <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>K</mi></math></formula>-stable equilibrium or becomes stuck in a closed cycle.
We also assume that at each time a selected coalition makes mistake in deviation with small
probability that add mutations (perturbations) into CBR dynamics. We prove that all
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>K</mi></math></formula>-stable equilibria and all action profiles from closed cycles, that have minimum stochastic
potential, are stochastically stable. Similar statement holds for strict <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>K</mi></math></formula>-stable equilibria.
We apply the CBR dynamics to study the dynamic formation of the networks in the presence of mutations.
Under the CBR dynamics all strongly stable networks and closed cycles of networks are stochastically stable.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid77" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Dynamic Games</bodyTitle>
          <p>In a collaboration with M. Tidball (INRA, France), A. Jean-Marie
considered the extension of an infinite-horizon dynamic game of
groundwater extension <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid45" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, due to Provencher
and Burt. As usual in this kind of models, the
marginal extraction cost depends on the level of the groundwater. The
goal of this paper is to point out the importance of the moment where
this cost is announced to the players. We consider the case where the
cost is announced before the extraction is made and the case where is
announced after extractions. For both cases, we also analyse the
possibility of taking into account the rainfall or not. The current
literature considers only the case where the cost is announced before
rain and harvesting. We characterize the equilibrium in the
linear-quadratic case. We compare solutions as functions of the
discount factor, with the particular cases of zero discount (myopic
model) and no discount (maximization of the steady state) from the
economic and the environmental points of view. We show that when the
level of the groundwater is small, announcing costs after harvesting
and rainfall is better from the economic and environmental point of
view than the case of announcing it before harvesting and rainfall.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid78" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Queueing Theory</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid79" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Retrial queues</bodyTitle>
          <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid46" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov in collaboration
with E. Morozov (Karelian Institute of Applied Mathematical Research, Russia)
and B. Steyaert (Gent Univ., Belgium) study multi-class retrial queueing
systems with Poisson inputs, general service times, and an arbitrary numbers
of servers and waiting places. A class-<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>i</mi></math></formula> blocked customer joins orbit <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>i</mi></math></formula>
and waits in the orbit for retrial. Orbit <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>i</mi></math></formula> works like a single-server
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mo>·</mo><mo>/</mo><mi>M</mi><mo>/</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></math></formula> queueing system with exponential retrial
time regardless of the orbit size. Such retrial systems are referred
to as retrial systems with constant retrial rate.
Our model is motivated by several telecommunication applications,
such as wireless multi-access systems, optical networks and transmission
control protocols, but represents independent
theoretical interest as well. Using a regenerative approach,
we provide sufficient stability conditions
which have a clear probabilistic interpretation. We show
that the provided sufficient conditions are
in fact also necessary, in the case of a single-server system
without waiting space and in the case of
symmetric classes. We also discuss a very interesting case,
when one orbit is unstable, whereas the
rest of the system is stable.</p>
          <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid47" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov in collaboration with
E. Morozov, R. Nekrasova (Karelian Institute of Applied Mathematical Research, Russia),
and B. Steyaert (Gent Univ., Belgium)
study the stability of a single-server retrial queueing system with constant retrial rate, general input and
service processes. First, we present a review of some relevant recent results related to the stability criteria
of similar systems. Sufficient stability conditions were obtained by (Avrachenkov and Morozov, 2014), which hold
for a rather general retrial system. However, only in case of Poisson input an explicit expression is provided;
otherwise one has to rely on simulation. On the other hand, the stability criteria derived by (Lillo, 1996) can
be easily computed, but only hold for the case of exponential service times.
We present new sufficient stability conditions, which are less tight than the ones obtained by (Avrachenkov
and Morozov, 2010), but have an analytical expression under rather general assumptions. A key assumption
is that interarrival times belongs to the class of <i>new better than used</i> (NBU) distributions. We illustrate
the accuracy of the condition based on this assumption (in comparison with known conditions when possible) for
a number of non-exponential distributions.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid80" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Polling Systems</bodyTitle>
          <p>In <ref xlink:href="#maestro-2016-bid48" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> K. Avrachenkov in collaboration with
E. Perel and U. Yechiali (Tel Aviv Univ., Israel)
consider a system of two separate finite-buffer
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>M</mi><mo>/</mo><mi>M</mi><mo>/</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></math></formula> queues served by a single server,
where the switching mechanism between the queues is threshold-based,
determined by the queue which is not being served.
Applications may be found in data centers, smart traffic-light control
and human behavior. We analyse both work-conserving and non-work-conserving
policies. We present occasions where the non-work-conserving policy is more
economical than the work-conserving policy when high switching costs are involved.
An intrinsic feature of the process is an oscillation phenomenon:
when the occupancy of one queue decreases, the occupancy of the other queue increases.
This fact is illustrated and discussed. By formulating the system as a three-dimensional
continuous-time Markov chain we provide a probabilistic analysis of the system and investigate
the effects of buffer sizes and arrival rates, as well as service rates, on the system's performance.
Numerical examples are presented and extreme cases are investigated.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </resultats>
  <contrats id="uid81">
    <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid82" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members are involved in the</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid83">
          <p noindent="true">Inria Nokia Bell Labs joint laboratory:
the joint laboratory consists of six ADRs (Action de
Recherche/Research Action) in its second phase (starting October
2012). <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members participate in two ADRs (see
§<ref xlink:href="#uid85" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and §<ref xlink:href="#uid88" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>).</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid84">
          <p noindent="true">Inria <span class="smallcap" align="left">Alstom</span> joint laboratory:
the joint laboratory consists of four projects. <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members
participate in project P11 (see §<ref xlink:href="#uid91" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>).</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <subsection id="uid85" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ADR “Self-Organized Networks in Wireless” (July 2008 – September 2016)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
            <lastname>Altman</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid86">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Contractor</em>: Nokia Bell Labs (<ref xlink:href="http://www.bell-labs.com" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>bell-labs.<allowbreak/>com</ref>)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid87">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Collaborator</em>: Laurent Roullet (coordinator).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p>Coordinator for Inria: Eric Fleury (team <span class="smallcap" align="left">Dante</span>).</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid88" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ADR “Network Science” (June 2013 – March 2017)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
            <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
            <moreinfo>coordinator</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="moais-2014-idp91576">
            <firstname>Guillaume</firstname>
            <lastname>Huard</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp83496">
            <firstname>Jithin</firstname>
            <lastname>Kazhuthuveettil Sreedharan</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
            <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid89">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Contractor</em>: Nokia Bell Labs (<ref xlink:href="http://www.bell-labs.com" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>bell-labs.<allowbreak/>com</ref>)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid90">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Collaborators</em>: Philippe Jacquet (coordinator), Alonso Silva.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p>“Network Science” aims at
understanding the structural properties and the dynamics of various
kind of large scale, possibly dynamic, networks in telecommunication (e.g., the Internet,
the web graph, peer-to-peer networks), social science (e.g., community
of interest, advertisement, recommendation systems), bibliometrics (e.g., citations,
co-authors), biology (e.g., spread of an epidemic, protein-protein interactions),
and physics. The complex networks encountered in these areas share common properties
such as power law degree distribution, small average distances,
community structure, etc. Many general questions/applications (e.g., community detection,
epidemic spreading, search, anomaly detection) are common in various disciplines and
are being analyzed in this ADR “Network Science”. In particular, in the framework
of this ADR we are interested in efficient network sampling.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid91" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Project P11 “Data Communication Network Performance” (December 2013 – May 2016)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
            <firstname>Sara</firstname>
            <lastname>Alouf</lastname>
            <moreinfo>coordinator</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
            <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idm27080">
            <firstname>Philippe</firstname>
            <lastname>Nain</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
            <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
            <firstname>Alina</firstname>
            <lastname>Tuholukova</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid92">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Contractor</em>: <span class="smallcap" align="left">Alstom</span> Transport (<ref xlink:href="http://www.alstom.com/transport/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>alstom.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>transport/</ref>)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid93">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Collaborators</em>: Pierre Cotelle, Pascal Derouet (coordinator from November 2015),
Pierre Dersin, Sébastien Simoens (coordinator until October 2015).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p>The objective of this study is to build a simulation platform (see §<ref xlink:href="#uid32" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>)
and develop an evaluation methodology for predicting Quality of Service and
availability of the various applications supported by the data
communication system of train networks.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid94" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>“Hybrid GPS-free Localization Algorithms” (May 2016 – October 2016)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
            <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
            <moreinfo>coordinator</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2016-idp170944">
            <firstname>Dimitra</firstname>
            <lastname>Politaki</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid95">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Contractor</em>: <span class="smallcap" align="left">Lucie Labs</span> (<ref xlink:href="http://www.lucielabs.com/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>lucielabs.<allowbreak/>com/</ref>)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid96">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Collaborators</em>: François Mazard.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p>G. Neglia and D. Tsigkari, together with F. Mazard (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Lucie Labs</span>) did a literature survey of localization algorithms that could be deployed in Lucie Labs entertainment wristbands. They proposed a localization algorithm that combines information from Bluetooth and WiFi connectivity in a centralized way.
This activity was partially funded by AMIES (Agence pour les Mathématiques en Interaction avec l’Entreprise et la Société).</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid97" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid98" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Huawei CIFRE on the topic “Scalable Online Algorithms for SDN controllers” (June 2016 – May 2019)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="maestro-2016-idp161040">
            <firstname>Zaid</firstname>
            <lastname>Allybokus</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
            <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid99">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Contractor</em>: Huawei Technologies (<ref xlink:href="http://www.huawei.com/en/about-huawei/research-development" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>huawei.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>en/<allowbreak/>about-huawei/<allowbreak/>research-development</ref>)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid100">
            <p noindent="true"><em style="UNDERLINE">Collaborators</em>: Jérémie Leguay et Lorenzo Maggi</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p>Software-Defined Networking (SDN) technologies have radically transformed network architectures. They provide programmable data planes that can be configured from a remote controller platform.</p>
        <p>The objective of this CIFRE thesis is to provide fundamental answers on how powerful SDN controller platforms could solve large online flow problems to optimize networks in real-time and in a distributed or semi-distributed fashion.
We plan to use methods from both optimization and dynamic programming.
</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </contrats>
  <partenariat id="uid101">
    <bodyTitle>Partnerships and Cooperations</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid102" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>National Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid103" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ANR Marmote</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
            <firstname>Alain</firstname>
            <lastname>Jean-Marie</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp74744">
            <firstname>Issam</firstname>
            <lastname>Rabhi</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid104">
            <p noindent="true">ANR Program: Modèles Numériques (MN) 2012, number ANR-12-MONU-0019</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid105">
            <p noindent="true">Project title: MARkovian MOdeling Tools and Environments</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid106">
            <p noindent="true">Duration: January 2013 - June 2017</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid107">
            <p noindent="true">Coordinator: Alain Jean Marie (Inria)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid108">
            <p noindent="true">Partners: Inria (project-teams <span class="smallcap" align="left">Dyogene</span>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Mescal</span>), Univ. Versailles-Saint-Quentin (DAVID lab.), Telecom SudParis (SAMOVAR lab.), Univ. Paris-Est Créteil (LACL), and Univ. Pierre-et-Marie-Curie (LIP6)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid109">
            <p noindent="true">Abstract:
<span class="smallcap" align="left">Anr</span> <span class="smallcap" align="left">Marmote</span> aims, among other goals, at realizing the prototype of a software environment dedicated to
modeling with Markov chains. It brings together seven partner teams,
expert in Markovian analysis, who will develop advanced solution
algorithms and applications in different scientific domains:
reliability, distributed systems, biology, physics and economics.</p>
            <p>
              <ref xlink:href="https://wiki.inria.fr/MARMOTE/Welcome" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>wiki.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>MARMOTE/<allowbreak/>Welcome</ref>
            </p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid110" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>European Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid111" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Collaborations in European Programs, Except FP7 &amp; H2020</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
            <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid112">
            <p noindent="true">Program: EU COST</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid113">
            <p noindent="true">Project acronym: ACROSS</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid114">
            <p noindent="true">Project title: Autonomous Control for a Reliable Internet of Services</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid115">
            <p noindent="true">Duration: November 2013 - November 2017</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid116">
            <p noindent="true">Coordinator: Rob Van Der Mei (CWI) and J.L. Van Den Berg (TNO), The Netherlands</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid117">
            <p noindent="true">Other partners: see <ref xlink:href="http://www.cost-across.nl/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>cost-across.<allowbreak/>nl/</ref></p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid118">
            <p noindent="true">Abstract: Currently, we are witnessing a paradigm shift from the traditional information-oriented
Internet into an Internet of Services (IoS). This transition opens up virtually unbounded possibilities
for creating and deploying new services. Eventually, the ICT landscape will migrate into a global
system where new services are essentially large-scale service chains, combining and integrating
the functionality of (possibly huge) numbers of other services offered by third parties, including
cloud services. At the same time, as our modern society is becoming more and more dependent on
ICT, these developments raise the need for effective means to ensure quality and reliability of the
services running in such a complex environment. Motivated by this, the aim of this Action is to
create a European network of experts, from both academia and industry, aiming at the development
of autonomous control methods and algorithms for a reliable and quality-aware IoS.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid119">
            <p noindent="true">Program: EU COST</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid120">
            <p noindent="true">Project acronym: COSTNET</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid121">
            <p noindent="true">Project title: European Cooperation for Statistics of Network Data Science</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid122">
            <p noindent="true">Duration: May 2016 - April 2020</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid123">
            <p noindent="true">Coordinator: Ernst Wit (NL), Gesine Reinert (UK)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid124">
            <p noindent="true">Other partners: see <ref xlink:href="http://www.cost.eu/COST_Actions/ca/CA15109" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>cost.<allowbreak/>eu/<allowbreak/>COST_Actions/<allowbreak/>ca/<allowbreak/>CA15109</ref></p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid125">
            <p noindent="true">Abstract: A major challenge in many modern economic, epidemiological, ecological and biological questions is to understand the randomness in the network structure of the entities they study: for example, the SARS epidemic showed how preventing epidemics relies on a keen understanding of random interactions in social networks, whereas progress in curing complex diseases is aided by a robust data-driven network approach to biology.</p>
            <p>Although analysis of data on networks goes back to at least the 1930s, the importance of statistical network modelling for many areas of substantial science has only been recognized in the past decade. The USA is at the forefront of institutionalizing this field of science through various interdisciplinary projects and networks. Also in Europe there are excellent statistical network scientists, but until now cross-disciplinary collaboration has been slow.</p>
            <p>This Action aims to facilitate interaction and collaboration between diverse groups of statistical network modellers, establishing a large and vibrant interconnected and inclusive community of network scientists. The aim of this interdisciplinary Action is two-fold. On the scientific level, the aim is to critically assess commonalities and opportunities for cross-fertilization of statistical network models in various applications, with a particular attention to scalability in the face of Big Data. On a meta-level, the aim is to create a broad community which includes researchers across the whole of Europe and at every stage in their scientific career and to facilitate contact with stakeholders.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid126" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid127" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria Associate Teams Not Involved in an Inria International Labs</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid128" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>
            <ref xlink:href="https://team.inria.fr/thanes/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">THANES</ref>
          </bodyTitle>
          <participants>
            <person key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
              <firstname>Eitan</firstname>
              <lastname>Altman</lastname>
            </person>
            <person key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
              <firstname>Konstantin</firstname>
              <lastname>Avrachenkov</lastname>
            </person>
            <person key="maestro-2014-idp83496">
              <firstname>Jithin</firstname>
              <lastname>Kazhuthuveettil Sreedharan</lastname>
            </person>
            <person key="maestro-2014-idm27080">
              <firstname>Philippe</firstname>
              <lastname>Nain</lastname>
            </person>
            <person key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
              <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
              <lastname>Neglia</lastname>
            </person>
          </participants>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid129">
              <p noindent="true">Title: THeory and Application of NEtwork Science</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid130">
              <p noindent="true">International Partners (Institution - Laboratory - Researcher):</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid131">
                  <p noindent="true">CMU (Brazil)
- Department of Computer Science - Bruno Ribeiro</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid132">
                  <p noindent="true">UFRJ (Brazil)
- Department of Computer and Systems Engineering - Edmundo de Souza e Silva, Daniel Ratton Figueiredo, Daniel Sadoc</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid133">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: 2014 – 2017</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid134">
              <p noindent="true">See also: <ref xlink:href="https://team.inria.fr/thanes/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>team.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>thanes/</ref></p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid135">
              <p noindent="true">Our goal is to study how services in Online Social Networks (OSN) can be efficiently designed and managed. This research requires to answer 3 main questions: 1) How can the topology of an OSN be discovered? Many services need or can take advantage of some knowledge of the network structure that is usually not globally available and in any case changes continuously due to structural dynamics. 2) How does services' adoption spread across the OSN? On the one hand the popularity of a service is determined by word-of-mouth through the links of the OSN and, on the other end, the service may contribute to reshape the structure of the OSN (e.g. by creating new connections). 3) How do different services compete for the finite attention and money of OSN users? In particular our purpose is to provide analytical models (corroborated by simulations and experiments on real networks) to understand such complex interactions.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid136" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria International Partners</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid137" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Informal International Partners</bodyTitle>
          <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> has continued collaborations with researchers from
GERAD, Univ. Montreal (Canada), Flinders Univ. (Australia), National
Univ. of Rosario (Argentina), Technion - Israel Institute of
Technology (Israel), Univ. of Arizona (USA), Univ. of Illinois at
Urbana-Champaign (USA), Univ. of Liverpool (UK), Univ. of
Massachusetts at Amherst (USA), Univ. of Florence (Italy), Univ. of Palermo (Italy), Univ. of
Twente (The Netherlands) and Petrozavodsk State Univ. (Russia);
Ghent Univ. (Belgium); see Sections <ref xlink:href="#uid160" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and
<ref xlink:href="#uid272" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid138" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Participation in Other International Programs</bodyTitle>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> has continued collaborations with researchers from IIT Mumbai and IISc Bangalore. In 2015, these collaborations where partly supported by IFCAM and Cefipra.</p>
        <subsection id="uid139" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid140">
              <p noindent="true">
                <b> DyGaMe</b>
              </p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid141">
              <p noindent="true">Title: Dynamic Games Methods: theory, algorithmics and application</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid142">
              <p noindent="true">International Partners (Institution - Laboratory - Researcher):</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid143">
                  <p noindent="true">Univ. de Chile (Chile)
- Department of Industrial Engineering - Fernando Ordóñez</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid144">
                  <p noindent="true">Univ. Nacional de Rosario (Argentina)
- Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, Ingeniería y Agrimensura - Eugenio Della Vecchia</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid145">
                  <p noindent="true">CNRS (France)
- LIP6 - Emmanuel Hyon</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid146">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: 2016 - 2017</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid147">
              <p noindent="true">Start year: 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid148">
              <p noindent="true">See also: <ref xlink:href="https://project.inria.fr/dygame" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>project.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>dygame</ref></p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid149">
              <p noindent="true">Stochastic Dynamic Game Theory is developing in Engineering sciences and is in need of more theoretical results, algorithms and applications. This project brings together researchers from Applied Mathematics, Operations Research and Economics, with the objective of contributing to these aspects. It will more specifically concentrate on agent rationality and the game structure, look for efficient solution algorithms by crossing Applied Mathematics and Operations Research techniques, and apply the results to problems originating from, on the one hand, security/conservation concerns, and on the other hand, sustainable development problems.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid150">
              <p noindent="true">
                <b>CEFIPRA Grant Monte Carlo, no.5100-IT1</b>
              </p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid151">
              <p noindent="true">Title: Monte Carlo and Learning Schemes for Network Analytics</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid152">
              <p noindent="true">International Partners (Institution - Laboratory - Researcher):</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid153">
                  <p noindent="true">IIT Bombay (India)
- Department of Electrical Engineering - Prof. V.S. Borkar;</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid154">
                  <p noindent="true">IIS Bangalore (India)
- Department of Electrical Engineering - Prof. R. Sundaresan.</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid155">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: 2014 - 2017</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid156">
              <p noindent="true">Start year: 2014</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid157">
              <p noindent="true">The project aims to approach various computation problems in network analytics by means of Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) and related simulation techniques as well as machine learning algorithms such as reinforcement learning, ant colony optimization, etc. This will include network diagnostics such as ranking, centrality measures, computation on networks using local message passing algorithms, resource allocation issues pertaining to networks and network-based systems such as the internet, peer-to-peer networks, social networks. The work will involve both development of analytical tools and extensive validation thereof using simulation studies. The research will draw upon techniques from graph theory, probability, optimization, and distributed computation.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid158" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Research Visitors</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid159" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits of International Scientists</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid160" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Professors / Researchers</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid161">
              <p noindent="true">Bernardo Amorim</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid162">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 4-8 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid163">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid164">
              <p noindent="true">Vivek Borkar</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid165">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 26-29 May and 4-17 September 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid166">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: IIT Mumbai (India)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid167">
              <p noindent="true">Damiano Carra</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid168">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 22-27 February and 18-22 July 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid169">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Verona (Italy)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid170">
              <p noindent="true">Francesco De Pellegrini</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid171">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 19-22 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid172">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: CREATE-NET (Italy)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid173">
              <p noindent="true">Ioannis Dimitriou</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid174">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 5-10 September 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid175">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Patras (Greece)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid176">
              <p noindent="true">Daniel Figueiredo</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid177">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 4-8 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid178">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid179">
              <p noindent="true">Michele Garetto</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid180">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 4-5 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid181">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Torino (Italy)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid182">
              <p noindent="true">Moshe Haviv</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid183">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 15-19 June 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid184">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Jerusalem (Israel)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid185">
              <p noindent="true">Nidhi Hegde</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid186">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 10-13 June 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid187">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Nokia Bell Labs (France)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid188">
              <p noindent="true">Giulio Iacobelli</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid189">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 11-21 January and 4-8 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid190">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid191">
              <p noindent="true">Philippe Jacquet</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid192">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 1 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid193">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Nokia Bell Labs (France)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid194">
              <p noindent="true">Jean-Yves Le Boudec</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid195">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 2 June 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid196">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: EPFL (Switzerland)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid197">
              <p noindent="true">Emilio Leonardi</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid198">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 6-16 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid199">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Politecnico di Torino (Italy)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid200">
              <p noindent="true">Nelly Litvak</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid201">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 1-4 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid202">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Twente (Netherlands)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid203">
              <p noindent="true">Natalia Markovich</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid204">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 18-27 June 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid205">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Russian Academy of Sciences (Russia)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid206">
              <p noindent="true">Evzey Morozov</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid207">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 21-29 July 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid208">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Petrozavodsk Univ. (Russia)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid209">
              <p noindent="true">Fernando Ordóñez</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid210">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 27-30 September</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid211">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Chile (Chile)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid212">
              <p noindent="true">Sreenath Ramanath</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid213">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 17-27 May 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid214">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: IIT Bombay (India)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid215">
              <p noindent="true">Bruno Ribeiro</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid216">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 10-20 June 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid217">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Carnegie Mellon Univ. (USA)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid218">
              <p noindent="true">Daniel Sadoc</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid219">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 4-8 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid220">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid221">
              <p noindent="true">Matteo Sereno</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid222">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: until March 2016 and 28 Nov-2 Dec 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid223">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Torino (Italy)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid224">
              <p noindent="true">Vinod Sharma</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid225">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 15-30 November 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid226">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: IIS Bangalore (India)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid227">
              <p noindent="true">Flora Spieksma</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid228">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 5-7 July 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid229">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Leiden (Netherlands)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid230">
              <p noindent="true">Rajesh Sundaresan</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid231">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 05-26 May 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid232">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: IIS Bangalore (India)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid233">
              <p noindent="true">Josh Taylor</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid234">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 24 June 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid235">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Toronto (Canada)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid236">
              <p noindent="true">Don Towsley</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid237">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 1-3 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid238">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Massachusetts (USA)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid239">
              <p noindent="true">Kavitha Voleti Veeraruna</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid240">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 17-27 May 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid241">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: IIT Bombay (India)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid242">
              <p noindent="true">Uri Yechiali</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid243">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 15-28 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid244">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Tel Aviv Univ. (Israel)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid245" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Post-doc / Ph.D. students</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid246">
              <p noindent="true">Víctor Bucarey López</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid247">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 27-30 September 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid248">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Chile</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid249">
              <p noindent="true">Ricardo Coelho Silveira</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid250">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: from Sep 2016 until Nov 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid251">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid252">
              <p noindent="true">Eduardo Hargreaves</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid253">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 20-23 June 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid254">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid255">
              <p noindent="true">Yahui Tian</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid256">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: from Jun 2016 until Jul 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid257">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Texas (USA)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid258" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Internships</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid259">
              <p noindent="true">Mikhail Kamalov</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid260">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: from Jun 2016 until Jul 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid261">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Saint Petersburg State Univ. (Russia)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid262">
                  <p noindent="true">Supervisor: Konstantin Avrachenkov</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid263">
              <p noindent="true">Mohamed Lamghari</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid264">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: from Apr 2016 until Aug 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid265">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: UNS (France)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid266">
                  <p noindent="true">Supervisor: Giovanni Neglia</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid267">
              <p noindent="true">Maksim Mironov</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid268">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: from Aug 2016 until Sept 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid269">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: MIPT (Russia)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid270">
                  <p noindent="true">Supervisor: Konstantin Avrachenkov</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid271" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits to International Teams</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid272" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Research Stays Abroad</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid273">
              <p noindent="true">Konstantin Avrachenkov</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid274">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 4 - 8 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid275">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: IIT Mumbai (India)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid276">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 25 April - 5 May 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid277">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology and
Yandex (Russia)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid278">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 10-11 August 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid279">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Aaalto Univ. (Finland)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid280">
              <p noindent="true">Alain Jean-Marie</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid281">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 5 - 16 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid282">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Montreal (Canada)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid283">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 28 March - 1 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid284">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. National of Rosario (Argentina)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid285">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 3 - 14 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid286">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. de Chile (Chile)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid287">
              <p noindent="true">Arun Kadavankandy</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid288">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 12-30 April 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid289">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Yandex (Russia)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid290">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 12-17 July 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid291">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: IIS Bangalore (India)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid292">
              <p noindent="true">Giovanni Neglia</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid293">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 14 - 22 February; 1 - 4 April; 20 - 25 September;
7 - 10 and 25 - 30 October 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid294">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Florence (Italy)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid295">
                  <p noindent="true">Dates: 11 - 16 May; 21 - 23 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid296">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Palermo (Italy)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid297">
              <p noindent="true">Dimitra Politaki</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid298">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: 18 October - 2 November and 12 - 20 December 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid299">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. of Torino (Italy)</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </partenariat>
  <diffusion id="uid300">
    <bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid301" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Promoting Scientific Activities</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid302" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Organisation</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid303" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>General Chair, Scientific Chair</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid304">
              <p noindent="true">S. Alouf and A. Jean-Marie are the general chairs of the 13th
SIGMETRICS/PERFORMANCE Joint International Conference on Measurement
and Modeling of Computer Systems (ACM SIGMETRICS/IFIP PERFORMANCE
2016, Antibes Juan-les-Pins, France).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid305" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Organizing Committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid306">
              <p noindent="true">A. Kadavankandy, J. Kazhuthuveettil Sreedharan,
H. Mykhailenko, D. Politaki, and D. Tsigkari, were in
the local organization committee of the 13th SIGMETRICS/PERFORMANCE
Joint International Conference on Measurement and Modeling of Computer
Systems (ACM SIGMETRICS/IFIP PERFORMANCE 2016, Antibes Juan-les-Pins,
France).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid307">
              <p noindent="true">A. Kadavankandy, H. Mykhailenko, D. Politaki, D. Tsigkari, and
A. Tuholukova were volunteer students at the 13th
SIGMETRICS/PERFORMANCE Joint International Conference on Measurement
and Modeling of Computer Systems (ACM SIGMETRICS/IFIP PERFORMANCE
2016, Antibes Juan-les-Pins, France).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid308">
              <p noindent="true">D. Politaki was a volunteer student at the Journées Cloud 2016,
Nice, France.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid309">
              <p noindent="true">D. Politaki and E. Vatamidou are members of the organizing committee of the workshop “Monde des mathématiques industrielles (MOMI)”, to be held on 27-28 February 2017 at Inria, Sophia Antipolis. Additional information:</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid310">
              <p noindent="true">L. Vermeersch was the local organization chair of the 13th
SIGMETRICS/PERFORMANCE Joint International Conference on Measurement
and Modeling of Computer Systems (ACM SIGMETRICS/IFIP PERFORMANCE
2016, Antibes Juan-les-Pins, France).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid311" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of Conference Steering Committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid312">
              <p noindent="true">E. Altman chairs the Steering Committee of the
Intl. Conference on NETwork Games, COntrol and
OPtimization (this year: NETGCOOP 2016, Avignon, France).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid313" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Selection</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid314" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Conference Program Committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid315">
              <p noindent="true">13th European Workshop on Performance Engineering (EPEW 2016,
Chios, Greece) (<b>A. Jean-Marie</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid316">
              <p noindent="true">IEEE Intl. Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM 2017,
Atlanta, GA, USA) (<b>G. Neglia</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid317">
              <p noindent="true">Intl. Conference on NETwork Games, COntrol and
OPtimization (NETGCOOP 2016, Avignon, France) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid318">
              <p noindent="true">16th Intl. Conference on Next Generation Wired/Wireless Networking
(NEW2AN 2016, St. Petersburg, Russia) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid319">
              <p noindent="true">10th Intl. Conference on Performance Evaluation Methodologies and
Tools (VALUETOOLS 2016, Taormina, Italy) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid320">
              <p noindent="true">31st Intl. Symposium on Computer and Information Sciences (ISCIS 2016,
Krakow, Poland) (<b>A. Jean-Marie</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid321">
              <p noindent="true">17th Intl. Symposium of Dynamic Games and Applications (ISDG 2016,
Urbino, Italy) (<b>E. Altman</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid322">
              <p noindent="true">Intl. Workshop on Bio-inspired
Security, Trust, Assurance and Resilience (BioSTAR 2016, Fairmont, San Jose,
CA, USA) (<b>E. Altman</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid323">
              <p noindent="true">9th Intl. Workshop on Multiple Access Communications (MACOM 2016,
Aalborg, Denmark) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid324">
              <p noindent="true">5th International Conference on Computational Social Networks (CSoNet 2016,
Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid325">
              <p noindent="true">1st Mini-Symposium on Stochastic Models: Methods and Applications
(SAMMA 2016, Rhodes, Greece) (<b>E. Vatamidou</b>);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid326">
              <p noindent="true">13th Workshop on Algorithms and Models for the Web Graph (WAW
2016, Montreal, Canada) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid327" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Session organizer</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid328">
              <p noindent="true">Session on Stochastic Modeling at the
17th Conference of the Société Française de Recherche Opérationnelle et
d'Aide à la Décision (ROADEF 2016, Compiègne, France)
(<b>A. Jean-Marie</b>).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid329" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Journal</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid330" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Editorial Boards</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid331">
              <p noindent="true"><i>ACM Transactions on Modeling and Performance Evaluation of Computing Systems</i> (ToMPECS) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b> since 2015).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid332">
              <p noindent="true"><i>Dynamic Games and Applications</i> (DGAA) (<b>E. Altman</b> since 2011);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid333">
              <p noindent="true"><i>Elsevier Computer Communications</i> (COMCOM) (<b>G. Neglia</b> since 2014);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid334">
              <p noindent="true"><i>IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</i> (ToN) (<b>E. Altman</b> since 2013);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid335">
              <p noindent="true">AIMS (American Institute of Mathematical Sciences)
<i>Journal of Dynamics and Games</i> (JDG) (<b>E. Altman</b> since 2015);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid336">
              <p noindent="true"><i>Performance Evaluation</i> (PEVA) (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b> since 2008);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid337">
              <p noindent="true"><i>Wiley Transactions on Emerging Telecommunications Technologies</i> (ETT) (<b>S. Alouf</b> since July 2016).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid338" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of Advisory Boards</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid339">
              <p noindent="true">E. Altman is Member of the advisory board of
the international journal <i>IRAN Journal of Computer Science</i>
published by University of Tabriz. Since 2016.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid340" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Invited Talks</bodyTitle>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members gave the following keynote lectures/plenary speeches (in alphabetical order):</p>
        <descriptionlist>
          <li id="uid341">
            <p noindent="true">Eitan Altman gave a keynote talk at <i>The International Symposium on Ubiquitous Networking, UNet 2016</i>, Casablanca, May 30 – June 1st, 2016. Title: Game theory applied to SIS Epidemics in Networks.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid342">
            <p noindent="true">Eitan Altman gave a keynote lecture at <i>ITC 28</i> in Würzburg on 15 September 2015. Title: Dynamic Games for Analyzing Competition in the Internet.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid343">
            <p noindent="true">Alain Jean-Marie gave a keynote lecture at the <i>11th Workshop on Retrial Queues (WRQ11)</i>, in Amsterdam, 31 August – 2 September, 2016. Title: Impatient Customers and Optimal Control.</p>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
        <p>and the following invited talks (in alphabetical order):</p>
        <descriptionlist>
          <li id="uid344">
            <p noindent="true"><i>Access-time aware cache algorithms</i>, at UCN'16 Workshop on
Future challenges in User-Centric Networks, Antibes Juan-les-Pins,
France, 14 June a workshop of ACM Sigmetrics / IFIP Performance 2016
(<b>G. Neglia</b>);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid345">
            <p noindent="true"><i>Distributed spectral decomposition and quantum random walk</i>,
at Workshop on critical and collective effects in graphs and networks,
MIPT, Moscow, April 2016 (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid346">
            <p noindent="true"><i>Distributed spectral decomposition and quantum random walk</i>,
at the 20th Conference of the International Linear Algebra Society (ILAS),
Leuven, Belgium, July 2016 (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid347">
            <p noindent="true"><i>Overview and comparison of random walk
based techniques for estimating network averages</i>,
at COSTNET Conference, Ribno, Slovenia, September 2016 (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid348">
            <p noindent="true"><i>Hitting Times in Markov
Chains with Restart and their Applications to Ranking</i>,
at Workshop dedicated to W. Stadje,
Osnabruck, Germany, October 2016 (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>).</p>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid349" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Leadership within the Scientific Community</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid350">
            <p noindent="true">E. Altman is a fellow member of IEEE (Class of 2010).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid351">
            <p noindent="true">E. Altman, A. Jean-Marie and P. Nain are (elected) members of
IFIP WG7.3 on “Computer System Modeling”. E. Altman is also
Member of WG 6.3 of IFIP on Performance of Communication Systems.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid352" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Research Administration</bodyTitle>
        <descriptionlist>
          <label>E. Altman</label>
          <li id="uid353">
            <simplelist>
              <li id="uid354">
                <p noindent="true">is co-responsible of one of the five themes of
the SFR (Structure Fédérative de Recherche) AGORANTIC
(in which Inria is a founding member) entitled
“Digital Culture and Virtual Societies”.</p>
              </li>
            </simplelist>
          </li>
          <label>S. Alouf</label>
          <li id="uid355">
            <simplelist>
              <li id="uid356">
                <p noindent="true">was member of the recruitment committee for junior Inria researchers (CR1, CR2);</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid357">
                <p noindent="true">is member of the scientific committee of the joint laboratory Inria-Alstom since May 2014.</p>
              </li>
            </simplelist>
          </li>
          <label>K. Avrachenkov</label>
          <li id="uid358">
            <simplelist>
              <li id="uid359">
                <p noindent="true">together with Arnaud Legout (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Diana</span> team) and Fabien Gandon (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Wimmics</span> team) is
co-responsible of the multi-disciplinary research theme
(Action Transversale) “Semantic and Complex Networks” at
Inria Sophia Antipolis - Méditerranée.</p>
              </li>
            </simplelist>
          </li>
          <label>A. Jean-Marie</label>
          <li id="uid360">
            <p noindent="true"/>
            <simplelist>
              <li id="uid361">
                <p noindent="true">is the scientific coordinator of Inria activities in
Montpellier (since 2008); as part of this duty, he represents Inria
at the Scientific Council of the Doctoral School “Sciences and Agrosciences”
of the Univ. of Avignon,
at the Regional Conference of Research Organisms (CODOR);</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid362">
                <p noindent="true">is a member of the Steering Committee of the <span class="smallcap" align="left">GDR RO</span>,
a national research initiative on Operations Research sponsored by
the <span class="smallcap" align="left">Cnrs</span>;</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid363">
                <p noindent="true">is Head of project-team <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> since October 2014;</p>
              </li>
            </simplelist>
          </li>
          <label>G. Neglia</label>
          <li id="uid364">
            <simplelist>
              <li id="uid365">
                <p noindent="true">is the scientific delegate for European partnerships for Inria Sophia Antipolis – Méditerranée since 2014;</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid366">
                <p noindent="true">is member of the Inria COST GTRI (International Relations Working Group of Inria's Scientific and Technological Orientation Council since 2016.</p>
              </li>
            </simplelist>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members are in the following committees of Inria Sophia Antipolis-Méditerranée</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid367">
            <p noindent="true">CLFP: Training Committee (<b>S. Alouf</b>, since November 2014);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid368">
            <p noindent="true">CSD: Doctoral Committee (<b>S. Alouf</b>, since February 2006);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid369">
            <p noindent="true">MASTIC: a commission in charge of popularization and regional
and internal scientific animation (<b>D. Politaki</b>, since July 2016);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid370">
            <p noindent="true">NICE: Invited Researchers Committee (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>, since 2010).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members are in charge of the following tasks for the research center and the project-team:</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid371">
            <p noindent="true">Supervision and validation of the project-teams' yearly activity reports (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b>, since 2010);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid372">
            <p noindent="true">Organizing the fortnightly PhD seminars of the research center (<b>D. Politaki</b>, since November 2016);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid373">
            <p noindent="true">Organizing the fortnightly <span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> internal meetings (<b>J. K. Sreedharan</b>, since November 2013).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid374" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Teaching - Supervision - Juries</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid375" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Teaching</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid376">
            <p noindent="true">Licence:</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid377">
                <p noindent="true">G. Neglia, “Probability”, 50.5H, 1st
year Water Engineering degree (L3), niv. of Nice Sophia Antipolis (UNS), France.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid378">
                <p noindent="true">D. Politaki, “Intro Web”, 36H, (L1), UNS, France.</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
          </li>
          <li id="uid379">
            <p noindent="true">Master:</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid380">
                <p noindent="true">S. Alouf, “Performance Evaluation of Networks”, 31.5H, M2 IFI Ubinet,
UNS, France.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid381">
                <p noindent="true">A. Jean-Marie, “Foundations of Network Modeling”, 12H,
MPRI, Univ. Paris Diderot/ENS Ulm/Univ. Paris Saclay, France.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid382">
                <p noindent="true">G. Neglia, “Distributed Optimization and Games”, 31.5H, M2 IFI Ubinet,
UNS, France.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid383">
                <p noindent="true">G. Neglia, responsible for the “Winter School on
Complex Networks”, 22.5H, M1 Computer Science, UNS, France.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid384">
                <p noindent="true">K. Avrachenkov, “Random-walk based algorithms for
complex network analysis” at “Winter School on Complex
Networks”, 2H, M1 Computer Science, UNS, France.</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid385" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Supervision</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid386">
            <p noindent="true">PhD defended:</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid387">
                <p noindent="true">Alexandre Reiffers-Masson, “Competition over
visibility and popularity in on line social networks”,
UAPV, 12 January 2016, advisors: Eitan Altman and
Yezekael Hayel.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid388">
                <p noindent="true">Jithin Kazhuthuveettil Sreedharan,
“Sampling and Inference in Complex Networks”,
Univ. Côte d'Azur, 2 December 2016, advisor:
Konstantin Avrachenkov.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid389">
                <p noindent="true">Nessrine Trabelsi,
“A Generic Framework for User Association and Interference
Management in LTE Cellular Networks”,
UAPV, 20 December 2016, advisors: Eitan Altman and
Rachid El Azouzi.</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
          </li>
          <li id="uid390">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress:</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid391">
                <p noindent="true">Zaid Allybokus, 1 July 2016,
advisors: Konstantin Avrachenkov and Lorenzo Maggi (Huawei).</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid392">
                <p noindent="true">Arun Kadavankandy, “Random Matrix Theory and Complex Networks,” 5 March 2014,
advisors: Konstantin Avrachenkov and Laura Cottatellucci (Eurecom).</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid393">
                <p noindent="true">Hlib Mykhailenko, “Probabilistic approaches for big data analysis,” 1 May 2014,
advisors: Fabrice Huet (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Scale</span> team) and Philippe Nain.</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid394">
                <p noindent="true">Dimitra Politaki, “Greening data center,” 1 February 2016,
advisors: Sara Alouf and Fabien Hermenier (UNS).</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid395">
                <p noindent="true">Alina Tuholukova, “Caching at the Edge: Distributed Phy-aware Caching Policies
for 5G Cellular Networks,” 1 July 2016,
advisors: Petros Elia (Eurecom) and Giovanni Neglia.</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid396" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Juries</bodyTitle>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members participated in the Habilitation (HDR) thesis committees of (in alphabetical order):</p>
        <descriptionlist>
          <li id="uid397">
            <p noindent="true">Patrick Loiseau, “Game theory and statistical learning in
security, privacy and networks”,
Univ. Pierre et Marie Curie (Paris),
8 December 2016 (<b>E. Altman</b> as reviewer and jury president);</p>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
        <p>and in the Ph.D. committees of (in alphabetical order):</p>
        <descriptionlist>
          <li id="uid398">
            <p noindent="true">Alexandre Reiffers-Masson, “Competition over
visibility and popularity in on line social networks”,
UAPV, 12 January 2016 (<b>E. Altman</b> as advisor);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid399">
            <p noindent="true">Nesrine Ben Khalifa, “Evolutionary games with non-uniform
interactions and delays”, UAPV, 16 December 2016 (<b>E.
Altman</b> as examiner).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid400">
            <p noindent="true">Mikael Touati, “Cooperative
Game Theory and Stable Matchings in Networks”,
Telecom ParisTech, 1st December 2016 (<b>E. Altman</b>
as advisor);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid401">
            <p noindent="true">Jithin Kazhuthuveettil Sreedharan,
“Sampling and Inference in Complex Networks”,
Univ. Côte d'Azur, 2 December 2016 (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b> as advisor,
<b>A. Jean-Marie</b> as jury president);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid402">
            <p noindent="true">Nessrine Trabelsi,
“A Generic Framework for User Association and Interference
Management in LTE Cellular Networks”,
UAPV, 20 December 2016 (<b>E. Altman</b> as advisor);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid403">
            <p noindent="true">Osti Prajwal,
“Resource allocation in wireless access network: A queueing theoretic approach”,
Aalto Univ., Helsinki, Finland, 11 August 2016 (<b>K. Avrachenkov</b> as opponent).</p>
          </li>
        </descriptionlist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid404" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Popularization</bodyTitle>
      <p>Activities are presented in chronological order:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid405">
          <p noindent="true">S. Alouf delivered a conference titled
“Comment marche le Web ?” at Lycée Pierre et Marie Curie, Menton, for
one classe of high school students (25 November 2016).</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid406">
          <p noindent="true">D. Politaki participated to the “Fête de la science”
at the Campus Valrose, Nice (13 October 2016) and at the Congress Center, Antibes Juan-les-Pins (22 October 2016). She animated the game “Datagramme” and the programming of Thymio.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid407">
          <p noindent="true">D. Politaki managed two sessions MEDITES in two middle schools (22 November 2016).</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid408">
          <p noindent="true">D. Politaki participated to the Thymio competition (26 November 2016) which was organized by Hackathon Women Creativity 2016 in Nice.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p>D. Politaki is a member of MASTIC, a commission in charge of
popularization and regional and internal scientific animation (since July 2016).</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid409" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Participation in scientific events</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid410" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Conferences and workshops</bodyTitle>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members gave presentations at the following scientific
events (in alphabetical order):</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid411">
            <p noindent="true">9th International Conference on Matrix Analytic Methods in Stochastic Models (MAM9), Budapest, Hungary, 28–30 June 2016 (<b>E. Vatamidou</b>).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid412">
            <p noindent="true">4th International workshop on Big Data and Social Networking Management and Security (BDSN), Barcelona, Spain, 5-7 December 2016 (<b>H. Mykhailenko</b>).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid413">
            <p noindent="true">1st International Conference on Reliability, Safety and Security of Railway Systems (RSSR 2016), Paris, France, 28-30 June 2016, (<b>A. Tuholukova</b>).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid414">
            <p noindent="true">2016 Americal Control Conference (ACC 2016), Boston, USA, July 6-8 2016, (<b>G. Neglia</b>).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid415" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Schools and doctoral courses</bodyTitle>
        <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Maestro</span> members have attended the following events (list in alphabetical order):</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid416">
            <p noindent="true">E3-RSD Summer School on “Efficacité Energétique des Réseaux et Systèmes Distribués” (20H), Dinard, France, 23-27 May 2016 (<b>S. Alouf</b>, <b>D. Politaki</b>);</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid417">
            <p noindent="true">WAW 2015 School on complex networks and graph models (16H),
Eindhoven, Netherlands, 7-8 December 2015 (<b>A. Kadavankandy</b>
and <b>J. K. Sreedharan</b>).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </diffusion>
  <biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" numero="10" titre="Bibliography">
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid60" type="phdthesis" rend="year" n="cite:reiffersmasson:tel-01293468">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="tel-01293468"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Competition over visibility and popularity on Online Social Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2015-idp83544">
            <foreName>Alexandre</foreName>
            <surname>Reiffers-Masson</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Université d’Avignon et des Pays de Vaucluse</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-01293468" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>tel-01293468</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Theses</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid62" type="phdthesis" rend="year" n="cite:Sreedharan">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Sampling and Inference in Complex Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jithin K.</foreName>
            <surname>Sreedharan</surname>
            <initial>J. K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Université Côte d’Azur</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Theses</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid63" type="phdthesis" rend="year" n="cite:Trabelsi">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">A Generic Framework for User Association and Interference Management in LTE Cellular Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2016-idp173424">
            <foreName>Nessrine</foreName>
            <surname>Trabelsi</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">UAPV</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Theses</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid36" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:alouf:hal-01258189">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.peva.2016.01.001"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01258189"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Performance models for hierarchy of caches: Application to modern DNS caches</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
            <foreName>Sara</foreName>
            <surname>Alouf</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp78480">
            <foreName>Nicaise</foreName>
            <surname>Choungmo Fofack</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nedko</foreName>
            <surname>Nedkov</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01567">
        <idno type="issn">0166-5316</idno>
        <title level="j">Performance Evaluation</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">97</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">57-82</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01258189" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01258189</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">Performance Evaluation Methodologies and Tools: Selected Papers from VALUETOOLS 2013.Free access to this article is provided until April 22, 2016 through this personal article link http://authors.elsevier.com/a/1SeQX_3oLTo1G2</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid17" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:altman:hal-01414802">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/TMC.2016.2611507"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01414802"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Adaptive Optimal Stochastic Control of Delay–Tolerant Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Francesco</foreName>
            <surname>De Pellegrini</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Daniele</foreName>
            <surname>Miorandi</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00740">
        <idno type="issn">1536-1233</idno>
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1 - 15</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01414802" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01414802</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid42" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:altman:hal-01340963">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s13226-016-0185-4"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01340963"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Generalising diagonal strict concavity property for uniqueness of Nash equilibrium</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Manjesh Kumar Hanawal</foreName>
            <surname>Hanawal</surname>
            <initial>M. K. H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rajesh</foreName>
            <surname>Sundaresan</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00802">
        <idno type="issn">0019-5588</idno>
        <title level="j">Indian Journal of Pure and Applied Mathematics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">47</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">213-228</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01340963" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01340963</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid11" type="incollection" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01400117">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-49787-7_4"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01400117"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Distributed and Asynchronous Methods for Semi-supervised Learning</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vivek S.</foreName>
            <surname>Borkar</surname>
            <initial>V. S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Krishnakant</foreName>
            <surname>Saboo</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anthony</foreName>
            <surname>Bonato</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Fan Chung</foreName>
            <surname>Graham</surname>
            <initial>F. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pawel</foreName>
            <surname>Pralat</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Algorithms and Models for the Web Graph: 13th International Workshop, WAW 2016, Montreal, QC, Canada, December 14―15, 2016, Proceedings</title>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">10088</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer International Publishing</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">34–46</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01400117" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01400117</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid56" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01402827">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s10479-014-1642-2"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402827"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">On transition matrices of Markov chains corresponding to Hamiltonian cycles</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ali</foreName>
            <surname>Eshragh</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jerzy A.</foreName>
            <surname>Filar</surname>
            <initial>J. A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00143">
        <idno type="issn">0254-5330</idno>
        <title level="j">Annals of Operations Research</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">243</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1-2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">19 - 35</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402827" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402827</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid41" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01399403">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.orl.2016.02.005"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01399403"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Singularly perturbed linear programs and Markov decision processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin E</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K. E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jerzy A</foreName>
            <surname>Filar</surname>
            <initial>J. A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vladimir G</foreName>
            <surname>Gaitsgory</surname>
            <initial>V. G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andrew</foreName>
            <surname>Stillman</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01541">
        <idno type="issn">0167-6377</idno>
        <title level="j">Operations Research Letters</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">44</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">297 - 301</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01399403" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01399403</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid47" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01402904">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s10958-016-2755-8"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402904"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Stability of Constant Retrial Rate Systems with NBU Input</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Evsey</foreName>
            <surname>Morozov</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ruslana</foreName>
            <surname>Nekrasova</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bart</foreName>
            <surname>Steyaert</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01199">
        <idno type="issn">1072-3374</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Sciences</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">214</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">22 - 33</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402904" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402904</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid46" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01402744">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s11134-015-9463-9"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402744"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Sufficient Stability Conditions for Multi-class Constant Retrial Rate Systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>K.</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>E.</foreName>
            <surname>Morozov</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Steyaert</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01651">
        <idno type="issn">0257-0130</idno>
        <title level="j">Queueing Systems</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">82</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1-2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">149 - 171</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402744" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402744</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid26" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01402923">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.3934/jdg.2016016"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402923"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Network formation games with teams</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp91080">
            <foreName>Vikas V</foreName>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <initial>V. V.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid02569">
        <idno type="issn">2164-6066</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Dynamics and Games</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">303 - 318</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402923" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402923</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid48" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01402886">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s11750-015-0408-6"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402886"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Finite-Buffer Polling Systems with Threshold-Based Switching Policy</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Efrat</foreName>
            <surname>Perel</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Uri</foreName>
            <surname>Yechiali</surname>
            <initial>U.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid03145">
        <idno type="issn">1134-5764</idno>
        <title level="j">TOP</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">24</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">541 - 571</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402886" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402886</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid44" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01403039">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403039"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Stochastic Coalitional Better-response Dynamics and Stable Equilibrium</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp91080">
            <foreName>Vikas Vikram</foreName>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <initial>V. V.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid03144">
        <idno type="issn">2074-9872</idno>
        <title level="j">Mathematical Game Theory and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01403039" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403039</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid51" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:bermond:hal-01223288">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1002/jcd.21506"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01223288"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Well Balanced Designs for Data Placement</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="coati-2014-idm26672">
            <foreName>Jean-Claude</foreName>
            <surname>Bermond</surname>
            <initial>J.-C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
            <foreName>Alain</foreName>
            <surname>Jean-Marie</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="abs-2014-idm27264">
            <foreName>Dorian</foreName>
            <surname>Mazauric</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Joseph</foreName>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid02969">
        <idno type="issn">1063-8539</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Combinatorial Designs</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">24</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">55-76</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01223288" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01223288</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid43" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:brunetti:hal-01305355">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01305355"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">On Non-Zero Sum Game Considered on Solutions of a Hybrid System with Frequent Random Jumps</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp77256">
            <foreName>Ilaria</foreName>
            <surname>Brunetti</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vladimir</foreName>
            <surname>Gaitsgory</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid02299">
        <idno type="issn">2153-0785</idno>
        <title level="j">Dynamic Games and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01305355" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01305355</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid61" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:brunetti:hal-01415310">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s13235-016-0208-0"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01415310"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">State-Policy Dynamics in Evolutionary Games</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp77256">
            <foreName>Ilaria</foreName>
            <surname>Brunetti</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yezekael</foreName>
            <surname>Hayel</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid02299">
        <idno type="issn">2153-0785</idno>
        <title level="j">Dynamic Games and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01415310" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01415310</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid52" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:hoteit:hal-01112367">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.comnet.2016.04.006"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01112367"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">On Fair Network Cache Allocation to Content Providers</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="infine-2016-idp181872">
            <foreName>Sahar</foreName>
            <surname>Hoteit</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp79752">
            <foreName>Mahmoud</foreName>
            <surname>El Chamie</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="diana-2014-idm26672">
            <foreName>Damien</foreName>
            <surname>Saucez</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Stefano</foreName>
            <surname>Secci</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00400">
        <idno type="issn">1389-1286</idno>
        <title level="j">Computer Networks</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">103</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">129-142</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01112367" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01112367</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid15" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:louzadapinto:hal-01391264">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.peva.2016.06.004"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01391264"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A framework for information dissemination in social networks using Hawkes processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Julio Cesar C</foreName>
            <surname>Louzada Pinto</surname>
            <initial>J. C. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T C</foreName>
            <surname>Chahed</surname>
            <initial>T. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan C</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E. C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01567">
        <idno type="issn">0166-5316</idno>
        <title level="j">Performance Evaluation</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">103</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">86 - 107</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01391264" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01391264</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid5" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:mazalov:hal-01402858">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.3233/FI-2016-1364"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402858"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Game-Theoretic Centrality Measures for Weighted Graphs</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vladimir</foreName>
            <surname>Mazalov</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Liudmila</foreName>
            <surname>Trukhina</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bulat</foreName>
            <surname>Tsynguev</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00618">
        <idno type="issn">0169-2968</idno>
        <title level="j">Fundamenta Informaticae</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">145</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">341-358</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402858" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402858</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid34" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:neglia:hal-01413636">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/3003977.3003998"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01413636"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Geographical Load Balancing across Green Datacenters</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Matteo</foreName>
            <surname>Sereno</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Giuseppe</foreName>
            <surname>Bianchi</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00010">
        <idno type="issn">0163-5999</idno>
        <title level="j">SIGMETRICS Performance Evaluation Review</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">44</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">64 - 69</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01413636" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01413636</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid57" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:refahi:hal-01390155">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.7554/eLife.14093.048"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01390155"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A stochastic multicellular model identifies biological watermarks from disorders in self-organized patterns of phyllotaxis</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="virtual_plants-2014-idp130000">
            <foreName>Yassin</foreName>
            <surname>Refahi</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Géraldine</foreName>
            <surname>Brunoud</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Etienne</foreName>
            <surname>Farcot</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
            <foreName>Alain</foreName>
            <surname>Jean-Marie</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Minna</foreName>
            <surname>Pulkkinen</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Teva</foreName>
            <surname>Vernoux</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="virtual_plants-2014-idp14624">
            <foreName>Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Godin</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid03038">
        <idno type="issn">2050-084X</idno>
        <title level="j">eLife</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">71</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">50</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01390155" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01390155</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid33" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:tinnirello:hal-01413649">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/TSG.2016.2563039"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01413649"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Large Scale Control of Deferrable Domestic Loads in Smart Grids</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ilenia</foreName>
            <surname>Tinnirello</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laura</foreName>
            <surname>Giarré</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Giuseppe</foreName>
            <surname>Di Bella</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
            <foreName>Alain</foreName>
            <surname>Jean-Marie</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mariano</foreName>
            <surname>Ippolito</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid02722">
        <idno type="issn">1949-3053</idno>
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">9</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01413649" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01413649</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid40" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:yu:hal-01379711">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/TMC.2015.2510629"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01379711"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Flow-Level QoE of Video Streaming in Wireless Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yuedong</foreName>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Salaheddine</foreName>
            <surname>Elayoubi</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rachid</foreName>
            <surname>El-Azouzi</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yinghao</foreName>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00740">
        <idno type="issn">1536-1233</idno>
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">15</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2762 - 2780</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01379711" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01379711</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid14" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:altman:hal-01377948">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01377948"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Finite Improvement Property in a stochastic game arising in competition over popularity in social networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Atulya</foreName>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yezekael</foreName>
            <surname>Hayel</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">NEtwork Games. Optimization and Control</title>
        <loc>Avignon, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01377948" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01377948</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid338325">
          <title>International conference on NETwork Games, COntrol and OPtimization</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">NetGCOOP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid28" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:altman:hal-01378901">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01378901"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Dynamic Games for analyzing competition in the Internet and in on-line social networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Atulya</foreName>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nahum</foreName>
            <surname>Shimkin</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Corinne</foreName>
            <surname>Touati</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">NETGCOOP 2016 - International conference on NEtwork Games. Optimization and Control</title>
        <loc>Avignon, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01378901" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01378901</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid338325">
          <title>International conference on NETwork Games, COntrol and OPtimization</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">NetGCOOP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid29" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:altman:hal-01249188">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-47413-7_1"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01249188"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Resilience of Routing in Parallel Link Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Aniruddha</foreName>
            <surname>Singhal</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Corinne</foreName>
            <surname>Touati</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="crypt-2014-idp71232">
            <foreName>Jie</foreName>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Quanyan</foreName>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <initial>Q.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tansu</foreName>
            <surname>Alpcan</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Emmanouil</foreName>
            <surname>Panaousis</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Milind</foreName>
            <surname>Tambe</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>William</foreName>
            <surname>Casey</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">GameSec 2016 - 7th International Conference on Decision and Game Theory for Security</title>
        <loc>New York, United States</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture notes in computer science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9996</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">3 - 17</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01249188" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01249188</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid401151">
          <title>Conference on Decision and Game Theory for Security</title>
          <num>7</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">GAMESEC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid27" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:altman:hal-01378907">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01378907"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Load Balancing Congestion Games and their Asymptotic Behavior</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Corinne</foreName>
            <surname>Touati</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">NEtwork Games. Optimization and Control</title>
        <loc>AVIGNON, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01378907" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01378907</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid338325">
          <title>International conference on NETwork Games, COntrol and OPtimization</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">NetGCOOP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid13" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:amorim:hal-01413647">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01413647"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Growing Networks Through Random Walks Without Restarts</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bernardo</foreName>
            <surname>Amorim</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Daniel</foreName>
            <surname>Figueiredo</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Giulio</foreName>
            <surname>Iacobelli</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Proceedings of the 7th Workshop on Complex Networks (CompleNet 2016)</title>
        <loc>Dijon, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01413647" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01413647</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid396086">
          <title>Workshop on Complex Networks</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CompleNet</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid7" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01402800">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-42345-6_3"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402800"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Comparison of Random Walk Based Techniques for Estimating Network Averages</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin E</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K. E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vivek S</foreName>
            <surname>Borkar</surname>
            <initial>V. S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp82232">
            <foreName>Arun</foreName>
            <surname>Kadavankandy</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jithin K</foreName>
            <surname>Sreedharan</surname>
            <initial>J. K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Computational Social Networks</title>
        <loc>Ho Chi Minh, Vietnam</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9795</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Hien T. Nguyen and Vaclav Snasel</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">27 - 38</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402800" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402800</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625158">
          <title>International Conference on Computational Social Networks</title>
          <num>5</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CSoNet</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid9" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01399090">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-49787-7_11"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01399090"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">On Mixing in Pairwise Markov Random Fields with Application to Social Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Lenar</foreName>
            <surname>Iskhakov</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Maksim</foreName>
            <surname>Mironov</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anthony</foreName>
            <surname>Bonato</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Fan Chung</foreName>
            <surname>Graham</surname>
            <initial>F. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pawel</foreName>
            <surname>Pralat</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Algorithms and Models for the Web Graph</title>
        <loc>Montreal, Canada</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">10088</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Anthony Bonato and Fan Chung Graham and Pawel Pralat</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">127-139</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01399090" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01399090</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid371586">
          <title>Workshop On Algorithms And Models For The Web-Graph</title>
          <num>13</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">WAW</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid10" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01263811">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01263811"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Distributed Spectral Decomposition in Networks by Complex Diffusion and Quantum Random Walk</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="hipercom2-2014-idp97304">
            <foreName>Philippe</foreName>
            <surname>Jacquet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jithin K.</foreName>
            <surname>Sreedharan</surname>
            <initial>J. K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE Infocom 2016</title>
        <loc>San Francisco, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01263811" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01263811</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid30452">
          <title>Annual IEEE Conference on Computer Communications</title>
          <num>35</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">INFOCOM</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid6" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01401287">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-43904-4_2"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401287"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Subsampling for Chain-Referral Methods</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
            <foreName>Alina</foreName>
            <surname>Tuholukova</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">International Conference on Analytical and Stochastic Modeling Techniques and Applications</title>
        <loc>Cardiff, United Kingdom</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">17 - 31</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401287" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401287</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid110733">
          <title>International Conference on Analytical and Stochastic Modelling Techniques and Applications</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ASMTA</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid8" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:avrachenkov:hal-01403018">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/2896377.2901477"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403018"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Inference in OSNs via Lightweight Partial Crawls</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bruno</foreName>
            <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jithin K</foreName>
            <surname>Sreedharan</surname>
            <initial>J. K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
        <loc>Juan Les Pins, France</loc>
        <title level="s">ACM SIGMETRICS 2016 Proceedings</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01403018" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403018</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid291156">
          <title>International Conference on Measurement and Modeling of Computer Systems</title>
          <num>11</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SIGMETRICS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid31" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:benegiamo:hal-01413637">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/ACC.2016.7525414"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01413637"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Dissecting demand response mechanisms: the role of consumption forecasts and personalized offers</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp76008">
            <foreName>Alberto</foreName>
            <surname>Benegiamo</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Loiseau</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Proceedings of the 2016 American Control Conference (ACC)</title>
        <loc>Boston, MA, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">3225 - 3230</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01413637" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01413637</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid28220">
          <title>American Control Conference</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ACC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid22" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:boularouk:hal-01414045">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01414045"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Interaction Homme Machine pour l'orientation spatiale des malvoyants</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Said</foreName>
            <surname>Boularouk</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Didier</foreName>
            <surname>Josselin</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">SAGEO 2016</title>
        <loc>Nice, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01414045" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01414045</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid400666">
          <title>Atelier OntoGeo "Ontologies Géographiques" associé à la conférence SAGEO</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SAGEO</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid2" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:dandoush:hal-01345425">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/2915371.2915378"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01345425"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">ns-3 Based Framework for Simulating Communication Based Train Control (CBTC) Systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp71784">
            <foreName>Abdulhalim</foreName>
            <surname>Dandoush</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
            <foreName>Alina</foreName>
            <surname>Tuholukova</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
            <foreName>Sara</foreName>
            <surname>Alouf</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sebastien</foreName>
            <surname>Simoens</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Derouet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Dersin</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Workshop on ns-3 (WNS3 '16)</title>
        <loc>Seattle, WA, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">116-123</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01345425" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01345425</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid623889">
          <title>Workshop on ns-3</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">WNS3</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid39" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:douros:hal-01404872">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01404872"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Caching Games between Content Providers and Internet Service Providers</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vaggelis G</foreName>
            <surname>Douros</surname>
            <initial>V. G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Salah Eddine</foreName>
            <surname>Elayoubi</surname>
            <initial>S. E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yezekael</foreName>
            <surname>Hayel</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Valuetools</title>
        <loc>Taormina, Italy</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01404872" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01404872</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid296546">
          <title>International Conference on Performance Evaluation Methodologies and Tools</title>
          <num>2</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">VALUETOOLS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid50" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:gopalasingham:hal-01216869">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01216869"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Generalized Software Defined Network Platform for Radio Access Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Aravinthan</foreName>
            <surname>Gopalasingham</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laurent</foreName>
            <surname>Roullet</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2016-idp173424">
            <foreName>Nessrine</foreName>
            <surname>Trabelsi</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Chung</foreName>
            <surname>Shue Chen</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Abdelkrim</foreName>
            <surname>Hebbar</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Erick</foreName>
            <surname>Bizouarn</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE Consumer Communications and Networking Conference (CCNC)</title>
        <loc>Las Vegas, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01216869" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01216869</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid79235">
          <title>IEEE Consumer Communications and Networking Conference</title>
          <num>13</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CCNC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid21" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:haddad:hal-01291728">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/WCNC.2016.7564917"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01291728"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Mobility State Estimation in LTE</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp73456">
            <foreName>Majed</foreName>
            <surname>Haddad</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="dyogene-2016-idp136032">
            <foreName>Dalia-Georgiana</foreName>
            <surname>Herculea</surname>
            <initial>D.-G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nidham</foreName>
            <surname>Ben Rached</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Véronique</foreName>
            <surname>Capdevielle</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Chung</foreName>
            <surname>Shue Chen</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Ratovelomanana</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference</title>
        <loc>Doha, Qatar</loc>
        <title level="s">10.1109/WCNC.2016.7564917</title>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">IEEE</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01291728" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01291728</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625028">
          <title>IEEE Wireless Communications and Networks Conference</title>
          <num>2017</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">WCNC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid55" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:haddad:hal-01380734">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01380734"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Online Mobile User Speed Estimation: Performance and Tradeoff Considerations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp73456">
            <foreName>Majed</foreName>
            <surname>Haddad</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="dyogene-2016-idp136032">
            <foreName>Dalia-Georgiana</foreName>
            <surname>Herculea</surname>
            <initial>D.-G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Chung</foreName>
            <surname>Shue Chen</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Veronique</foreName>
            <surname>Capdevielle</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE Consumer Communications and Networking Conference (CCNC)</title>
        <loc>Las Vegas, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2017</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01380734" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01380734</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid79235">
          <title>IEEE Consumer Communications and Networking Conference</title>
          <num>13</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CCNC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid53" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:jeanmarie:hal-01276456">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01276456"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">marmoteCore: a software platform for Markov modeling</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
            <foreName>Alain</foreName>
            <surname>Jean-Marie</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp74744">
            <foreName>Issam</foreName>
            <surname>Rabhi</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="no" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">ROADEF: Recherche Opérationnelle et d'Aide à la Décision</title>
        <loc>Compiègne, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Aziz Moukrim</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01276456" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01276456</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid56156">
          <title>Congrès de la Société Française de Recherche Opérationnelle et d'Aide à la Décision</title>
          <num>17</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ROADEF</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid45" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:jeanmarie:hal-01416049">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416049"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Extraction cost: before or after harvesting? Economic and environmental consequences</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idm25584">
            <foreName>Alain</foreName>
            <surname>Jean-Marie</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mabel</foreName>
            <surname>Tidball</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">17th International Symposium on Dynamic Games and Applications</title>
        <loc>Urbino, Italy</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416049" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416049</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid313894">
          <title>International Symposium on Dynamic Games and Applications</title>
          <num>17</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISDG</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid1" type="inproceedings" rend="best" n="cite:josselin:hal-01338081">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01338081"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Sonorous cartography for sighted and blind people</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Didier</foreName>
            <surname>Josselin</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dorian</foreName>
            <surname>Roussel</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Said</foreName>
            <surname>Boularouk</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Abdelberry</foreName>
            <surname>Saidi</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Driss</foreName>
            <surname>Matrouf</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Olivier</foreName>
            <surname>Bonin</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">AGILE’2016 - 19th AGILE International Conference on Geographic Information Science</title>
        <loc>Helsinki, Finland</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01338081" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01338081</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid283203">
          <title>International Conference on Geographic Information Science</title>
          <num>19</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">AGILE</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid49" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:josselin:hal-01414647">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01414647"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Sonorous Cartography for Sighted and Blind People</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Didier</foreName>
            <surname>Josselin</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dorian</foreName>
            <surname>Roussel</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Said</foreName>
            <surname>Boularouk</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Abdelberry</foreName>
            <surname>Saidi</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Driss</foreName>
            <surname>Matrouf</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Olivier</foreName>
            <surname>Bonin</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Agile2016 19th Agile conference on Geographic Information Science</title>
        <loc>Helsinki, Finland</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01414647" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01414647</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid283203">
          <title>International Conference on Geographic Information Science</title>
          <num>19</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">AGILE</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid12" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:kadavankandy:hal-01403048">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403048"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Characterization of L1-norm Statistic for Anomaly Detection in Erdos Renyi Graphs</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp82232">
            <foreName>Arun</foreName>
            <surname>Kadavankandy</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laura</foreName>
            <surname>Cottatellucci</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE CDC 2016</title>
        <loc>Las Vegas, United States</loc>
        <title level="s">Proceedings of IEEE CDC</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01403048" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403048</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid78271">
          <title>IEEE Conference on Decision and Control</title>
          <num>55</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CDC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid16" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:legenvre:hal-01378846">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01378846"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Potential Game approach to virus attacks in network with general topology</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>François-Xavier</foreName>
            <surname>Legenvre</surname>
            <initial>F.-X.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yezekael</foreName>
            <surname>Hayel</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">NETGCOOP 2016 - International conference on NEtwork Games. Optimization and Control</title>
        <loc>Avignon, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01378846" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01378846</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid338325">
          <title>International conference on NETwork Games, COntrol and OPtimization</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">NetGCOOP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid3" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:mykhailenko:hal-01401338">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401338"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Comparison of Edge Partitioners for Graph Processing</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp84760">
            <foreName>Hlib</foreName>
            <surname>Mykhailenko</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="scale-2014-idp68920">
            <foreName>Fabrice</foreName>
            <surname>Huet</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">The 2016 International Conference on Computational Science and Computational Intelligence (CSCI)</title>
        <loc>Las Vegas, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401338" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401338</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625534">
          <title>International Conference on Computational Science and Computational Intelligence</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CSCI</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid4" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:mykhailenko:hal-01401309">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401309"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Which Metrics for Vertex-Cut Partitioning?</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp84760">
            <foreName>Hlib</foreName>
            <surname>Mykhailenko</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="scale-2014-idp68920">
            <foreName>Fabrice</foreName>
            <surname>Huet</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">The 11th International Conference for Internet Technology and Secured Transactions (ICITST)</title>
        <loc>Barcelona, Spain</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401309" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401309</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid108014">
          <title>International Conference for Internet Technology and Secured Transactions</title>
          <num>11</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICITST</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid18" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:neglia:hal-01345437">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-43425-4_23"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01345437"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Performance Evaluation of Train Moving-Block Control</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
            <foreName>Sara</foreName>
            <surname>Alouf</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp71784">
            <foreName>Abdulhalim</foreName>
            <surname>Dandoush</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sebastien</foreName>
            <surname>Simoens</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Dersin</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
            <foreName>Alina</foreName>
            <surname>Tuholukova</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Billion</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Derouet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Gul</foreName>
            <surname>Agha</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Benny Van</foreName>
            <surname>Houdt</surname>
            <initial>B. V.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">13th International Conference on Quantitative Evaluation of SysTems (QEST)</title>
        <loc>Quebec City, Quebec, Canada</loc>
        <title level="s">Quantitative Evaluation of Systems</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">LNCS</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">9826</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName> Springer International Publishing Switzerland</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">348-363</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01345437" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01345437</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid297847">
          <title>International Conference on Quantitative Evaluation of Systems</title>
          <num>13</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">QEST</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid0" type="inproceedings" rend="best" n="cite:neglia:hal-01402425">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01402425"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Access-time aware cache algorithms</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Damiano</foreName>
            <surname>Carra</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mingdong</foreName>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vaishnav</foreName>
            <surname>Janardhan</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pietro</foreName>
            <surname>Michiardi</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2016-idp175904">
            <foreName>Dimitra</foreName>
            <surname>Tsigkari</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">International Teletraffic Congress ITC-28</title>
        <loc>Würzburg, Germany</loc>
        <title level="s">Proc. of ITC-28</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01402425" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01402425</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid320040">
          <title>International Teletraffic Congress</title>
          <num>28</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ITC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid25" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:ramanath:hal-01240266">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01240266"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Optimal User Association in Multi-user MIMO Small Cell Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sreenath</foreName>
            <surname>Ramanath</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="hipercom2-2014-idp95872">
            <foreName>Merouane</foreName>
            <surname>Debbah</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">8th International Conference on Communication Systems and Networks (COMSNETS)</title>
        <loc>Bangalore, India</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01240266" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01240266</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid401001">
          <title>International Conference on Communication Systems and Networks</title>
          <num>8</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">COMSNETS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid38" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:reiffersmasson:hal-01327681">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01327681"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Timelines are Publisher-Driven Caches: Analyzing and Shaping Timeline Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2015-idp83544">
            <foreName>Alexandre</foreName>
            <surname>Reiffers-Masson</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Eduardo</foreName>
            <surname>Hargreaves</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Wouter</foreName>
            <surname>Caarls</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Daniel Sadoc</foreName>
            <surname>Menasche</surname>
            <initial>D. S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">NetEcon</title>
        <loc>Juan-les-Pins, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01327681" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01327681</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid20999">
          <title>ACM SIGCOMM Workshop on Economics of Networked Systems</title>
          <num>11</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">NETECON</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid30" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:trabelsi:hal-01291722">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01291722"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Coordinated Scheduling via Frequency and Power Allocation Optimization in LTE Cellular Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2016-idp173424">
            <foreName>Nessrine</foreName>
            <surname>Trabelsi</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Chung</foreName>
            <surname>Shue Chen</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laurent</foreName>
            <surname>Roullet</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rachid</foreName>
            <surname>El-Azouzi</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium</title>
        <loc>Istanbul, Turkey</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">IEEE/IFIP</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01291722" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01291722</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid79563">
          <title>IEEE IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">NOMS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid23" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:zaaraoui:hal-01332507">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01332507"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Forecast scheduling for mobile users</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Hind</foreName>
            <surname>Zaaraoui</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Zwi</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>Z.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tania</foreName>
            <surname>Jimenez</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">27th IEEE International Symposium on Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Commuinications (PIMRC'16)</title>
        <loc>Valence, Spain</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01332507" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01332507</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid90001">
          <title>IEEE International Symposium on Personal Indoor and Mobile Radio Communications</title>
          <num>27</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">PIMRC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid24" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:zaaraoui:hal-01248529">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01248529"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Beam focusing antenna array technology for non-stationary mobility</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Hind</foreName>
            <surname>Zaaraoui</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Zwi</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>Z.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC)</title>
        <loc>Doha, Qatar</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01248529" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01248529</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid95678">
          <title>IEEE International Wireless Communications and Networking Conference</title>
          <num>2012</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">WCNC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid32" type="techreport" rend="year" n="cite:benegiamo:hal-01292365">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01292365"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Dissecting Demand Response Mechanisms: the Role of Consumption Forecasts and Personalized Offers</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp76008">
            <foreName>Alberto</foreName>
            <surname>Benegiamo</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Loiseau</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">RR-8881</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Inria Sophia Antipolis</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01292365" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01292365</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Research Report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid59" type="techreport" rend="year" n="cite:kadavankandy:hal-01394889">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01394889"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Subgraph Detection with Cues Using Belief Propagation</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp82232">
            <foreName>Arun</foreName>
            <surname>Kadavankandy</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp69104">
            <foreName>Konstantin</foreName>
            <surname>Avrachenkov</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laura</foreName>
            <surname>Cottatellucci</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sundaresan</foreName>
            <surname>Rajesh</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">RR-8974</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Inria Sophia Antipolis</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">18</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01394889" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01394889</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Research Report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid20" type="techreport" rend="year" n="cite:neglia:hal-01323589">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01323589"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Performance Evaluation of Train Moving-Block Control</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
            <foreName>Sara</foreName>
            <surname>Alouf</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp71784">
            <foreName>Abdulhalim</foreName>
            <surname>Dandoush</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sebastien</foreName>
            <surname>Simoens</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Dersin</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
            <foreName>Alina</foreName>
            <surname>Tuholukova</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Billion</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Derouet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">RR-8917</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Inria Sophia Antipolis</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01323589" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01323589</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Research Report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid37" type="techreport" rend="year" n="cite:neglia:hal-01292834">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01292834"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Access-time aware cache algorithms</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Damiano</foreName>
            <surname>Carra</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mingdong</foreName>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Vaishnav</foreName>
            <surname>Janardhan</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pietro</foreName>
            <surname>Michiardi</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2016-idp175904">
            <foreName>Dimitra</foreName>
            <surname>Tsigkari</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">RR-8886</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Inria Sophia Antipolis</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01292834" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01292834</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Research Report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid54" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:chattopadhyay:hal-01331936">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01331936"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Cell planning for mobility management in heterogeneous cellular networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="dyogene-2015-idp81960">
            <foreName>Arpan</foreName>
            <surname>Chattopadhyay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="dyogene-2014-idp64408">
            <foreName>Bartłomiej</foreName>
            <surname>Błaszczyszyn</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01331936" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01331936</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">13 pages, 5 diagrams, 2 plots, 3 images</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid58" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:chattopadhyay:hal-01401007">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401007"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Location Aware Opportunistic Bandwidth Sharing between Static and Mobile Users with Stochastic Learning in Cellular Networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="dyogene-2015-idp81960">
            <foreName>Arpan</foreName>
            <surname>Chattopadhyay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="dyogene-2014-idp64408">
            <foreName>Bartłomiej</foreName>
            <surname>Błaszczyszyn</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp67664">
            <foreName>Eitan</foreName>
            <surname>Altman</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401007" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401007</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">16 Pages, 1 Figure, 1 Table</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid19" type="misc" rend="year" n="cite:neglia:hal-01404854">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-43425-4_23"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01404854"/>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no">
        <title level="m">Performance Evaluation of Train Moving-Block Control</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp70544">
            <foreName>Giovanni</foreName>
            <surname>Neglia</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
            <foreName>Sara</foreName>
            <surname>Alouf</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp71784">
            <foreName>Abdulhalim</foreName>
            <surname>Dandoush</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sebastien</foreName>
            <surname>Simoens</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Dersin</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2015-idp74320">
            <foreName>Alina</foreName>
            <surname>Tuholukova</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Billion</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Derouet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">348 - 363</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01404854" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01404854</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="howpublished">Reliability, Safety and Security of Railway Systems</note>
      <note type="bnote">Poster</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="maestro-2016-bid35" type="misc" rend="foot" n="footcite:poster-dimitra">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Towards exploiting the sun</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="maestro-2016-idp170944">
            <foreName>Dimitra</foreName>
            <surname>Politaki</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="maestro-2014-idp66488">
            <foreName>Sara</foreName>
            <surname>Alouf</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="howpublished">Poster presented at Labex UCN@Sophia General Assembly</note>
    </biblStruct>
  </biblio>
</raweb>
