<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2016">
  <identification id="nachos" isproject="true">
    <shortname>NACHOS</shortname>
    <projectName>Numerical modeling and high performance computing
for evolution problems in complex domains and
heterogeneous media</projectName>
    <theme-de-recherche>Numerical schemes and simulations</theme-de-recherche>
    <domaine-de-recherche>Applied Mathematics, Computation and Simulation</domaine-de-recherche>
    <urlTeam>http://www-sop.inria.fr/nachos/</urlTeam>
    <structure_exterieure type="Labs">
      <libelle>Laboratoire Jean-Alexandre Dieudonné (JAD)</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>CNRS</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>Université Nice - Sophia Antipolis</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <header_dates_team>Creation of the Project-Team: 2007 July 01</header_dates_team>
    <LeTypeProjet>Project-Team</LeTypeProjet>
    <keywordsSdN>
      <term>6.2.1. - Numerical analysis of PDE and ODE</term>
      <term>6.2.7. - High performance computing</term>
    </keywordsSdN>
    <keywordsSecteurs>
      <term>5.3. - Nanotechnology</term>
      <term>5.5. - Materials</term>
    </keywordsSecteurs>
    <UR name="Sophia"/>
  </identification>
  <team id="uid1">
    <person key="castor-2014-idp73584">
      <firstname>Montserrat</firstname>
      <lastname>Argente</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idm26576">
      <firstname>Loula</firstname>
      <lastname>Fezoui</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idm25352">
      <firstname>Marie-Hélène</firstname>
      <lastname>Lallemand Tenkes</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
      <firstname>Stephane</firstname>
      <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idm28072">
      <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
      <lastname>Descombes</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>LJAD, Université Nice Sophia Antipolis, Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
      <firstname>Claire</firstname>
      <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>LJAD, Université Nice Sophia Antipolis, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp70568">
      <firstname>Tristan</firstname>
      <lastname>Cabel</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, ADT SIMON, until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
      <firstname>Raphaël</firstname>
      <lastname>Léger</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by FP7 HPC4E project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
      <firstname>Ludovic</firstname>
      <lastname>Moya</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by FP7 PRACE-4IP project</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
      <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
      <lastname>Viquerat</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, ADT DIOGENeS</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2015-idp71640">
      <firstname>Alexandra</firstname>
      <lastname>Christophe Argenvillier</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2016-idp137360">
      <firstname>Alexis</firstname>
      <lastname>Gobé</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Université de Reims Champagne-Ardenne, Master intern, from Apr 2016 until Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2016-idp137360">
      <firstname>Alexis</firstname>
      <lastname>Gobé</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, from Nov 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2016-idp142416">
      <firstname>Mohamed</firstname>
      <lastname>Mayen</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Polytech Nice Sophia, Master intern from May 2016 until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp78184">
      <firstname>Nikolai</firstname>
      <lastname>Schmitt</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Université Nice Sophia Antipolis</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2015-idp77944">
      <firstname>Van Hieu</firstname>
      <lastname>Nguyen</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Université Nice Sophia Antipolis</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2016-idp149952">
      <firstname>Vincent</firstname>
      <lastname>Vadez</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Polytech Nice Sophia, Master intern, from Jun 2016 until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2015-idp88088">
      <firstname>Nathalie</firstname>
      <lastname>Glinsky Olivier</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>IFSTTA, DTer Méd, Nice, External Collaborator</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp86848">
      <firstname>Liang</firstname>
      <lastname>Li</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>UESTC, Chengdu, China, from Mar 2016 until Feb 2017</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2015-idp76656">
      <firstname>Hao</firstname>
      <lastname>Wang</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>UESTC, Chengdu, China, Visiting PhD student, from Sep 2015 until Aug 2017</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2016-idp159936">
      <firstname>Antonio</firstname>
      <lastname>Tadeu Gomez</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>LNCC, Petropolis, Brazil, from Dec 2016 until Feb 2017</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2014-idp91952">
      <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
      <lastname>Valentin</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>LNCC, Petropolis, Brazil, from Dec 2016 until Feb 2017</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="nachos-2016-idp164992">
      <firstname>Nora</firstname>
      <lastname>Hagmeyer</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Technical University of Munich, Master intern, from Aug 2016 until Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
  </team>
  <presentation id="uid2">
    <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid3" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Overall objectives</bodyTitle>
      <p>The overall objectives of the NACHOS project-team are the design,
mathematical analysis and actual leveraging of numerical methods for
the solution of first order linear systems of partial differential
equations (PDEs) with variable coefficients modeling wave propagation
problems. The two main physical contexts considered by the team are
electrodynamics and elastodynamics. The corresponding applications
lead to the simulation of electromagnetic or seismic wave interaction
with media exhibiting space and time heterogeneities. Moreover, in
most of the situations of practical relevance, the propagation
settings involve structures or/and material interfaces with complex
shapes. Both the heterogeneity of the media and the complex
geometrical features of the propagation domains motivate the use of
numerical methods that can deal with non-uniform discretization
meshes. In this context, the research efforts of the team concentrate
on numerical methods formulated on unstructured or hybrid
structured/unstructured meshes for the solution of the systems of PDEs
of electrodynamics and elastodynamics. Our activities include the
implementation of these numerical methods in advanced 3D simulation
software that efficiently exploit the capabilities of modern high
performance computing platforms. In this respect, our research
efforts are also concerned with algorithmic issues related to the
design of numerical algorithms that perfectly fit to the hardware
characteristics of petascale class supercomputers.</p>
      <p noindent="true" spacebefore="6.0pt">In the case of electrodynamics, the mathematical model of interest is
the full system of unsteady Maxwell equations <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
which is a first-order hyperbolic linear system of PDEs (if the
underlying propagation media is assumed to be linear). This system
can be numerically solved using so-called time-domain methods among
which the Finite Difference Time-Domain (FDTD) method introduced by
K.S. Yee <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> in 1996 is the most popular and which
often serves as a reference method for the works of the team. For
certain types of problems, a time-harmonic evolution can be assumed
leading to the formulation of the frequency-domain Maxwell equations
whose numerical resolution requires the solution of a linear system of
equations (i.e in that case, the numerical method is naturally
implicit). Heterogeneity of the propagation media is taken into
account in the Maxwell equations through the electrical permittivity,
the magnetic permeability and the electric conductivity coefficients.
In the general case, the electrical permittivity and the magnetic
permeability are tensors whose entries depend on space (i.e
heterogeneity in space) and frequency. In the latter case, the
time-domain numerical modeling of such materials requires specific
techniques in order to switch from the frequency evolution of the
electromagnetic coefficients to a time dependency. Moreover, there
exist several mathematical models for the frequency evolution of these
coefficients (Debye model, Drude model, Drude-Lorentz model, etc.).</p>
      <p noindent="true" spacebefore="6.0pt">In the case of elastodynamics, the mathematical model of interest is
the system of elastodynamic equations <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> for
which several formulations can be considered such as the
velocity-stress system. For this system, as with Yee's scheme for
time-domain electromagnetics, one of the most popular numerical method
is the finite difference method proposed by J. Virieux
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> in 1986. Heterogeneity of the propagation media
is taken into account in the elastodynamic equations through the
Lamé and mass density coefficients. A frequency dependence of the
Lamé coefficients allows to take into account physical attenuation
of the wave fields and characterizes a viscoelastic material. Again,
several mathematical models are available for expressing the frequency
evolution of the Lamé coefficients.
</p>
    </subsection>
  </presentation>
  <fondements id="uid4">
    <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid5" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Scientific foundations</bodyTitle>
      <p>The research activities undertaken by the team aim at developing
innovative numerical methodologies putting the emphasis on several
features:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid6">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Accuracy</b>. The foreseen numerical methods should rely on
discretization techniques that best fit to the geometrical
characteristics of the problems at hand. Methods based on
unstructured, locally refined, even non-conforming, simplicial
meshes are particularly attractive in this regard. In addition, the
proposed numerical methods should also be capable to accurately
describe the underlying physical phenomena that may involve highly
variable space and time scales. Both objectives are generally
addressed by studying so-called <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>h</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></math></formula>-adaptive solution strategies
which combine <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>h</mi></math></formula>-adaptivity using local refinement/coarsening of
the mesh and <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>p</mi></math></formula>-adaptivity using adaptive local variation of the
interpolation order for approximating the solution variables.
However, for physical problems involving strongly heterogeneous or
high contrast propagation media, such a solution strategy may not be
sufficient. Then, for dealing accurately with these situations, one
has to design numerical methods that specifically address the
multiscale nature of the underlying physical phenomena.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid7">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Numerical efficiency</b>. The simulation of unsteady problems
most often relies on explicit time integration schemes. Such
schemes are constrained by a stability criterion, linking some space
and time discretization parameters, that can be very restrictive
when the underlying mesh is highly non-uniform (especially for
locally refined meshes). For realistic 3D problems, this can
represent a severe limitation with regards to the overall computing
time. One possible overcoming solution consists in resorting to an
implicit time scheme in regions of the computational domain where
the underlying mesh size is very small, while an explicit time
scheme is applied elsewhere in the computational domain. The
resulting hybrid explicit-implicit time integration strategy raises
several challenging questions concerning both the mathematical
analysis (stability and accuracy, especially for what concern
numerical dispersion), and the computer implementation on modern
high performance systems (data structures, parallel computing
aspects). A second, often considered approach is to devise a local
time stepping strategy. Beside, when considering time-harmonic
(frequency-domain) wave propagation problems, numerical efficiency
is mainly linked to the solution of the system of algebraic
equations resulting from the discretization in space of the
underlying PDE model. Various strategies exist ranging from the
more robust and efficient sparse direct solvers to the more flexible
and cheaper (in terms of memory resources) iterative methods.
Current trends tend to show that the ideal candidate will be a
judicious mix of both approaches by relying on domain decomposition
principles.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid8">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Computational efficiency</b>. Realistic 3D wave propagation
problems involve the processing of very large volumes of data. The
latter results from two combined parameters: the size of the mesh
i.e the number of mesh elements, and the number of degrees of
freedom per mesh element which is itself linked to the degree of
interpolation and to the number of physical variables (for systems
of partial differential equations). Hence, numerical methods must
be adapted to the characteristics of modern parallel computing
platforms taking into account their hierarchical nature (e.g
multiple processors and multiple core systems with complex cache and
memory hierarchies). In addition, appropriate parallelization
strategies need to be designed that combine SIMD and MIMD
programming paradigms.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p noindent="true" spacebefore="6.0pt">From the methodological point of view, the research activities of the
team are concerned with four main topics: (1) high order finite
element type methods on unstructured or hybrid structured/unstructured
meshes for the discretization of the considered systems of PDEs, (2)
efficient time integration strategies for dealing with grid induced
stiffness when using non-uniform (locally refined) meshes, (3)
numerical treatment of complex propagation media models (e.g.
physical dispersion models), (4) algorithmic adaptation to modern high
performance computing platforms.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid9" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>High order discretization methods</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid10" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>The Discontinuous Galerkin method</bodyTitle>
        <p noindent="true">The Discontinuous Galerkin method (DG) was introduced in 1973 by Reed
and Hill to solve the neutron transport equation. From this time to
the 90's a review on the DG methods would likely fit into one page.
In the meantime, the Finite Volume approach (FV) has been widely
adopted by computational fluid dynamics scientists and has now nearly
supplanted classical finite difference and finite element methods in
solving problems of non-linear convection and conservation law
systems. The success of the FV method is due to its ability to
capture discontinuous solutions which may occur when solving
non-linear equations or more simply, when convecting discontinuous
initial data in the linear case. Let us first remark that DG methods
share with FV methods this property since a first order FV scheme may
be viewed as a 0th order DG scheme. However a DG method may also be
considered as a Finite Element (FE) one where the continuity
constraint at an element interface is released. While keeping almost
all the advantages of the FE method (large spectrum of applications,
complex geometries, etc.), the DG method has other nice properties
which explain the renewed interest it gains in various domains in
scientific computing as witnessed by books or special issues of
journals dedicated to this method <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>- <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>- <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>:</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid11">
            <p noindent="true">It is naturally adapted to a high order approximation of the
unknown field. Moreover, one may increase the degree of the
approximation in the whole mesh as easily as for spectral methods
but, with a DG method, this can also be done very locally. In most
cases, the approximation relies on a polynomial interpolation method
but the DG method also offers the flexibility of applying local
approximation strategies that best fit to the intrinsic features of
the modeled physical phenomena.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid12">
            <p noindent="true">When the space discretization is coupled to an explicit time
integration scheme, the DG method leads to a block diagonal mass
matrix whatever the form of the local approximation (e.g. the type
of polynomial interpolation). This is a striking difference with
classical, continuous FE formulations. Moreover, the mass matrix may
be diagonal if the basis functions are orthogonal.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid13">
            <p noindent="true">It easily handles complex meshes. The grid may be a classical
conforming FE mesh, a non-conforming one or even a hybrid mesh made
of various elements (tetrahedra, prisms, hexahedra, etc.). The DG
method has been proven to work well with highly locally refined
meshes. This property makes the DG method more suitable (and
flexible) to the design of some <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>h</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></math></formula>-adaptive solution strategy.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid14">
            <p noindent="true">It is also flexible with regards to the choice of the time
stepping scheme. One may combine the DG spatial discretization with
any global or local explicit time integration scheme, or even
implicit, provided the resulting scheme is stable.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid15">
            <p noindent="true">It is naturally adapted to parallel computing. As long as an
explicit time integration scheme is used, the DG method is easily
parallelized. Moreover, the compact nature of DG discretization
schemes is in favor of high computation to communication ratio
especially when the interpolation order is increased.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p noindent="true" spacebefore="3.0pt">As with standard FE methods, a DG method relies on a variational
formulation of the continuous problem at hand. However, due to the
discontinuity of the global approximation, this variational
formulation has to be defined locally, at the element level. Then, a
degree of freedom in the design of a DG method stems from the
approximation of the boundary integral term resulting from the
application of an integration by parts to the element-wise variational
form. In the spirit of FV methods, the approximation of this boundary
integral term calls for a numerical flux function which can be based
on either a centered scheme or an upwind scheme, or a blending between
these two schemes.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid16" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>High order DG methods for wave propagation models</bodyTitle>
        <p noindent="true">DG methods are at the heart of the activities of the team regarding
the development of high order discretization schemes for the PDE
systems modeling electromagnetic and elatsodynamic wave propagation.</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid17">
            <p noindent="true"><b>Nodal DG methods for time-domain problems</b>. For the
numerical solution of the time-domain Maxwell equations, we have
first proposed a non-dissipative high order DGTD (Discontinuous
Galerkin Time-Domain) method working on unstructured conforming
simplicial meshes <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. This DG method
combines a central numerical flux function for the approximation of
the integral term at the interface of two neighboring elements with
a second order leap-frog time integration scheme. Moreover, the
local approximation of the electromagnetic field relies on a nodal
(Lagrange type) polynomial interpolation method. Recent achievements
by the team deal with the extension of these methods towards
non-conforming unstructured
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid10" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and hybrid
structured/unstructured meshes <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, their
coupling with hybrid explicit/implicit time integration schemes in
order to improve their efficiency in the context of locally refined
meshes
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
A high order DG method has also been proposed for the numerical
resolution of the elastodynamic equations modeling the propagation
of seismic waves
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid15" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid18">
            <p noindent="true"><b>Hybridizable DG (HDG) method for time-domain and
time-harmonic problems</b>. For the numerical treatment of the
time-harmonic Maxwell equations, nodal DG methods can also be
considered <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. However, such DG
formulations are highly expensive, especially for the discretization
of 3D problems, because they lead to a large sparse and undefinite
linear system of equations coupling all the degrees of freedom of
the unknown physical fields. Different attempts have been made in
the recent past to improve this situation and one promising strategy
has been recently proposed by Cockburn <i>et al.</i><ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> in the form of so-called hybridizable
DG formulations. The distinctive feature of these methods is that
the only globally coupled degrees of freedom are those of an
approximation of the solution defined only on the boundaries of the
elements. This work is concerned with the study of such
Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin (HDG) methods for the solution
of the system of Maxwell equations in the time-domain when the time
integration relies on an implicit scheme, or in the
frequency-domain. The team has been a precursor in the development
of HDG methods for the frequency-domain Maxwell equations
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid19" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid20" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid19">
            <p noindent="true"><b>Multiscale DG methods for time-domain problems</b>. More
recently, in collaboration with LNCC in Petropolis (Frédéric
Valentin) the framework of the HOMAR assoacite team, we are
investigating a family of methods specifically designed for an
accurate and efficient numerical treatment of multiscale wave
propagation problems. These methods, referred to as Multiscale
Hybrid Mixed (MHM) methods, are currently studied in the team for
both time-domain electromagnetic and elastodynamic PDE models. They
consist in reformulating the mixed variational form of each system
into a global (arbitrarily coarse) problem related to a weak
formulation of the boundary condition (carried by a Lagrange
multiplier that represents e.g. the normal stress tensor in
elastodynamic sytems), and a series of small, element-wise, fully
decoupled problems resembling to the initial one and related to some
well chosen partition of the solution variables on each element. By
construction, that methodology is fully parallelizable and
recursivity may be used in each local problem as well, making MHM
methods belonging to multi-level highly parallelizable methods. Each
local problem may be solved using DG or classical Galerkin FE
approximations combined with some appropriate time integration
scheme (<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>θ</mi></math></formula>-scheme or leap-frog scheme).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid20" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Efficient time integration strategies</bodyTitle>
      <p>The use of unstructured meshes (based on triangles in two space
dimensions and tetrahedra in three space dimensions) is an important
feature of the DGTD methods developed in the team which can thus
easily deal with complex geometries and heterogeneous propagation
media. Moreover, DG discretization methods are naturally adapted to
local, conforming as well as non-conforming, refinement of the
underlying mesh. Most of the existing DGTD methods rely on explicit
time integration schemes and lead to block diagonal mass matrices
which is often recognized as one of the main advantages with regards
to continuous finite element methods. However, explicit DGTD methods
are also constrained by a stability condition that can be very
restrictive on highly refined meshes and when the local approximation
relies on high order polynomial interpolation. There are basically
three strategies that can be considered to cure this computational
efficiency problem. The first approach is to use an unconditionally
stable implicit time integration scheme to overcome the restrictive
constraint on the time step for locally refined meshes. In a second
approach, a local time stepping strategy is combined with an explicit
time integration scheme. In the third approach, the time step size
restriction is overcome by using a hybrid explicit-implicit procedure.
In this case, one blends a time implicit and a time explicit schemes
where only the solution variables defined on the smallest elements are
treated implicitly. The first and third options are considered in the
team in the framework of DG
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>-<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
and HDG discretization methods.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid21" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Numerical treatment of complex material models</bodyTitle>
      <p>Towards the general aim of being able to consider concrete physical
situations, we are interested in taking into account in the numerical
methodologies that we study, a better description of the propagation
of waves in realistic media. In the case of electromagnetics, a
typical physical phenomenon that one has to consider is <i>dispersion</i>. It is present in almost all media and expresses the way
the material reacts to an electromagnetic field. In the presence of
an electric field a medium does not react instantaneously and thus
presents an electric polarization of the molecules or electrons that
itself influences the electric displacement. In the case of a linear
homogeneous isotropic media, there is a linear relation between the
applied electric field and the polarization. However, above some
range of frequencies (depending on the considered material), the
dispersion phenomenon cannot be neglected and the relation between the
polarization and the applied electric field becomes complex. This is
rendered via a frequency-dependent complex permittivity. Several
models of complex permittivity exist. Concerning biological media,
the Debye model is commonly adopted in the presence of water,
biological tissues and polymers, so that it already covers a wide
range of applications <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid21" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In the context
of nanoplasmonics, one is interested in modeling the dispersion
effects on metals on the nanometer scale and at optical
frequencies. In this case, the Drude or the Drude-Lorentz models are
generally chosen <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid22" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In the context of
seismic wave propagation, we are interested by the intrinsic
attenuation of the medium <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid23" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In realistic
configurations, for instance in sedimentary basins where the waves are
trapped, we can observe site effects due to local geological and
geotechnical conditions which result in a strong increase in
amplification and duration of the ground motion at some particular
locations. During the wave propagation in such media, a part of the
seismic energy is dissipated because of anelastic losses relied to the
internal friction of the medium. For these reasons, numerical
simulations based on the basic assumption of linear elasticity are no
more valid since this assumption results in a severe overestimation of
amplitude and duration of the ground motion, even when we are not in
presence of a site effect, since intrinsic attenuation is not taken
into account.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid22" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>High performance numerical computing</bodyTitle>
      <p>Beside basic research activities related to the design of numerical
methods and resolution algorithms for the wave propagation models at
hand, the team is also committed to demonstrate the benefits of the
proposed numerical methodologies in the simulation of challenging
three-dimensional problems pertaining to computational
electromagnetics and computational geoseismics. For such
applications, parallel computing is a mandatory path. Nowadays,
modern parallel computers most often take the form of clusters of
heterogeneous multiprocessor systems, combining multiple core CPUs
with accelerator cards (e.g Graphical Processing Units - GPUs), with
complex hierarchical distributed-shared memory systems. Developing
numerical algorithms that efficiently exploit such high performance
computing architectures raises several challenges, especially in the
context of a massive parallelism. In this context, current efforts of
the team are towards the exploitation of multiple levels of
parallelism (computing systems combining CPUs and GPUs) through the
study of hierarchical SPMD (Single Program Multiple Data) strategies
for the parallelization of unstructured mesh based solvers.</p>
    </subsection>
  </fondements>
  <domaine id="uid23">
    <bodyTitle>Application Domains</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid24" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Electromagnetic wave propagation</bodyTitle>
      <p>Electromagnetic devices are ubiquitous in present day technology.
Indeed, electromagnetism has found and continues to find applications
in a wide array of areas, encompassing both industrial and societal
purposes. Applications of current interest include (among others)
those related to communications (e.g transmission through optical
fiber lines), to biomedical devices (e.g microwave imaging,
micro-antenna design for telemedecine, etc.), to circuit or magnetic
storage design (electromagnetic compatibility, hard disc operation),
to geophysical prospecting, and to non-destructive evaluation (e.g
crack detection), to name but just a few. Equally notable and
motivating are applications in defence which include the design of
military hardware with decreased signatures, automatic target
recognition (e.g bunkers, mines and buried ordnance, etc.)
propagation effects on communication and radar systems, etc. Although
the principles of electromagnetics are well understood, their
application to practical configurations of current interest, such as
those that arise in connection with the examples above, is
significantly complicated and far beyond manual calculation in all but
the simplest cases. These complications typically arise from the
geometrical characteristics of the propagation medium (irregular
shapes, geometrical singularities), the physical characteristics of
the propagation medium (heterogeneity, physical dispersion and
dissipation) and the characteristics of the sources (wires, etc.).</p>
      <p noindent="true" spacebefore="6.0pt">Although many of the above-mentioned application contexts can
potentially benefit from numerical modeling studies, the team
currently concentrates its efforts on two physical situations.</p>
      <subsection id="uid25" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Microwave interaction with biological tissues</bodyTitle>
        <p noindent="true">Two main reasons motivate our commitment to consider this type of
problem for the application of the numerical methodologies developed
in the NACHOS project-team:</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid26">
            <p noindent="true">First, from the numerical modeling point of view, the
interaction between electromagnetic waves and biological tissues
exhibit the three sources of complexity identified previously and are
thus particularly challenging for pushing one step forward the
state-of-the art of numerical methods for computational
electromagnetics. The propagation media is strongly heterogeneous
and the electromagnetic characteristics of the tissues are frequency
dependent. Interfaces between tissues have rather complicated
shapes that cannot be accurately discretized using cartesian meshes.
Finally, the source of the signal often takes the form of a
complicated device (e.g a mobile phone or an antenna array).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid27">
            <p noindent="true">Second, the study of the interaction between electromagnetic
waves and living tissues is of interest to several applications of
societal relevance such as the assessment of potential adverse
effects of electromagnetic fields or the utilization of
electromagnetic waves for therapeutic or diagnostic purposes. It is
widely recognized nowadays that numerical modeling and computer
simulation of electromagnetic wave propagation in biological tissues
is a mandatory path for improving the scientific knowledge of the
complex physical mechanisms that characterize these applications.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p noindent="true">Despite the high complexity both in terms of heterogeneity and
geometrical features of tissues, the great majority of numerical
studies so far have been conducted using variants of the widely known
FDTD method due to Yee <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In this method, the whole
computational domain is discretized using a structured (cartesian)
grid. Due to the possible straightforward implementation of the
algorithm and the availability of computational power, FDTD is
currently the leading method for numerical assessment of human
exposure to electromagnetic waves. However, limitations are still
seen, due to the rather difficult departure from the commonly used
rectilinear grid and cell size limitations regarding very detailed
structures of human tissues. In this context, the general objective
of the contributions of the NACHOS project-team is to demonstrate the
benefits of high order unstructured mesh based Maxwell solvers for a
realistic numerical modeling of the interaction of electromagnetic
waves and biological tissues with emphasis on applications related to
numerical dosimetry. Since the creation of the team, our works on
this topic have mainly been focussed on the study of the exposure of
humans to radiations from mobile phones or wireless communication
systems (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid28" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). This activity has been
conducted in close collaboration with the team of Joe Wiart at Orange
Labs/Whist Laboratory
<ref xlink:href="http://whist.institut-telecom.fr/en/index.html" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>whist.<allowbreak/>institut-telecom.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>en/<allowbreak/>index.<allowbreak/>html</ref> (formerly, France
Telecom Research &amp; Development) in Issy-les-Moulineaux
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        <object id="uid28">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/E_peau-1.jpg" type="inline" width="153.6447pt" height="128.0374pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/E_crane-1.jpg" type="inline" width="153.6447pt" height="128.0374pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Exposure of head tissues to an electromagnetic wave emitted
by a localized source. Top figures: surface triangulations of the
skin and the skull. Bottom figures: contour lines of the amplitude
of the electric field.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid29" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Light/matter interaction on the nanoscale</bodyTitle>
        <p noindent="true">Nanostructuring of materials has opened up a number of new
possibilities for manipulating and enhancing light-matter
interactions, thereby improving fundamental device
properties. Low-dimensional semiconductors, like quantum dots, enable
one to catch the electrons and control the electronic properties of a
material, while photonic crystal structures allow to synthesize the
electromagnetic properties. These technologies may, e.g., be employed
to make smaller and better lasers, sources that generate only one
photon at a time, for applications in quantum information technology,
or miniature sensors with high sensitivity. The incorporation of
metallic structures into the medium add further possibilities for
manipulating the propagation of electromagnetic waves. In particular,
this allows subwavelength localisation of the electromagnetic field
and, by subwavelength structuring of the material, novel effects like
negative refraction, e.g. enabling super lenses, may be realized.
Nanophotonics is the recently emerged, but already well defined, field
of science and technology aimed at establishing and using the peculiar
properties of light and light-matter interaction in various
nanostructures. Nanophotonics includes all the phenomena that are
used in optical sciences for the development of optical devices.
Therefore, nanophotonics finds numerous applications such as in
optical microscopy, the design of optical switches and electromagnetic
chips circuits, transistor filaments, etc. Because of its numerous
scientific and technological applications (e.g. in relation to
telecommunication, energy production and biomedicine), nanophotonics
represents an active field of research increasingly relying on
numerical modeling beside experimental studies.</p>
        <p noindent="true" spacebefore="3.0pt">Plasmonics is a related field to nanophotonics. Metallic
nanostructures whose optical scattering is dominated by the response
of the conduction electrons are considered as plasmomic media. If the
structure presents an interface with e.g. a dielectric with a positive
permittivity, collective oscillations of surface electrons create
surface-plasmons-polaritons (SPPs) that propagate along the interface.
SPPs are guided along metal-dielectric interfaces much in the same way
light can be guided by an optical fiber, with the unique
characteristic of subwavelength-scale confinement perpendicular to the
interface. Nanofabricated systems that exploit SPPs offer fascinating
opportunities for crafting and controlling the propagation of light in
matter. In particular, SPPs can be used to channel light efficiently
into nanometer-scale volumes, leading to direct modification of mode
dispersion properties (substantially shrinking the wavelength of light
and the speed of light pulses for example), as well as huge field
enhancements suitable for enabling strong interactions with non-linear
materials. The resulting enhanced sensitivity of light to external
parameters (for example, an applied electric field or the dielectric
constant of an adsorbed molecular layer) shows great promise for
applications in sensing and switching. In particular, very promising
applications are foreseen in the medical domain
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>- <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid26" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        <p noindent="true" spacebefore="3.0pt">Numerical modeling of electromagnetic wave propagation in interaction
with metallic nanostructures at optical frequencies requires to solve
the system of Maxwell equations coupled to appropriate models of
physical dispersion in the metal, such as the Drude and Drude-Lorentz
models. Here again, the FDTD method is a widely used approach for
solving the resulting system of PDEs <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid27" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
However, for nanophotonic applications, the space and time scales, in
addition to the geometrical characteristics of the considered
nanostructures (or structured layouts of the latter), are particularly
challenging for an accurate and efficient application of the FDTD
method. Recently, unstructured mesh based methods have been developed
and have demonstrated their potentialities for being considered as
viable alternatives to the FDTD method
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid28" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>- <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid29" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>- <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid30" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
Since the end of 2012, nanophotonics/plasmonics is increasingly
becoming a focused application domain in the research activities of
the team in close collaboration with physicists from CNRS
laboratories, and also with researchers from international
institutions.</p>
        <object id="uid30">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/nano_sphere-mie.jpg" type="inline" width="170.71652pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/nano_sphere-dgtd.jpg" type="inline" width="170.71652pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/nano_sphere-1d.jpg" type="inline" width="248.96161pt" height="149.37697pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Scattering of a 20 nanometer radius gold nanosphere by a
plane wave. The gold properties are described by a Drude dispersion
model. Modulus of the electric field in the frequency-domain. Top
left figure: Mie solution. Top right figure: numerical solution.
Bottom figure: 1d plot of the electric field modulus for various
orders of approximation (PhD thesis of Jonathan Viquerat).</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid31" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Elastodynamic wave propagation</bodyTitle>
      <p>Elastic wave propagation in interaction with solids are encountered in
a lot of scientific and engineering contexts. One typical example is
geoseismic wave propagation, in particular in the context of
earthquake dynamics or resource prospection.</p>
      <subsection id="uid32" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Earthquake dynamics</bodyTitle>
        <p noindent="true">To understand the basic science of earthquakes and to help engineers
better prepare for such an event, scientists want to identify which
regions are likely to experience the most intense shaking,
particularly in populated sediment-filled basins. This understanding
can be used to improve buildings in high hazard areas and to help
engineers design safer structures, potentially saving lives and
property. In the absence of deterministic earthquake prediction,
forecasting of earthquake ground motion based on simulation of
scenarios is one of the most promising tools to mitigate earthquake
related hazard. This requires intense modeling that meets the spatial
and temporal resolution scales of the continuously increasing density
and resolution of the seismic instrumentation, which record dynamic
shaking at the surface, as well as of the basin models. Another
important issue is to improve the physical understanding of the
earthquake rupture processes and seismic wave propagation.
Large-scale simulations of earthquake rupture dynamics and wave
propagation are currently the only means to investigate these
multiscale physics together with data assimilation and inversion.
High resolution models are also required to develop and assess fast
operational analysis tools for real time seismology and early warning
systems.</p>
        <p noindent="true" spacebefore="6.0pt">Numerical methods for the propagation of seismic waves have been
studied for many years. Most of existing numerical software rely on
finite difference type methods. Among the most popular schemes, one
can cite the staggered grid finite difference scheme proposed by
Virieux <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and based on the first order
velocity-stress hyperbolic system of elastic waves equations, which is
an extension of the scheme derived by Yee <ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> for the
solution of the Maxwell equations. Many improvements of this method
have been proposed, in particular, higher order schemes in space or
rotated staggered-grids allowing strong fluctuations of the elastic
parameters. Despite these improvements, the use of cartesian grids is
a limitation for such numerical methods especially when it is
necessary to incorporate surface topography or curved interface.
Moreover, in presence of a non planar topography, the free surface
condition needs very fine grids (about 60 points by minimal Rayleigh
wavelength) to be approximated. In this context, our objective is to
develop high order unstructured mesh based methods for the numerical
solution of the system of elastodynamic equations for elastic media in
a first step, and then to extend these methods to a more accurate
treatment of the heterogeneities of the medium or to more complex
propagation materials such as viscoelastic media which take into
account the intrinsic attenuation. Initially, the team has considered
in detail the necessary methodological developments for the
large-scale simulation of earthquake dynamics
<ref xlink:href="#nachos-2016-bid31" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. More recently, the team has initiated a
close collaboration with CETE Méditerranée
<ref xlink:href="http://www.cete-mediterranee.fr/gb" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>cete-mediterranee.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>gb</ref> which is a regional technical
and engineering centre whose activities are concerned with seismic
hazard assessment studies, and IFSTTAR
<ref xlink:href="http://www.ifsttar.fr/en/welcome" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>ifsttar.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>en/<allowbreak/>welcome</ref> which is the French institute
of science and technology for transport, development and networks,
conducting research studies on control over aging, risks and
nuisances.</p>
        <object id="uid33">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/topo-Nice.jpg" type="inline" width="142.26378pt" height="142.26378pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/swave-Nice.jpg" type="inline" width="119.50148pt" height="56.9055pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/spectro-Nice.jpg" type="inline" width="156.49014pt" height="142.26378pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Propagation of a plane wave in a heterogeneous model of Nice
area (provided by CETE Méditerranée). Left figure: topography of
Nice and location of the cross-section used for numerical
simulations (black line). Middle figure: S-wave velocity
distribution along the cross-section in the Nice basin. Right
figure: transfer functions (amplification) for a vertically incident
plane wave ; receivers every 5 m at the surface. This numerical
simulation was performed using a numerical method for the solution
of the elastodynamics equations coupled to a Generalized Maxwell
Body (GMB) model of viscoelasticity (PhD thesis of Fabien
Peyrusse).</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid34" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Seismic exploration</bodyTitle>
        <p noindent="true">This application topic is considered in close collaboration with the
MAGIQUE-3D project-team at Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest which is
coordinating the Depth Imaging Partnership (DIP)
<ref xlink:href="http://dip.inria.fr" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>dip.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr</ref> between Inria and TOTAL. The research
program of DIP includes different aspects of the modeling and
numerical simulation of sesimic wave propagation that must be
considered to construct an efficient software suites for producing
accurate images of the subsurface. Our common objective with the
MAGIQUE-3D project-team is to design high order unstructured mesh
based methods for the numerical solution of the system of
elastodynamic equations in the time-domain and in the
frequency-domain, that will be used as forward modelers in appropriate
inversion procedures.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </domaine>
  <logiciels id="uid35">
    <bodyTitle>New Software and Platforms</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid36" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>DIOGENeS</bodyTitle>
      <p>DIscOntinuous GalErkin Nanoscale Solvers</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> High-Performance Computing - Computational electromagnetics -
Discontinuous Galerkin - Computational nanophotonics</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>DIOGENeS is a software suite dedicated to the numerical modeling of
light interaction with nanometer scale structures with applications to
nanophotonics and nanoplasmonics. DIOGENeS relies on a two layer
architecture. The core of the suite is a library of generic software
components (data structures and algorithms) for the implementation of
high order DG (Dicontinuous Galerkin) and HDG (Hybridizable
Dicontinuous Galerkin) schemes formulated on unstructured tetrahedral
and hybrid structured/unstructured (cubic/tetrahedral) meshes. This
library is used to develop dedicated simulation software for
time-domain and frequency-domain problems relevant to nanophotonics
and nanoplasmonics, considering various material models.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid37">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Stéphane Lanteri</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid38">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/nachos/index.php/Software/DIOGENeS" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www-sop.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>nachos/<allowbreak/>index.<allowbreak/>php/<allowbreak/>Software/<allowbreak/>DIOGENeS</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid39" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>GERShWIN</bodyTitle>
      <p>discontinuous GalERkin Solver for microWave INteraction
with biological tissues</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> High-Performance Computing -
Computational electromagnetics -
Discontinuous Galerkin - Computational bioelectromagnetics</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>GERShWIN is based on a high order DG method formulated on unstructured
tetrahedral meshes for solving the 3D system of time-domain Maxwell
equations coupled to a Debye dispersion model.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid40">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Stéphane Lanteri</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid41">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/nachos/index.php/Software/GERShWIN" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www-sop.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>nachos/<allowbreak/>index.<allowbreak/>php/<allowbreak/>Software/<allowbreak/>GERShWIN</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid42" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>HORSE</bodyTitle>
      <p>High Order solver for Radar cross Section Evaluation</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> High-Performance Computing -
Computational electromagnetics -
Discontinuous Galerkin</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>HORSE is based on a high order HDG (Hybridizable Discontinuous
Galerkin) method formulated on unstructured tetrahedral and hybrid
structured/unstructured (cubic/tetrahedral) meshes for the
discretization of the 3D system of frequency-domain Maxwell equations,
coupled to domain decomposition solvers.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid43">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Stéphane Lanteri</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid44">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/nachos/index.php/Software/HORSE" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www-sop.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>nachos/<allowbreak/>index.<allowbreak/>php/<allowbreak/>Software/<allowbreak/>HORSE</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </logiciels>
  <resultats id="uid45">
    <bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid46" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Electromagnetic wave propagation</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid47" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Numerical study of the non-linear Maxwell equations for
Kerr media</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idm26576">
            <firstname>Loula</firstname>
            <lastname>Fezoui</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The system of Maxwell equations describes the evolution of the
interaction of an electromagnetic field with a propagation medium.
The different properties of the medium, such as isotropy, homogeneity,
linearity, among others, are introduced through <i>constitutive
laws</i> linking fields and inductions. In the present study, we focus
on non-linear effects and address non-linear Kerr materials
specifically. In this model, any dielectric may become non-linear
provided the electric field in the material is strong enough. As a
first setp, we considered the one-dimensional case and study the
numerical solution of the non-linear Maxwell equations thanks to DG
methods. In particular, we make use of an upwind scheme and
limitation techniques because they have a proven ability to capture
shocks and other kinds of singularities in the fluid dynamics
framework. The numerical results obtained in this preliminary study
gave us confidence towards extending them to higher spatial
dimensions. This year, we have completed the development of a first
version a parallel DGTD solver for the three-dimensional based on our
past contributions on DGTD methods for the case of linear propagation
media.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid48" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Numerical treatment of non-local dispersion for nanoplasmonics</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp78184">
            <firstname>Nikolai</firstname>
            <lastname>Schmitt</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
            <lastname>Viquerat</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>When metallic nanostructures have sub-wavelength sizes and the
illuminating frequencies are in the regime of metal's plasma
frequency, electron interaction with the exciting fields have to be
taken into account. Due to these interactions, plasmonic surface
waves can be excited and cause extreme local field enhancements
(surface plasmon polariton electromagnetic waves). Exploiting such
field enhancements in applications of interest requires a detailed
knowledge about the occurring fields which can generally not be
obtained analytically. For the numerical modeling of light/matter
interaction on the nanoscale, the choice of an appropriate model is a
crucial point. Approaches that are adopted in a first instance are
based on local (no interaction between electrons) dispersion models
e.g. Drude or Drude-Lorentz. From the mathematical point of view,
these models lead to an additional ordinary differential equation in
time that is coupled to Maxwell's equations. When it comes to very
small structures in a regime of 2 nm to 25 nm, non-local effects due
to electron collisions have to be taken into account. Non-locality
leads to additional, in general non-linear, partial differential
equations and is significantly more difficult to treat, though. In
this work, we study a DGTD method able to solve the system of Maxwell
equations coupled to a linearized non-local dispersion model relevant
to nanoplasmonics. This year, we have developed a parallel DGTD
solver for the three-dimentional Maxwell equations coupeld to a
non-local Drude model. Both centered flux-based and upwind flux-based
DG schemes have been considered, in combination with with leap-frog
and Runge-Kutta time stepping respectively.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid49" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Corner effects in nanoplasmonics</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Camille</firstname>
            <lastname>Carvalho</lastname>
            <moreinfo>ENSTA, POEMS project-team</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
            <lastname>Ciarlet</lastname>
            <moreinfo>ENSTA, POEMS project-team</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>In this work, we study nanoplasmonic structures with corners
(typically a diedral/truangular structure). This is the central
subject considered in the PhD thesis of Camille Carvalho. In the
latter, the focus is made on a lossles Drude dispersion model with a
frequency-domain approach. Several well posedness problems arise due
to the presence of corners and are addressed in the PhD thesis. A
time-domain approach in this context is also relevant and we propose
to use the techniques developed in the team in this prospect. Even if
both approaches (time-domain and frequency-domain) represent similar
physical phenomena, problems that arise are different. These two
approaches appear as complementary; it is thus worth bridging the gap
between the two frameworks. We are currently performing a thorough
comparison in the case of theses 2D structures with corners and we
especially focus on the amplitude principle limit that raises a lot of
questions.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid50" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Travelling waves for the non-linear
Schrödinger equation in 2D</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>David</firstname>
            <lastname>Chiron</lastname>
            <moreinfo>J.A. Dieudonné Laboratory,
Université Nice Sophia Antipolis</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Serge</firstname>
            <lastname>Nicaise</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Université de Valenciennes et du Hainaut-Cambrésis</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>We are interested in the numerical study of the two-dimensional
travelling waves of the non-linear Schrödinger equation for a
general non-linearity and with nonzero condition at infinity. This
equation is appearing in models of nonlinear optics. It has a
variational structure that we propose to exploit to design a numerical
method. We continue the sudy initiated in [1] and investigate excited
states of the Kadomtsev-Petviashvili-I (KP-I) and Gross-Pitaevskii
(GP) equations in dimension 2. We address numerically the question of
the Morse index of some explicit solutions of KP-I. The results
confirm that the lump solitary wave has Morse index one and that the
other explicit solutions correspond to excited states. We then turn to
the 2D GP equation which in some long wave regime converges to the
KP-I equation. We finally perform numerical simulations showing that
the other explicit solitary waves solutions to the KP-I equation give
rise to new branches of travelling waves of GP corresponding to
excited states.</p>
        <p>In this ongoing work, we are interested in fundamental properties of
the non local linearized hydrodynamic Drude model introduced in the
context of nanoplasmonics. We propose an existence and detailed
(polynomial/exponential) stability study for these models. We also
investigate the discrete stability results. We propose to study the
impact of the DG schemes developped in the team on these properties.
This study complements the numerical approach that we already propose
in the context of the PhD of Nikolai Schmitt for this model, towards a
thorough understanding of its fundamentals properties.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid51" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>A structure preserving numerical discretization framework
for the Maxwell Klein Gordon equation in 2D.</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Snorre</firstname>
            <lastname>Christiansen</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Department of Mathematics, University of Oslo, Norway</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>Toward a better understanding of non-linear optical phenomena, we
focus on the case of the Maxwell Klein Gordon (MKG) equation in
dimension 2. This equation appears in the context of quantum
electrodynamics but also in relativity. We propose to develop a
numerical discretization framework that takes advantage of the
Hamiltonian structure of the equation. The gauge invariance is
recovered at the discrete level with the help of the Lattice Gauge
theory. We then propose a fully discrete scheme and prove its
convergence. The strategy of proof, based on discrete energy
principle, is developed in a more general context and next applied in
the particular case of MKG equation. This work has been conducted and
finalized during a of five month's stay of C. Scheid at the
University of Oslo through an invitation in the contexty of the ERC
Starting Grant project STUCCOFIELD of S. Christiansen.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid52" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Multiscale DG methods for the time-domain Maxwell equations</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <firstname>Raphaël</firstname>
            <lastname>Léger</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Diego</firstname>
            <lastname>Paredes Concha</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Instituto de Matemáticas,
Universidad Católica de Valparaiso,
Chile</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp91952">
            <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
            <lastname>Valentin</lastname>
            <moreinfo>LNCC, Petropolis, Brazil</moreinfo>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>Although the DGTD method has already been successfully applied to
complex electromagnetic wave propagation problems, its accuracy may
seriously deteriorate on coarse meshes when the solution presents
multiscale or high contrast features. In other physical contexts,
such an issue has led to the concept of multiscale basis functions as
a way to overcome such a drawback and allow numerical methods to be
accurate on coarse meshes. The present work, which is conducted in
the context of the HOMAR Associate Team, is concerned with the study
of a particular family of multiscale methods, named Multiscale
Hybrid-Mixed (MHM) methods. Initially proposed for fluid flow
problems, MHM methods are a consequence of a hybridization procedure
which caracterize the unknowns as a direct sum of a coarse (global)
solution and the solutions to (local) problems with Neumann boundary
conditions driven by the purposely introduced hybrid (dual) variable.
As a result, the MHM method becomes a strategy that naturally
incorporates multiple scales while providing solutions with high order
accuracy for the primal and dual variables. The completely independent
local problems are embedded in the upscaling procedure, and
computational approximations may be naturally obtained in a parallel
computing environment. In this study, a family of MHM methods is
proposed for the solution of the time-domain Maxwell equations where
the local problems are discretized either with a continuous FE method
or a DG method (that can be viewed as a multiscale DGTD method).
Preliminary results have been obtained in the two-dimensional case.</p>
        <object id="uid53">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/mhm_mesh-quad.png" type="inline" width="135.15059pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/mhm_sol-quad.png" type="inline" width="135.15059pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Light propagation in a photonic crystal structure using a
MHM-DGTD method for solving the 2D Maxwell's equations. Left:
quadrangular mesh. Right: contour lines of the amplitude of the
electric field.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid54" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>HDG methods for the time-domain Maxwell equations</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Alexandra</firstname>
            <lastname>Christophe-Argenvillier</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idm28072">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Descombes</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>This study is concerned with the development of accurate and efficient
solution strategies for the system of 3D time-domain Maxwell equations
coupled to local dispersion models (e.g. Debye, Drude or Drude-Lorentz
models) in the presence of locally refined meshes. Such meshes impose
a constraint on the allowable time step for explicit time integration
schemes that can be very restrictive for the simulation of 3D
problems. We consider here the possibility of using an unconditionally
stable implicit time or a locally implicit time integration scheme
combined to a HDG discretization method.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid55" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>HDG methods for the frequency-domain Maxwell equations</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="nachos-2016-idp137360">
            <firstname>Alexis</firstname>
            <lastname>Gobé</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
            <firstname>Ludovic</firstname>
            <lastname>Moya</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>In the context of the ANR TECSER project, we continue our efforts
towards the development of scalable high order HDG methods for the
solution of the system of 3D frequency-domain Maxwell equations. We
aim at fully exploiting the flexibiity of the HDG discretization
framework with regards to the adaptation of the interpolation order
(<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>p</mi></math></formula>-adaptivity) and the mesh (<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>h</mi></math></formula>-adaptivity). In particular, we
study the formulation of HDG methods on a locally refined
non-conforming tetrahedral mesh and on a non-confoming hybrid
cubic/tetrahedral mesh. We also investigate the coupling between the
HDG formulation and a BEM (Boundary Element Method) discretization of
an integral representation of the electromagnetic field in the case of
propagation problems theoretically defined in unbounded domains. The
associated methodological contributions are implemented in the HORSE
simulation software.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid56" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>HDG methods for the frequency-domain plasmonics</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp86848">
            <firstname>Liang</firstname>
            <lastname>Li</lastname>
            <moreinfo>UESTC, Chengdu, China</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Asger</firstname>
            <lastname>Mortensen</lastname>
            <moreinfo>DTU Fotonik, Technical University of Denmark</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Martijn</firstname>
            <lastname>Wubs</lastname>
            <moreinfo>DTU Fotonik, Technical University of Denmark</moreinfo>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>In this colleaboration with physicists at DTU Fotonik, we study HDG
methods for solving the frequency-domain Maxwell's equations coupled
to the Nonlocal Hydrodynamic Drude (NHD) and Generalized Nonlocal
Optical Response (GNOR) models, which are employed to describe the
optical properties of nanoplasmonic scatterers and waveguides. The
formulations of the HDG method for these two models are exetnsion of
our previous works for classical microwave applications. In teh
present case, two conservativity conditions are globally enforced to
make the problem solvable and to guarantee the continuity of the
tangential component of the electric field and the normal component of
the current density. Numerical results show that the proposed HDG
methods converge at optimal rate. These new HDG formulations hace
been implemented and numerically assessed for two-dimensional
problems.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid57" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Exponential time integrators for a DGTD method</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idm28072">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Descombes</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp86848">
            <firstname>Bin</firstname>
            <lastname>Li</lastname>
            <moreinfo>UESTC, Chengdu, China</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2015-idp76656">
            <firstname>Hao</firstname>
            <lastname>Wang</lastname>
            <moreinfo>UESTC, Chengdu, China</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Li</firstname>
            <lastname>Xu</lastname>
            <moreinfo>UESTC, Chengdu, China</moreinfo>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The objective of this study is to design efficient and (high order)
accurate time integration strategies for the system of time-domain
Maxwell equations discretized in space by a high order discontinuous
Galerkin scheme formulated on locally refined unstructured meshes. A
new family of implicit-explicit (IMEX) schemes using exponential time
integration is developed. The Lawson procedure is applied based on a
partitioning of the underlying tetrahedral mesh in coarse and fine
parts, allowing the contruction of a time advancing strategy that
combines an exact integration of the semi-discrete system for the
problem unknowns associated to the elements of the fine part, with an
arbitrary high order explicit time integration scheme for the
Lawson-transformed system.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid58" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Elastodynamic wave propagation</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid59" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>HDG method for the frequency-domain elastodynamic equations</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Hélène</firstname>
            <lastname>Barucq</lastname>
            <moreinfo>MAGIQUE-3D project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Marie</firstname>
            <lastname>Bonnasse</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Julien</firstname>
            <lastname>Diaz</lastname>
            <moreinfo>MAGIQUE-3D project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>One of the most used seismic imaging methods is the full waveform
inversion (FWI) method which is an iterative procedure whose algorithm
is the following. Starting from an initial velocity model, (1) compute
the solution of the wave equation for the <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>N</mi></math></formula> sources of the seismic
acquisition campaign, (2) evaluate, for each source, a residual
defined as the difference between the wavefields recorded at receivers
on the top of the subsurface during the acquisition campaign and the
numerical wavefields, (3) compute the solution of the wave equation
using the residuals as sources, and (4) update the velocity model by
cross correlation of images produced at steps (1) and (3). Steps
(1)-(4) are repeated until convergence of the velocity model is
achieved. We then have to solve <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>N</mi></mrow></math></formula> wave equations at each
iteration. The number of sources, <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>N</mi></math></formula>, is usually large (about 1000)
and the efficiency of the inverse solver is thus directly related to
the efficiency of the numerical method used to solve the wave
equation. Seismic imaging can be performed in the time-domain or in
the frequency-domain regime. In this work which is conducted in the
framework of the Depth Imaging Partnership (DIP) between Inria and
TOTAL, we adopt the second setting. The main difficulty with
frequency-domain inversion lies in the solution of large sparse linear
systems which is a challenging task for realistic 3D elastic media,
even with the progress of high performance computing. In this context,
we study novel high order HDG methods formulated on unstructured
meshes for the solution of the frency-domain elastodynamic equations.
Instead of solving a linear system involving the degrees of freedom of
all volumic cells of the mesh, the principle of a HDG formulation is
to introduce a new unknown in the form of Lagrange multiplier
representing the trace of the numerical solution on each face of the
mesh. As a result, a HDG formulation yields a global linear system in
terms of the new (surfacic) unknown while the volumic solution is
recovered thanks to a local computation on each element.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid60" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Multiscale DG methods for the time-domain elastodynamic
equations</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Marie-Hélène</firstname>
            <lastname>Lallemand</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <firstname>Raphaël</firstname>
            <lastname>Léger</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp91952">
            <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
            <lastname>Valentin</lastname>
            <moreinfo>LNCC, Petropolis, Brazil</moreinfo>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>In the context of the visit of Frédéric Valentin in the team, we
have initiated a study aiming at the design of novel multiscale
methods for the solution of the time-domain elastodynamic equations,
in the spirit of MHM (Multiscale Hybrid-Mixed) methods previously
proposed for fluid flow problems. Motivation in that direction
naturally came when dealing with non homogeneous anisotropic elastic
media as those encountered in geodynamics related applications, since
multiple scales are naturally present when high contrast elasticity
parameters define the propagation medium. Instead of solving the
usual system expressed in terms of displacement or displacement
velocity, and stress tensor variables, a hybrid mixed-form is derived
in which an additional variable, the Lagrange multiplier, is sought as
representing the (opposite) of the surface tension defined at each
face of the elements of a given discretization mesh. We consider the
velocity/stress formulation of the elastodynamic equations, and study
a MHM method defined for a heterogeneous medium where each elastic
material is considered as isotropic to begin with. If the source term
(the applied given force on the medium) is time independent, and if we
are given an arbitrarily coarse conforming mesh (triangulation in 2D,
tetrahedrization in 3D), the proposed MHM method consists in first
solving a series of fully decoupled (therefore parallelizable) local
(element-wise) problems defining parts of the full solution variables
which are directly related to the source term, followed by the
solution of a global (coarse) problem, which yields the degrees of
freedom of both the Lagrange multiplier dependent part of the full
solution variables and the Lagrange multiplier itself. Finally, the
updating of the full solution variables is obtained by adding each
splitted solution variables, before going on the next time step of a
leap-frog time integration scheme. Theoretical analysis and
implementation of this MHM method where the local problems are
discretized with a DG method, are underway.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid61" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>High performance numerical computing</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid62" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Poring a DGTD solver for bioelectromagnetics
to the DEEP-ER architecture</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Alejandro</firstname>
            <lastname>Duran</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Barcelona Supercomputing Center, Spain</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <firstname>Raphaël</firstname>
            <lastname>Léger</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Damian</firstname>
            <lastname>A. Mallón</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Juelich Supercomputing Center, Germany</moreinfo>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>We are concerned here with the porting of the GERShWIN DGDT solver for
computational bioelectromagnetics to the novel heterogeneous
architecture proposed in the DEEP-ER european project on exascale
computing. This architecture is based on a Cluster/Booster division
concept (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid63" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). The Booster nodes are based
on the Intel Many Integrated Core (MIC) architecture. Therfore, one
objective of our efforts is the algorithmic adaptation of the DG
kernels in order to leverage the vectorizing capabilities of the MIC
processor. The other activities that are undertaken in the context of
our contribution to this project aim at exploiting the software
environments and tools proposed by DEEP-ER partners for implementing
resiliency strategies and high performance I/O operations. In
particular, the Cluster nodes are used for running some parts of the
pre- and post-processing phases of the DGTD solver which do not lend
themselves well to multithreading, as well as I/O intensive
routines. One possibility to achieve this is to consider a model in
which these less scalable and I/O phases are reverse-offloaded from
Booster processes to Cluster processes in a one-to-one mapping. This
is achieved by exploiting the OmpSs offload functionality, developed
at Barcelona Supercomputing Center for the DEEP-ER platform.</p>
        <object id="uid63">
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/deep-er_arch.png" type="float" width="312.9803pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <caption>DEEP-ER hardware architecture sketch.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid64" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>High order HDG schemes and domain decomposition solvers
for frequency-domain electromagnetics</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Emmanuel</firstname>
            <lastname>Agullo</lastname>
            <moreinfo>HIEPACS project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Luc</firstname>
            <lastname>Giraud</lastname>
            <moreinfo>HIEPACS project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Matthieu</firstname>
            <lastname>Kuhn</lastname>
            <moreinfo>HIEPACS project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
            <firstname>Ludovic</firstname>
            <lastname>Moya</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Olivier</firstname>
            <lastname>Rouchon</lastname>
            <moreinfo>CINES, Montpellier</moreinfo>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>This work is undertaken in the context of the ANR TECSER project on
one hand, and PRACE 4IP project on the other hand, and is concerned
with the development of scalable frequency-domain electromagnetic wave
propagation solvers, in the framework of the HORSE simulation
software. HORSE is based on a high order HDG scheme formulated on an
unstructured tetrahedral grid for the discretization of the system of
three-dimensional Maxwell equations in heterogeneous media, leading to
the formulation of large sparse undefinite linear system for the
hybrid variable unknowns. This system is solved with domain
decomposition strategies that can be either a purely algebraic
algorithm working at the matrix operator level (i.e. a black-box
solver), or a tailored algorithm designed at the continuous PDE level
(i.e. a PDE-based solver). In the former case, we use the MaPHyS
(Massively Parallel Hybrid Solver) developed in the HIEPACS
project-team at Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest.</p>
        <object id="uid65">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/F104_P3_View1.png" type="inline" width="173.56198pt" height="145.10922pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/F104_P3_View2.png" type="inline" width="173.56198pt" height="145.10922pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Scattering of a plane wave by a Lockheed F-104 Starfighter.
Contour lines of the amplitude of the electric field. Simulations
are performed with a HDG scheme based on a cubic interpolation of
the electric and magnetic field unknowns, combined with a PDE-based
domain decomposition solver.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid66" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Applications</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid67" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Light diffusion in nanostructured optical fibers</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Wilfried</firstname>
            <lastname>Blanc</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Optical Fibers team, LPMC,
Université Nice Sophia Antipolis, Nice</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Paul</firstname>
            <lastname>Loriot</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>Optical fibers are the basis for applications that have grown
considerably in recent years (telecommunications, sensors, fiber
lasers, etc.). Despite these undeniable successes, it is necessary to
develop new generations of amplifying optical fibers that will
overcome some limitations typical of silica. In this sense, the
amplifying Transparent Glass Ceramics (TGC), and particularly the
fibers based on this technology, open new perspectives that combine
the mechanical and chemical properties of a glass host and the
augmented spectroscopic properties of embedded nanoparticles,
particularly rare earth-doped oxide nanoparticles. Such rare
earth-doped silica-based optical fibers with transparent glass ceramic
(TGC) core are fabricated by the Optical Fibers team of the Laboratory
of Condensed Matter Physics (LPMC) in Nice. The objective of this
collaboration with Wilfried Blanc at LPMC is the study of optical
transmission terms of loss due to scattering through the numerical
simulation of light propagation in a nanostructured optical fiber core
using a high order DGTD method developed in the team.</p>
        <object id="uid68">
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/nano_fiber.png" type="float" width="142.26378pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <caption>Unstructured tetrahdral mesh of a nanostructured optical
fiber core.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid69" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Gap-plasmon confinement with gold nanocubes</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Antoine</firstname>
            <lastname>Moreau</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Institut Pascal, Université Blaise Pascal</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
            <lastname>Viquerat</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The propagation of light in a slit between metals is known to give
rise to guided modes. When the slit is of nanometric size, plasmonic
effects must be taken into account, since most of the mode propagates
inside the metal. Indeed, light experiences an important slowing-down
in the slit, the resulting mode being called <i>gap-plasmon</i>.
Hence, a metallic structure presenting a nanometric slit can act as a
light trap, i.e. light will accumulate in a reduced space and lead to
very intense, localized fields. Recently, the chemical production of
random arrangements of nanocubes on gold films at low cost was proved
possible by Antoine Moreau and colleagues at Institut Pascal.
Nanocubes are separated from the gold substrate by a dielectric spacer
of variable thickness, thus forming a narrow slit under the cube. When
excited from above, this configuration is able to support gap-plasmon
modes which, once trapped, will keep bouncing back and forth inside
the cavity. At visible frequencies, the lossy behavior of metals will
cause the progressive absorption of the trapped electromagnetic field,
turning the metallic nanocubes into efficient absorbers. The
frequencies at which this absorption occurs can be tuned by adjusting
the dimensions of the nanocube and the spacer. In collaboration with
Antoine Moreau, we propose to study numerically the impact of the
geometric parameters of the problem on the behaviour of a single
nanocube placed over a metallic slab (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid70" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>).
The behavior of single nanocubes on metallic plates has been
simulated, for lateral sizes <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>c</mi></math></formula> ranging from 50 to 80 nm, and spacer
thicknesses <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>δ</mi></math></formula> from 3 to 22 nm. The absorption efficiency in
the cube <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msub><mi>Q</mi><mtext>cube</mtext></msub></math></formula> at the resonance frequency is retrieved
from the results of each computation (see
Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid71" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>).</p>
        <object id="uid70">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/r2_d5_c75.png" type="inline" width="142.26378pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/r10_d5_c75.png" type="inline" width="142.26378pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Meshes of rounded nanocubes with rounding radii ranging from
2 to 10 nm. Red cells correspond to the cube. The latter lies on the
dielectric spacer (gray cells) and the metallic plate (green). Blue
cells represent the air surrounding the device.</caption>
        </object>
        <object id="uid71">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/nanocube_d12nm_c70nm_H_visu2.png" type="inline" width="142.26378pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/nanocube_d18nm_c60nm_H_visu2.png" type="inline" width="142.26378pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center"><formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>c</mi><mo>=</mo></mrow></math></formula> 70 nm, <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo>=</mo></mrow></math></formula> 12 nm</td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center"><formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>c</mi><mo>=</mo></mrow></math></formula> 60 nm, <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo>=</mo></mrow></math></formula> 18 nm</td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Amplitude of the discrete Fourier transform of the magnetic
field for different nanocube configurations. All field maps are
scaled identically for better comparison. The obtained field is more
intense for configurations that yield high <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msub><mi>Q</mi><mtext>cube</mtext></msub></math></formula>
values.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid72" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Dielectric reflectarrays</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Maciej</firstname>
            <lastname>Klemm</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Centre for Communications Research,
University of Bristol</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <firstname>Claire</firstname>
            <lastname>Scheid</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
            <lastname>Viquerat</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>In the past few years, important efforts have been deployed to find
alternatives to on-chip, low-performance metal interconnects between
devices. Because of the ever-increasing density of integrated
components, intra- and inter-chip data communications have become a
major bottleneck in the improvement of information processing. Given
the compactness and the simple implantation of the devices,
communications <i>via</i> free-space optics between
nanoantenna-based arrays have recently drawn more attention. Here, we
focus on a specific low-loss design of dielectric reflectarray (DRA),
whose geometry is based on a periodic repartition of dielectric
cylinders on a metallic plate. When illuminated in normal incidence,
specific patterns of such resonators provide a constant phase gradient
along the dielectric/metal interface, thus altering the phase of the
incident wavefront. The gradient of phase shift generates an effective
wavevector along the interface, which is able to deflect light from
specular reflection. However, the flaws of the lithographic
production process can lead to discrepancies between the ideal device
and the actual resonator array. Here, we propose to exploit our DGTD
solver to study the impact of the lithographic flaws on the
performance of a 1D reflectarray (see
Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid73" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). Efficient computations are obtained by
combining high-order polynomial approximation with curvilinear meshing
of the resonators, yielding accurate results on very coarse meshes
(see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid74" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). The study is continued with the
computation of the reflection of a 2D reflectarray. This work
constitutes the base of a wider study in collaboration with Maciej
Klemm at the Centre for Communications Research, University of
Bristol.</p>
        <object id="uid73">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/bigdiel_sharp.png" type="inline" width="284.52756pt" height="85.35826pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">Ideal reflectarray</td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/bigdiel_imperfect.png" type="inline" width="284.52756pt" height="85.35826pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">Realistic reflectarray</td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Ideal and realistic 1D dielectric reflectarray meshes. The
red tetrahedra correspond to silver, while the green ones are made
of an anisotropic dielectric material. The device is surrounded by
air and terminated by a PML above and below, and by periodic
boundary conditions on the lateral sides.</caption>
        </object>
        <object id="uid74">
          <table rend="inline">
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/bigdiel_ideal_f1.png" type="inline" width="170.71652pt" height="199.16928pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/bigdiel_imperfect_f1.png" type="inline" width="170.71652pt" height="199.16928pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="">
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">Ideal reflectarray</td>
              <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">Realistic reflectarray</td>
            </tr>
            <caption/>
          </table>
          <caption>Time-domain snapshot of <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msub><mi>E</mi><mi>y</mi></msub></math></formula> component for ideal and
realistic 1D dielectric reflectarrays. Solution is obtained in
established regime at <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>t</mi><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>.</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></math></formula> ps. Fields are scaled to <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mfenced separators="" open="[" close="]"><mo>-</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>,</mo><mn>1</mn></mfenced></math></formula>.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </resultats>
  <contrats id="uid75">
    <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid76" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid77" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Nucletudes</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="PASUSERID">
            <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
            <lastname>Breuilh</lastname>
            <moreinfo>Nuclétudes, Les Ulis, France</moreinfo>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2016-idp137360">
            <firstname>Alexis</firstname>
            <lastname>Gobé</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
            <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The objective of this collaboration with the Nucletudes company that
has been initiated this year is to design a high order HDG formulation
able to deal with non-conforming hybrid cubic/tetrahedral meshes, for
the simulation of time-domain electromagnetic wave propagation
problems with applications to radiation hardening. This first part of
this study has been concerned with the specification and development
of a preprocessing tool for the construction of such hybrid
structured/unstructured meshes.</p>
        <object id="uid78">
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/avion_creneau_y.png" type="float" width="312.9803pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <caption>Non-confoming hybrid cubic/tetrahedral mesh around a jet
fighter for Radar Cross Section evaluation using a frequency-domain
Maxwell solver based on a HDG method.</caption>
        </object>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </contrats>
  <partenariat id="uid79">
    <bodyTitle>Partnerships and Cooperations</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid80" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>National Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid81" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria Project Lab</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid82" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>C2S@Exa (Computer and Computational Sciences at Exascale)</bodyTitle>
          <participants>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Olivier</firstname>
              <lastname>Aumage</lastname>
              <moreinfo>STORM project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Philippe</firstname>
              <lastname>Helluy</lastname>
              <moreinfo>TONUS project-team, Inria Nancy - Grand-Est</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Luc</firstname>
              <lastname>Giraud</lastname>
              <moreinfo>HIEPACS project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
              <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
              <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
              <moreinfo>Coordinator of the project</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Jean-François</firstname>
              <lastname>Méhaut</lastname>
              <moreinfo>CORSE project-team, Inria Grenoble - Rhône-Alpes</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Christian</firstname>
              <lastname>Perez</lastname>
              <moreinfo>AVALON project-team, Inria Grenoble - Rhône-Alpes</moreinfo>
            </person>
          </participants>
          <p>Since January 2013, the team is coordinating the C2S@Exa
<ref xlink:href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/c2s_at_exa" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www-sop.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>c2s_at_exa</ref> Inria Project Lab (IPL).
This national initiative aims at the development of numerical modeling
methodologies that fully exploit the processing capabilities of modern
massively parallel architectures in the context of a number of
selected applications related to important scientific and
technological challenges for the quality and the security of life in
our society. At the current state of the art in technologies and
methodologies, a multidisciplinary approach is required to overcome
the challenges raised by the development of highly scalable numerical
simulation software that can exploit computing platforms offering
several hundreds of thousands of cores. Hence, the main objective of
C2S@Exa is the establishment of a continuum of expertise in the
computer science and numerical mathematics domains, by gathering
researchers from Inria project-teams whose research and development
activities are tightly linked to high performance computing issues in
these domains. More precisely, this collaborative effort involves
computer scientists that are experts of programming models,
environments and tools for harnessing massively parallel systems,
algorithmists that propose algorithms and contribute to generic
libraries and core solvers in order to take benefit from all the
parallelism levels with the main goal of optimal scaling on very large
numbers of computing entities and, numerical mathematicians that are
studying numerical schemes and scalable solvers for systems of partial
differential equations in view of the simulation of very large-scale
problems.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid83" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ANR project</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid84" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>TECSER</bodyTitle>
          <participants>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Emmanuel</firstname>
              <lastname>Agullo</lastname>
              <moreinfo>HIEPACS project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Xavier</firstname>
              <lastname>Antoine</lastname>
              <moreinfo>CORIDA project-team, Inria Nancy - Grand-Est</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
              <lastname>Breuil</lastname>
              <moreinfo>Nuclétudes, Les Ulis</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Thomas</firstname>
              <lastname>Frachon</lastname>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Luc</firstname>
              <lastname>Giraud</lastname>
              <moreinfo>HIEPACS project-team, Inria Bordeaux - Sud-Ouest</moreinfo>
            </person>
            <person key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
              <firstname>Stéphane</firstname>
              <lastname>Lanteri</lastname>
            </person>
            <person key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
              <firstname>Ludovic</firstname>
              <lastname>Moya</lastname>
            </person>
            <person key="PASUSERID">
              <firstname>Guillaume</firstname>
              <lastname>Sylvand</lastname>
              <moreinfo>Airbus Group Innovations</moreinfo>
            </person>
          </participants>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid85">
              <p noindent="true">Type: ANR ASTRID</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid86">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: May 2014 - April 2017</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid87">
              <p noindent="true">Coordinator: Inria</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid88">
              <p noindent="true">Partner: Airbus Group Innovations, Inria, Nuclétudes</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid89">
              <p noindent="true">Inria contact: Stéphane Lanteri</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid90">
              <p noindent="true">Abstract: the objective of the TECSER project is to develop an
innovative high performance numerical methodology for
frequency-domain electromagnetics with applications to RCS (Radar
Cross Section) calculation of complicated structures. This numerical
methodology combines a high order hybridized DG method for the
discretization of the frequency-domain Maxwell in heterogeneous
media with a BEM (Boundary Element Method) discretization of an
integral representation of Maxwell's equations in order to obtain
the most accurate treatment of boundary truncation in the case of
theoretically unbounded propagation domain. Beside, scalable hybrid
iterative/direct domain decomposition based algorithms are used for
the solution of the resulting algebraic system of equations.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid91" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>European Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid92" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>FP7 &amp; H2020 Projects</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid93" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>DEEP-ER</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid94">
              <p noindent="true">Title: Dynamic Exascale Entry Platform - Extended Reach</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid95">
              <p noindent="true">Program: FP7</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid96">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: October 2013 - September 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid97">
              <p noindent="true">Coordinator: Forschungszentrum Juelich Gmbh (Germany)</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid98">
              <p noindent="true">Partner: Intel Gmbh (Germany), Bayerische Akademie der
Wissenschaften (Germany), Ruprecht-Karls-Universitaet Heidelberg
(Germany), Universitaet Regensburg (Germany),
Fraunhofer-Gesellschaft zur Foerderung der Angewandten Forschung E.V
(Germany), Eurotech Spa (Italy), Consorzio Interuniversitario Cineca
(Italy), Barcelona Supercomputing Center - Centro Nacional de
Supercomputacion (Spain), Xyratex Technology Limited (United
Kingdom), Katholieke Universiteit Leuven (Belgium), Stichting
Astronomisch Onderzoek in Nederland (The Netherlands) and Inria
(France).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid99">
              <p noindent="true">Inria contact: Stéphane Lanteri</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid100">
              <p noindent="true">Abstract: the DEEP-ER project aims at extending the
Cluster-Booster Architecture that has been developed within the DEEP
project with a highly scalable, efficient, easy-to-use parallel I/O
system and resiliency mechanisms. A Prototype will be constructed
leveraging advances in hardware components and integrate new storage
technologies. They will be the basis to develop a highly scalable,
efficient and user-friendly parallel I/O system tailored to HPC
applications. Building on this I/O functionality a unified
user-level checkpointing system with reduced overhead will be
developed, exploiting multiple levels of storage. The DEEP
programming model will be extended to introduce easy-to-use
annotations to control checkpointing, and to combine automatic
re-execution of failed tasks and recovery of long-running tasks from
multi-level checkpoint. The requirements of HPC codes with regards
to I/O and resiliency will guide the design of the DEEP-ER hardware
and software components. Seven applications will be optimised for
the DEEP-ER Prototype to demonstrate and validate the benefits of
the DEEP-ER extensions to the Cluster-Booster Architecture.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid101" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>HPC4E</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid102">
              <p noindent="true">Title: HPC for Energy</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid103">
              <p noindent="true">Programm: H2020</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid104">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: December 2015 - November 2017</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid105">
              <p noindent="true">Coordinator: Barcelona Supercomputing Center</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid106">
              <p noindent="true">Partner: Barcelona Supercomputing Center (Spain), Centro de
Investigaciones Energeticas, Medioambientales y Tecnologicas -
CIEMAT (Spain), REPSOL SA (Spain), Iberdrola Renovables Energia SA
(spain), Lancaster University (United Kingdom), COPPE/UFRJ -
Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (Brazil), LNCC (Brazil),
INF/UFRGS - Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul (Brazil),
CER/UFPE - Universidade Federal de Pernambuco (Brazil), PETROBRAS
(Brazil), TOTAL SA (France), and Inria (France).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid107">
              <p noindent="true">Inria contact: Stéphane Lanteri</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid108">
              <p noindent="true">Abstract: This project aims to apply the new exascale HPC
techniques to energy industry simulations, customizing them, and
going beyond the state-of-the-art in the required HPC exascale
simulations for different energy sources: wind energy production and
design, efficient combustion systems for biomass-derived fuels
(biogas), and exploration geophysics for hydrocarbon reservoirs.
For wind energy industry HPC is a must. The competitiveness of wind
farms can be guaranteed only with accurate wind resource assessment,
farm design and short-term micro-scale wind simulations to forecast
the daily power production. The use of CFD LES models to analyse
atmospheric flow in a wind farm capturing turbine wakes and array
effects requires exascale HPC systems. Biogas, i.e. biomass-derived
fuels by anaerobic digestion of organic wastes, is attractive
because of its wide availability, renewability and reduction of CO2
emissions, contribution to diversification of energy supply, rural
development, and it does not compete with feed and food
feedstock. However, its use in practical systems is still limited
since the complex fuel composition might lead to unpredictable
combustion performance and instabilities in industrial
combustors. The next generation of exascale HPC systems will be able
to run combustion simulations in parameter regimes relevant to
industrial applications using alternative fuels, which is required
to design efficient furnaces, engines, clean burning vehicles and
power plants. One of the main HPC consumers is the oil &amp; gas
(O&amp;G) industry. The computational requirements arising from full
wave-form modelling and inversion of seismic and electromagnetic
data is ensuring that the O&amp;G industry will be an early adopter of
exascale computing technologies. By taking into account the complete
physics of waves in the subsurface, imaging tools are able to reveal
information about the Earth’s interior with unprecedented quality.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid109" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid110" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria Associate Teams not involved in an Inria International Labs</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid111" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>HOMAR</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid112">
              <p noindent="true">Title: High performance Multiscale Algorithms for wave
pRopagation problems</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid113">
              <p noindent="true">International Partner (Institution - Laboratory - Researcher):</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid114">
                  <p noindent="true">Laboratório Nacional de Computaçao Científica (Brazil) -
Coordenaçao de Matemática Aplicada e Computaciona -
Frédéric Valentin</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid115">
              <p noindent="true">Start year: 2015</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid116">
              <p noindent="true">See also: <ref xlink:href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/nachos/index.php/Main/HOMAR" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www-sop.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>nachos/<allowbreak/>index.<allowbreak/>php/<allowbreak/>Main/<allowbreak/>HOMAR</ref></p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid117">
              <p noindent="true">The general scientific context of the collaboration proposed in
the HOMAR project is the study of time dependent wave propagation
problems presenting multiscale features (in space and time). The
general goal is the design, analysis and implementation of a family
of innovative high performance numerical methods particularly well
suited to the simulation of such multiscale wave propagation
problems. Mathematical models based on partial differential
equations (PDE) embedding multiscale features occur in a wide range
of scientific and technological applications involving wave
propagation in heterogeneous media. Electromagnetic wave propagation
and seismic wave propagation are two relevant physical settings that
will be considered in the project. Indeed, the present
collaborative project will focus on two particular application
contexts: the interaction of light (i.e. optical wave) with
nanometer scale structure (i.e. nanophotonics) and, the interaction
of seismic wave propagation with geological media for quantitative
and non destructive evaluation of imperfect interfaces.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid118" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria International Partners</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid119" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Informal International Partners</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid120">
              <p noindent="true">Prof. Kurt Busch, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Institut
für Physik, Theoretical Optics &amp; Photonics</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid121">
              <p noindent="true">Prof. Martijn Wubs, Technical University of Denmark (DTU),
Structured Electromagnetic Materials Theory group</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid122">
              <p noindent="true">Dr. Maciej Klemm, University of Bristol, Communication Systems
&amp; Networks Laboratory, Centre for Communications Research (United
Kingdom)</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid123">
              <p noindent="true">Dr. Urs Aeberhard and Dr. Markus Ermes, Theory and Multiscale
Simulation, IEK-5 Photovoltaik, Forschungszentrum Jülich, Germany</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid124" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Research Visitors</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid125" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits of International Scientists</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid126">
            <p noindent="true">Prof. Liang Li, School of Mathematical Sciences, University of
Electronic Science and Technology of China, Chengdu. From March 2016
to February 2017.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid127">
            <p noindent="true">Dr. Antonio Tadeu Gomez and Dr. Frédéric Valentin, LNCC,
Petropolis, Brazil. From December 15, 2016 to February 15, 2017.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid128">
            <p noindent="true">Prof. Bin Li and Prof. Li Xu, School of Physical Electronics,
University of Electronic Science and Technology of China,
Chengdu. From August 1st to Agust 12, 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </partenariat>
  <diffusion id="uid129">
    <bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid130" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Promoting Scientific Activities</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid131" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific events organisation</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid132" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Conference Program Committees</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid133">
              <p noindent="true">Stéphane Lanteri, Claire Scheid and Wilfried Blanc (LPMC,
Université Nice Sophia Antipolis, Nice) have co-organized the
meeting "CompNano2016: Modelling and simulation for nanophotonics"
that took place at Inria Sophia Antipolis-Méditerranée, October
5-7, 2016.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid134">
              <p noindent="true">Stéphane Lanteri and Frédéric Valentin (LNCC, Petropolis,
Brazil) have co-organized a mini-symposium on "Hybridized and
multiscale methods for waves" in the framework of the Icosahom 2016
conference that took place in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, June 27-July
1st, 2016.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid135" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Invited Talks</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid136">
            <p noindent="true">Claire Scheid, "Numerical modelling of light-matter interaction at the nanoscale",
BioComp seminar, Simula, Oslo, Norway, November 9, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid137">
            <p noindent="true">Claire Scheid, "A structure preserving numerical discretization framework
for the Maxwell Klein Gordon equation in 2D",
Workshop on Structure and Scaling in Computational Field Theories,
University of Oslo, Norway, October 26-28, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid138">
            <p noindent="true">Claire Scheid, "A high order discretization framework for the numerical modelling
in nanoplasmonics", Colloque Couplages Numériques, LJAD,
Université Nice Sophia Antipolis, Nice, France, September 27-29, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid139">
            <p noindent="true">Claire Scheid, "A discontinuous Galerkin framework for the numerical
modelling in nanoplasmonics"
Workshop on Recent Advances in Discontinuous Galerkin Methods,
University of Reading, UK, June 13, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid140">
            <p noindent="true">Claire Scheid, "A discontinuous Galerkin framework for the numerical modelling
of light-matter interaction at the nanoscale",
28th CEA-GAMNI Seminar on CFD, IHP, Paris, January 25-26, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid141">
            <p noindent="true">Stéphane Lanteri, "Recent advances on a finite element type
simulation method for nanoscale light/matter interactions", 8èmes
Journées Scientifiques du C'Nano PACA, Porquerolles, France, May
25-27, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid142">
            <p noindent="true">Stéphane Lanteri, "Development of finite element type
simulation methods for nanoscale light/matter interactions", ONERA
Palaiseau, France, June 15, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid143">
            <p noindent="true">Stéphane Lanteri, "High order HDG method for frequency-domain
electromagnetics", Institut fuer Physik, Humboldt-Universitaet zu
Berlin, Germany, February 9-11, 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid144" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Teaching - Supervision - Juries</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid145" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Teaching</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid146">
            <p noindent="true">Stéphane Descombes, <i>Scientific computing</i>, M1, 36 h,
Université Nice Sophia Antipolis.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid147">
            <p noindent="true">Stéphane Descombes, <i>Principal components analysis</i>,
M2, 30 h, Université Nice Sophia Antipolis.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid148">
            <p noindent="true">Stéphane Lanteri, <i>Computational electromagnetics</i>, MAM5,
20 h, Polytech Nice Sophia.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid149">
            <p noindent="true">Claire Scheid, <i>Lectures and practical works, Analysis</i>,
<i>Agrégation</i>, 27 h, Université Nice Sophia Antipolis.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid150">
            <p noindent="true">Claire Scheid, <i>Lectures and practical works, Numerical Analysis</i>,
<i>Agrégation</i>, 34 h, Université Nice Sophia Antipolis.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid151" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Supervision</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid152">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Alexis Gobé, <i>Multiscale hybrid-mixed
methods for time-domain nanophotonics</i>, November 2016, Stéphane
Lanteri.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid153">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Nikolai Schmitt, <i>Numerical modeling of
electron beam interaction with nanostructures</i>, October 2015,
Stéphane Lanteri and Claire Scheid.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid154">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Hao Wang, <i>High order DGTD method for
multiscale electromagnetic wave propagation problems</i>, September
2015, Bin Li and Li Xu (UESTC, Chengdu, China) and Stéphane
Lanteri.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </diffusion>
  <biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" numero="10" titre="Bibliography">
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid31" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:benjemaa-etal:09">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">3D dynamic rupture simulations by a finite volume method</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M</foreName>
            <surname>Benjemaa</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>N.</foreName>
            <surname>Glinsky-Olivier</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>V.M.</foreName>
            <surname>Cruz-Atienza</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Virieux</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Geophys. J. Int.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">178</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">541–560</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid15" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:delcourte-etal:09">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A high-order discontinuous Galerkin method for the seismic wave propagation</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="kaliffe-2014-idp67816">
            <foreName>Sarah</foreName>
            <surname>Delcourte</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idm26576">
            <foreName>Loula</foreName>
            <surname>Fézoui</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nathalie</foreName>
            <surname>Glinsky-Olivier</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">ESAIM: Proc.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">27</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">70–89</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid52" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:descombes-etal:13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Recent advances on a DGTD method for time-domain electromagnetics</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idm28072">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Descombes</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Durochat</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Moya</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Viquerat</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Photonics and Nanostructures - Fundamentals and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">11</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">291–302</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid12" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:dolean-etal:10">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Locally implicit discontinuous Galerkin method for time domain electromagnetics</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>V.</foreName>
            <surname>Dolean</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>H.</foreName>
            <surname>Fahs</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Loula</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">J. Comput. Phys.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">229</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">512–526</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid53" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:durochat-etal:13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A non-conforming multi-element DGTD method for the simulation of human exposure to electromagnetic waves</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Durochat</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Léger</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Int. J. Numer. Model., Electron. Netw. Devices Fields</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">27</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">614-625</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid11" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:durochat-eta:13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">High order non-conforming multi-element discontinuous Galerkin method for time domain electromagnetics</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Durochat</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Appl. Math. Comput.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">224</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">681–704</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid51" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:bouajaji-etal:12">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Optimized Schwarz methods for the time-harmonic Maxwell equations with damping</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="corida-2014-idp75568">
            <foreName>M</foreName>
            <surname>El Bouajaji</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>V.</foreName>
            <surname>Dolean</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.J.</foreName>
            <surname>Gander</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comp.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">34</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">A20148–A2071</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid17" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:elbouajaji-lanteri:13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">High order discontinuous Galerkin method for the solution of 2D time-harmonic Maxwell's equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="corida-2014-idp75568">
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>El Bouajaji</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Appl. Math. Comput.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">219</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">13</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">7241–7251</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid16" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:etienne-etal:10">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">An hp-adaptive discontinuous Galerkin finite-element method for 3-D elastic wave modelling</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>V.</foreName>
            <surname>Etienne</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>E.</foreName>
            <surname>Chaljub</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Virieux</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp85616">
            <foreName>N.</foreName>
            <surname>Glinsky</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Geophys. J. Int.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">183</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">941–962</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid9" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:fahs:09a">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Development of a <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>h</mi><mi>p</mi></mrow></math></formula>-like discontinuous Galerkin time-domain method on non-conforming simplicial meshes for electromagnetic wave propagation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>H.</foreName>
            <surname>Fahs</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Int. J. Numer. Anal. Mod.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">193–216</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid10" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:fahs:09b">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">High-order Leap-Frog based biscontinuous Galerkin bethod for the time-domain Maxwell equations on non-conforming simplicial meshes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>H.</foreName>
            <surname>Fahs</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Numer. Math. Theor. Meth. Appl.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">275–300</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid24" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:fahs-etal:11">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Calculation of the SAR induced in head tissues using a high order DGTD method and triangulated geometrical models</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>H.</foreName>
            <surname>Fahs</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Hadjem</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Wiart</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.F.</foreName>
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Trans. Ant. Propag.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">59</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">12</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">4669–4678</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid8" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:fezoui-etal:05">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Convergence and stability of a discontinuous Galerkin time-domain method for the 3D heterogeneous Maxwell equations on unstructured meshes</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idm26576">
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Fezoui</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lohrengel</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Piperno</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">ESAIM: Math. Model. Num. Anal.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">39</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2005</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1149–1176</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid54" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:leger-etal:14">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A parallel non-conforming multi-element DGTD method for the simulation of electromagnetic wave interaction with metallic nanoparticles</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Léger</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Viquerat</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Durochat</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">J. Comp. Appl. Math.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">270</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2014</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">330–342</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid21" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:lanteri-scheid:13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Convergence of a discontinuous Galerkin scheme for the mixed time domain Maxwell's equations in dispersive media</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IMA J. Numer. Anal.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">33</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">432-459</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid19" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:li-etal:13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Numerical investigation of a high order hybridizable discontinuous Galerkin method for 2d time-harmonic Maxwell's equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp86848">
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp90696">
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Perrussel</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">COMPEL</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1112–1138</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid20" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:li-etal:14">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A hybridizable discontinuous Galerkin method combined to a Schwarz algorithm for the solution of 3d time-harmonic Maxwell's equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp86848">
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp90696">
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Perrussel</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">J. Comput. Phys.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">256</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2014</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">563–581</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid14" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:moya-etal:13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Locally implicit time integration strategies in a discontinuous Galerkin method for Maxwell's equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Moya</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idm28072">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Descombes</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">J. Sci. Comp.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">56</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">190–218</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid13" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:moya:12">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Temporal convergence of a locally implicit discontinuous Galerkin method for Maxwell's equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Moya</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">ESAIM: Mathematical Modelling and Numerical Analysis</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">46</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1225–1246</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid23" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:peyrusse-etal:14">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A nodal discontinuous Galerkin method for site effects assessment in viscoelastic media - verification and validation in the Nice basin</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp80712">
            <foreName>F</foreName>
            <surname>Peyrusse</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>N.</foreName>
            <surname>Glinsky-Olivier</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Gélis</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Geophys. J. Int.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">199</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2014</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">315-334</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid22" type="techreport" rend="refer" n="refercite:viquerat-etal:13">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00819758"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Theoretical and numerical analysis of local dispersion models coupled to a discontinuous Galerkin time-domain method for Maxwell's equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Viquerat</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>Klemm</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="number">RR-8298</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Inria</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">79</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/hal-00819758" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00819758</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Research Report</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid32" type="proceedings" rend="year" n="cite:leger:hal-01243708">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.3233/978-1-61499-621-7-349"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01243708"/>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes">
        <title level="m">Adapting a Finite-Element Type Solver for Bioelectromagnetics to the DEEP-ER Platform</title>
        <title level="s">Advances in parallel computing</title>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <foreName>Raphaël</foreName>
            <surname>Léger</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Damian</foreName>
            <surname>Alvarez Mallon</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alejandro</foreName>
            <surname>Duran</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">Parallel Computing: On the Road to Exascale</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">27</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>IOS Press<address><addrLine>Edinburgh, United Kingdom</addrLine></address></orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">850</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01243708" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01243708</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid37" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:chiron:hal-00873794">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00332-015-9273-6"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00873794"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Travelling Waves for the Nonlinear Schrödinger Equation with General Nonlinearity in Dimension Two</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>David</foreName>
            <surname>Chiron</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01226">
        <idno type="issn">0938-8974</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Nonlinear Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00873794" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00873794</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid36" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:descombes:hal-01133694">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1137/15M1010282"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01133694"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Locally implicit discontinuous Galerkin time domain method for electromagnetic wave propagation in dispersive media applied to numerical dosimetry in biological tissues</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idm28072">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Descombes</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
            <foreName>Ludovic</foreName>
            <surname>Moya</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01739">
        <idno type="issn">1064-8275</idno>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">38</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">5</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">A2611-A2633</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01133694" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01133694</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid33" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:he:hal-01258441">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.cpc.2015.11.011"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01258441"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a"> Optimized Schwarz algorithms for solving time-harmonic Maxwell's equations discretized by a Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin method</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yu-Xuan</foreName>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <initial>Y.-X.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp86848">
            <foreName>Liang</foreName>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ting-Zhu</foreName>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <initial>T.-Z.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00401">
        <idno type="issn">0010-4655</idno>
        <title level="j">Computer Physics Communications</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01258441" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01258441</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid34" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:schmitt:hal-01334396">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.jcp.2016.04.020"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01334396"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A DGTD method for the numerical modeling of the interaction of light with nanometer scale metallic structures taking into account non-local dispersion effects</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp78184">
            <foreName>Nikolai</foreName>
            <surname>Schmitt</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Moreau</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <foreName>Jonathan</foreName>
            <surname>Viquerat</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01098">
        <idno type="issn">0021-9991</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Computational Physics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">316</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01334396" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01334396</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid45" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:viquerat:hal-01389163">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.photonics.2015.12.004"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01389163"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Simulation of near-field plasmonic interactions with a local approximation order discontinuous Galerkin time-domain method</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <foreName>Jonathan</foreName>
            <surname>Viquerat</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid02579">
        <idno type="issn">1569-4410</idno>
        <title level="j">Photonics and Nanostructures - Fundamentals and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">18</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">43 - 58</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01389163" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01389163</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid42" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:agullo:hal-01404669">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01404669"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">High order scalable HDG method fro frequency-domain electromagnetics</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="hiepacs-2014-idp77424">
            <foreName>Emmanuel</foreName>
            <surname>Agullo</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="ipso-2014-idp71664">
            <foreName>Matthieu</foreName>
            <surname>Kuhn</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp74360">
            <foreName>Ludovic</foreName>
            <surname>Moya</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Icosahom 2016 - International Conference on Spectral and High Order Methods</title>
        <loc>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01404669" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01404669</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid301492">
          <title>International Conference on Spectral and High Order Methods</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICOSAHOM</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid41" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bonnassegahot:hal-01400663">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01400663"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Comparison of solvers performance when solving the 3D Helmholtz elastic wave equations over the Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin method</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="magique-3d-2014-idp78832">
            <foreName>Marie</foreName>
            <surname>Bonnasse-Gahot</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Henri</foreName>
            <surname>Calandra</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="magique-3d-2014-idm24968">
            <foreName>Julien</foreName>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stephane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">MATHIAS – TOTAL Symposium on Mathematics</title>
        <loc>Paris, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01400663" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01400663</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid346070">
          <title>Journées MATHIAS</title>
          <num>2012</num>
          <abbr type="sigle"/>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid39" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bonnassegahot:hal-01400656">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01400656"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Comparison of solvers performance when solving the 3D Helmholtz elastic wave equations using the Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin method</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="magique-3d-2014-idp78832">
            <foreName>Marie</foreName>
            <surname>Bonnasse-Gahot</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Henri</foreName>
            <surname>Calandra</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="magique-3d-2014-idm24968">
            <foreName>Julien</foreName>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stephane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">Workshop DIP - Depth Imaging Partnership</title>
        <loc>Houston, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01400656" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01400656</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid623703">
          <title>Workshop Depth Imaging Partnership (Inria-TOTAL)</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">DIP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid40" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bonnassegahot:hal-01400643">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01400643"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Resolution strategy for the Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin system for solving Helmholtz elastic wave equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="magique-3d-2014-idp78832">
            <foreName>Marie</foreName>
            <surname>Bonnasse-Gahot</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Henri</foreName>
            <surname>Calandra</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="magique-3d-2014-idm24968">
            <foreName>Julien</foreName>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stephane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">Face to face meeting HPC4E Brazilian-European project</title>
        <loc>Gramado, Brazil</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01400643" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01400643</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625273">
          <title>Face to face meeting HPC4E Brazilian-European project</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle"/>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid35" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:lanteri:hal-01245904">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01245904"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A multiscale hybrid-mixed method for the Maxwell equations in the time domain</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <foreName>Raphaël</foreName>
            <surname>Léger</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Diego</foreName>
            <surname>Paredes</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp91952">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Valentin</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">WONAPDE 2016</title>
        <loc>Concepción, Chile</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Universidad de Concepción, Chile</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01245904" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01245904</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid398389">
          <title>Chilean Workshop on Numerical Analysis of Partial Differential Equations WONAPDE</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">WONAPDE</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid44" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:lanteri:hal-01404684">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01404684"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A multiscale hybrid-mixed method for the Maxwell equations in time-domain</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp73080">
            <foreName>Raphaël</foreName>
            <surname>Léger</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Diego</foreName>
            <surname>Paredes</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp91952">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Valentin</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Icosahom 2016 - International Conference on Spectral and High Order Methods</title>
        <loc>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01404684" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01404684</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid301492">
          <title>International Conference on Spectral and High Order Methods</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICOSAHOM</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid46" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:lanteri:hal-01391566">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01391566"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Discontinuous Galerkin Time Domain Methods for Nonlocal Dispersion Models and Electron Beam Modeling in the Context of Nanoplasmonics</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stephane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp78184">
            <foreName>Nikolai</foreName>
            <surname>Schmitt</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <foreName>Jonathan</foreName>
            <surname>Viquerat</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">META 2016 - 7th International Conference on Metamaterials, Photonic Crystals and Plasmonics</title>
        <loc>Malaga, Spain</loc>
        <title level="s">Meta 2016 Program</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01391566" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01391566</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625406">
          <title>International Conference on Metamaterials, Photonic Crystals and Plasmonics</title>
          <num>7</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">META</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid43" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:lanteri:hal-01404672">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01404672"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">High order DGTD solver for the numerical modeling of nanoscale light/matter interaction</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp83168">
            <foreName>Jonathan</foreName>
            <surname>Viquerat</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Icosahom 2016 - International Conference on Spectral and High Order Methods</title>
        <loc>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01404672" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01404672</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid301492">
          <title>International Conference on Spectral and High Order Methods</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICOSAHOM</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid38" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:li:hal-01416919">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416919"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Model order reduction based solver for discontinuous Galerkin element approximation of time-domain Maxwell’s equations in dispersive media</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Kun</foreName>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ting-Zhu</foreName>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <initial>T.-Z.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp86848">
            <foreName>Liang</foreName>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stephane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IMACS2016 - 20th IMACS WORLD CONGRESS</title>
        <loc>Xiamen, China</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416919" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416919</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid315786">
          <title>International Symposium on Iterative Methods in Scientific Computing</title>
          <num>20</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IMACS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid47" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:schmitt:hal-01391569">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01391569"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Discontinuous Galerkin Time Domain Methods for Nonlocal Dispersion Models and Electron Beam Modeling in the Context of Nanoplasmonics</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp78184">
            <foreName>Nikolai</foreName>
            <surname>Schmitt</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stephane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">KWT 2016</title>
        <loc>Riezlern, Austria</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01391569" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01391569</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625408">
          <title>KWT</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle"/>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid48" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:schmitt:hal-01391575">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01391575"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Numerical modeling of electron beam interactions with metallic nanostructures using high order time domain solvers</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp78184">
            <foreName>Nikolai</foreName>
            <surname>Schmitt</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stephane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">School of Plasmonics 2016</title>
        <loc>Cortona, Italy</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01391575" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01391575</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625407">
          <title>School of Plasmonics</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle"/>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid49" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:christopheargenvillier:hal-01374521">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01374521"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">An implicit hybridized discontinuous Galerkin method for the 3D time-domain Maxwell equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp75640">
            <foreName>Alexandra</foreName>
            <surname>Christophe-Argenvillier</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idm28072">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Descombes</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01374521" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01374521</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid50" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:lanteri:hal-01393011">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01393011"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">The multiscale hybrid-mixed method for the maxwell equations in heterogeneous media</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp66624">
            <foreName>Stéphane</foreName>
            <surname>Lanteri</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Diego</foreName>
            <surname>Paredes</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp68072">
            <foreName>Claire</foreName>
            <surname>Scheid</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="nachos-2014-idp91952">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Valentin</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01393011" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01393011</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid2" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:aki-richards:02">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Quantitative seismology</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>K.</foreName>
            <surname>Aki</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.G.</foreName>
            <surname>Richards</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>University Science Books, Sausalito, CA, USA</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2002</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid30" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:busch-etal:11">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Discontinuous Galerkin methods in nanophotonics</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>K.</foreName>
            <surname>Busch</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="graphik-2014-idp89488">
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>König</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Niegemann</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Laser and Photonics Reviews</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1–37</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid18" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:cockburn-etal:09a">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Unified hybridization of discontinuous Galerkin, mixed, and continuous Galerkin methods for second order elliptic problems</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Cockburn</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Gopalakrishnan</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Lazarov</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">SIAM J. Numer. Anal.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">47</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1319–1365</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid4" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:DG:00">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Discontinuous Galerkin methods. Theory, computation and applications</title>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computational Science and Engineering</title>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Cockburn</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>G.E.</foreName>
            <surname>Karniadakis</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Shu</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">11</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer-Verlag</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2000</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid5" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:DG:05">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Special issue on discontinuous Galerkin methods</title>
        <title level="s">J. Sci. Comput.</title>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Cockburn</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Shu</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">22-23</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2005</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid25" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:csaki-etal:11">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Molecular plasmonics: light meets molecules at the nanosacle</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Csaki</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T.</foreName>
            <surname>Schneider</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Wirth</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>N.</foreName>
            <surname>Jahr</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Steinbrück</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>O.</foreName>
            <surname>Stranik</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Garwe</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Müller</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>W.</foreName>
            <surname>Fritzsche</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">369</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">3483–3496</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid6" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:DG:06">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Special issue on discontinuous Galerkin methods</title>
        <title level="s">Comput. Meth. App. Mech. Engng.</title>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Dawson</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">195</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Elsevier</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2006</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid7" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:hesthaven-warburton:07">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Nodal discontinuous Galerkin methods: algorithms, analysis and applications</title>
        <title level="s">Springer Texts in Applied Mathematics</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jan S.</foreName>
            <surname>Hesthaven</surname>
            <initial>J. S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T</foreName>
            <surname>Warburton</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer Verlag</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2007</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid0" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:jackson:98">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Classical Electrodynamics</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.D.</foreName>
            <surname>Jackson</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <edition>Third edition</edition>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>John Wiley and Sons, INC</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1998</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid28" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:ji-etal:07">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">High-order DGTD method for dispersive Maxwell's equations and modelling of silver nanowire coupling</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>X.</foreName>
            <surname>Ji</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>W.</foreName>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.</foreName>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Int. J. Numer. Meth. Engng.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">69</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2007</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">308–325</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid29" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:niegemann-etal:09">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Higher-order time-domain methods for the analysis of nano-photonic systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Niegemann</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="graphik-2014-idp89488">
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>König</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>K.</foreName>
            <surname>Stannigel</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>K.</foreName>
            <surname>Busch</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Photonics Nanostruct.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">7</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2–11</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid27" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:taflove-hagness:05">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Computational electrodynamics: the finite-difference time-domain method (3rd edition)</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Taflove</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.C.</foreName>
            <surname>Hagness</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Artech House</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2005</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid3" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:virieux:86">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">P-SV wave propagation in heterogeneous media: velocity-stress finite difference method</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Virieux</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Geophysics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">51</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1986</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">889–901</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid1" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:yee:66">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Numerical solution of initial boundary value problems involving Maxwell's equations in isotropic media</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>K.S.</foreName>
            <surname>Yee</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Trans. Antennas and Propagation</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">14</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1966</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">302–307</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="nachos-2016-bid26" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:zheng-etal:12">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Molecular plasmonics for biology and nanomedicine</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Y.B.</foreName>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Kiraly</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.S.</foreName>
            <surname>Weiss</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T.J.</foreName>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Nanomedicine</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">7</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">5</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">751–770</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
  </biblio>
</raweb>
