<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2016">
  <identification id="serpico" isproject="true">
    <shortname>SERPICO</shortname>
    <projectName>Space-timE RePresentation, Imaging and cellular dynamics of molecular COmplexes</projectName>
    <theme-de-recherche>Computational Biology</theme-de-recherche>
    <domaine-de-recherche>Digital Health, Biology and Earth</domaine-de-recherche>
    <urlTeam>http://serpico.rennes.inria.fr/</urlTeam>
    <header_dates_team>Creation of the Team: 2010 January 01, updated into Project-Team: 2013 July 01</header_dates_team>
    <LeTypeProjet>Project-Team</LeTypeProjet>
    <keywordsSdN>
      <term>3.1.1. - Modeling, representation</term>
      <term>3.1.2. - Data management, quering and storage</term>
      <term>3.3. - Data and knowledge analysis</term>
      <term>3.4. - Machine learning and statistics</term>
      <term>5.3. - Image processing and analysis</term>
      <term>5.3.2. - Sparse modeling and image representation</term>
      <term>5.3.3. - Pattern recognition</term>
      <term>5.3.4. - Registration</term>
      <term>5.4.4. - 3D and spatio-temporal reconstruction</term>
      <term>5.4.5. - Object tracking and motion analysis</term>
      <term>5.4.6. - Object localization</term>
      <term>5.9.1. - Sampling, acquisition</term>
      <term>5.9.2. - Estimation, modeling</term>
      <term>5.9.3. - Reconstruction, enhancement</term>
      <term>5.9.6. - Optimization tools</term>
      <term>6.1.2. - Stochastic Modeling (SPDE, SDE)</term>
      <term>6.1.3. - Discrete Modeling (multi-agent, people centered)</term>
      <term>6.1.4. - Multiscale modeling</term>
      <term>6.1.5. - Multiphysics modeling</term>
      <term>6.2.3. - Probabilistic methods</term>
      <term>6.2.4. - Statistical methods</term>
      <term>6.2.6. - Optimization</term>
      <term>6.3.1. - Inverse problems</term>
      <term>6.3.2. - Data assimilation</term>
      <term>6.3.3. - Data processing</term>
    </keywordsSdN>
    <keywordsSecteurs>
      <term>1.1.1. - Structural biology</term>
      <term>1.1.3. - Cellular biology</term>
      <term>1.1.9. - Bioinformatics</term>
      <term>1.1.10. - Mathematical biology</term>
      <term>2.2.3. - Cancer</term>
      <term>2.6. - Biological and medical imaging</term>
    </keywordsSecteurs>
    <UR name="Rennes"/>
  </identification>
  <team id="uid1">
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
      <firstname>Charles</firstname>
      <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
      <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
      <lastname>Bouthemy</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="visages-2014-idp105392">
      <firstname>Sylvain</firstname>
      <lastname>Prima</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Researcher, from Sept 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
      <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
      <lastname>Lavancier</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Nantes, Faculty Member, Associate Professor (“Inria delegation”), from Sept 2014</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2016-idp116432">
      <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
      <lastname>Petrazzuoli</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, from Jul 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp112760">
      <firstname>Vincent</firstname>
      <lastname>Briane</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Inria &amp; ENSAI-CREST, from Oct 2014</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2016-idp121376">
      <firstname>Anca-Georgiana</firstname>
      <lastname>Caranfil</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Rennes I, from Dec 2015</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2015-idm5880">
      <firstname>Ancageorgiana</firstname>
      <lastname>Caranfil</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by ANR France-BioImaging project, from Dec 2015 to Nov 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2016-idp126368">
      <firstname>Sandeep</firstname>
      <lastname>Manandhar</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, from Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp103904">
      <firstname>Emmanuel</firstname>
      <lastname>Moebel</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by Région Bretagne, from Nov 2015</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp111528">
      <firstname>Juan Manuel</firstname>
      <lastname>Perez Rua</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Technicolor, granted by CIFRE</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp110280">
      <firstname>Bertha Mayela</firstname>
      <lastname>Toledo Acosta</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Conacyt Grant, from Oct 2014</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
      <firstname>Thierry</firstname>
      <lastname>Pécot</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by ANR France-BioImaging project, from Sept 2013 to Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp114008">
      <firstname>Huguette</firstname>
      <lastname>Bechu</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2016-idp141280">
      <firstname>Aminata</firstname>
      <lastname>Diouf</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Internship Master 1 INSA-Rouen, from Jun 2016 until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="serpico-2014-idp109032">
      <firstname>Hoai Nam</firstname>
      <lastname>Nguyen</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Rennes</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, granted by Innopsys Company, from Oct 2013 to Nov 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
  </team>
  <presentation id="uid2">
    <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid3" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Glossary</bodyTitle>
      <glosslist>
        <label>FLIM</label>
        <li>
          <p>(Fluorescence Lifetime Microscopy Imaging):
imaging of fluorescent molecule lifetimes.</p>
        </li>
        <label>PALM</label>
        <li>
          <p>(Photo-Activated Localization Microscopy):
high-resolution microscopy using stochastic photo-activation of fluorophores and adjustment of point spread functions <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        </li>
        <label>SIM</label>
        <li>
          <p>(Structured Illumination Microscopy):
high-resolution light microscopy using structured patterns and interference analysis <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        </li>
        <label>TIRF</label>
        <li>
          <p>(Total Internal Reflectance):
2D optical microscopy using evanescent waves and total reflectance <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        </li>
        <label>Cryo-EM</label>
        <li>
          <p>(Cryo Electron Tomography):
3D representation of sub-cellular and molecular objects of 5-20 nanometres, frozen at very low temperatures, from 2D projections using a transmission electron microscope.</p>
        </li>
      </glosslist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid4" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Scientific context and motivations</bodyTitle>
      <p>Light microscopy, especially fluorescence microscopy, has
taken a prominent role in life science research due to its ability
to investigate the 3D interior of cells and organisms. It enables to visualize,
in vitro and in vivo, particular biomolecules and proteins (gene
expression) with high specificity through fluorescent labeling (GFP - Green
Fluorescence Protein probes) both at the microscopic and
nanoscopic scales. Nevertheless, the mechanisms of life are very
complex and driven by multimolecular interactions: mitotic spindle,
cell signaling complexes, intracellular transport, cell morphogenesis and motility...
A dynamical quantitative and
integrated description of molecular interactions and coordination
within macromolecular complexes at different scales appears essential today
for the global understanding of live mechanisms. A
long-term research consists in inferring the relationships
between the dynamics of macromolecules and their functions.
This constitutes one of the challenges of modern biology.
The proposed mathematical models and algorithms are mainly developed to identify molecular
processes in fundamental
biology but they have also a strong potential for applications in
biotechnology and medicine: disease diagnosis, detection of genomic
instabilities, deterioration of cell cycle, epigenetic mechanisms and
cancer prevention.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid5" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Objectives in cell imaging</bodyTitle>
      <p>Facing the amount of information provided by
high-throughput multidimensional microscopy, the <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> team investigates computational
and statistical models to better elucidate the role of specific
proteins inside their multiprotein complexes and to help to
decipher the dynamic coordination and organization of molecular complexes at
the single cell level. We investigate image processing methods,
mathematical models, and algorithms to build an integrated imaging
approach that bridges the resolution gaps between the molecule and
the whole cell, in space and time <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. We
address the following topics:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid6">
          <p noindent="true">Image superresolution/image denoising required to preserve cell integrity
(photo-toxicity versus exposure time) and image analysis in
multidimensional microscopy;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid7">
          <p noindent="true">Motion analysis and computation of molecule trajectories in live-cell imaging
to study molecular interactions in space and time);</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid8">
          <p noindent="true">Computational simulation and modelling of molecule trafficking
at different spatial and temporal scales (e.g. biophysical model
assimilation for dynamic representation in video-microscopy and
prediction in biology.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p>We focus on the cellular and molecular mechanisms involved in membrane transport and
trafficking at the scale of a single cell.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid9" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Main challenges in image processing for multimodal and multidimensional microscopy</bodyTitle>
      <p>In most cases, modern microscopy in biology is characterized by a large number of dimensions that
fits perfectly with the complexity of biological features: two or three spatial dimensions,
at macro to nano-scales, and one temporal dimension, sometimes spectrally defined and often corresponding to
one particular bio-molecular species. Dynamic microscopy is also characterized by the nature of the
observable objects (cells, organelles, single molecules, ...), by the large number of
small size and mobile elements (chromosomes, vesicles, ...), by the complexity of the dynamic processes
involving many entities or group of entities sometimes interacting, by particular phenomena of
coalescence often linked to image resolution problems, finally by
the association, dissociation, recomposition or constitution of
those entities (such as membrane fusion and budding). Thus, the
corpus of data to be considered for a comparative analysis of
multiple image series acquisitions is
massive (up to few GigaBytes per hour).
Therefore, it becomes necessary to facilitate and rationalize the production of those multidimensional data, to
improve post acquisition analysis (i.e. image processing) which are
limiting factors in front of the data, and to favor the organization
and the interpretation of the information associated to this data
corpus. It motivates and requires innovative mathematical tools and concepts: data fusion, image
registration, superresolution, data mining, life dynamics modelling, ...</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid10" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Organization and collaborations</bodyTitle>
      <p>In collaboration with UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie (“Space Time imaging of Endomembranes and
organelles Dynamics” team) and PICT-IBiSA (Cell and Tissue Imaging Facilities), the members
of the <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> team participate in several projects (PhD and post-doc
supervision, contracts...) with biologists in the field of cell
biology and microscopy. We have promoted and designed non-parametric
methods since prior knowledge cannot be easily taken into account for
extracting unattended but desired information from image data. We
have proposed user-friendly algorithms for processing 3D or 4D data.</p>
      <p>The scientific projects of the <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> team are complementary to the other on-going
and planned projects of the UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie Unit. A subset of projects is related
to instrumentation in electronic and photonic microscopy (PICT-IBiSA platform) including
computational aspects on the reconstruction and enhancement of images
related to sub-diffraction light microscopy and multimodal approaches.
Our projects rely partially on the results and advances of these instrumental projects and
a positive synergy is foreseen.</p>
    </subsection>
  </presentation>
  <fondements id="uid11">
    <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid12" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Statistics and algorithms for computational microscopy</bodyTitle>
      <p noindent="true">Many live-cell fluorescence imaging experiments are limited in time to prevent phototoxicity
and photobleaching. The amount of light and time required to observe entire cell divisions can
generate biological artifacts. In order to produce images compatible with the dynamic processes
in living cells as seen in video-microscopy, we study the potential of denoising, superresolution,
tracking, and motion analysis methods in the Bayesian and the robust statistics framework to extract
information and to improve image resolution while preserving cell integrity.</p>
      <p>In this area, we have already demonstrated that image denoising allows images to be taken more frequently
or over a longer period of time <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The major advantage is to
preserve cell integrity over time since spatio-temporal information can be restored using computational
methods <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. This idea
has been successfully applied to wide-field, spinning-disk confocal microscopy
<ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, TIRF <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, fast live imaging and 3D-PALM
using the OMX system in collaboration with J. Sedat and M. Gustafsson at UCSF
<ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The corresponding <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-safir</span> denoiser software
(see Section <ref xlink:href="#uid68" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) has been licensed to a large set of laboratories over the world.
New information restoration and image denoising methods are currently investigated to make SIM imaging
compatible with the imaging of molecular dynamics in live cells. Unlike other optical sub-diffraction
limited techniques (e.g. STED <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid10" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, PALM <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) SIM has the strong
advantage of versatility when considering the photo-physical properties of the fluorescent probes
<ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Such developments are also required to be compatible with “high-throughput
microscopy” since several hundreds of cells are observed at the same time and the exposure times are
typically reduced.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid13" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>From image data to descriptors: dynamic analysis and trajectory computation</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid14" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Motion analysis and tracking</bodyTitle>
        <p>The main challenge is to detect and track xFP tags with high precision in movies representing
several GigaBytes of image data. The data are most often collected and processed automatically
to generate information on partial or complete trajectories. Accordingly, we address both
the methodological and computational issues involved in object detection and multiple objects
tracking in order to better quantify motion in cell biology.
Classical tracking methods have limitations as the number of objects and clutter increase. It is
necessary to correctly associate measurements with tracked objects, i.e. to solve the difficult data
association problem <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Data association even combined with sophisticated particle
filtering techniques <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> or matching techniques <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> is problematic
when tracking several hundreds of similar objects with variable velocities. Developing new optical flow
and robust tracking methods and models in this area is then very stimulating since the problems we have
to solve are really challenging and new for applied mathematics. In motion analysis, the goal is to
formulate the problem of optical flow estimations in ways that take physical causes of brightness
constancy violations into account <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid15" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The interpretation of
computed flow fields enables to provide spatio-temporal signatures of particular dynamic processes
(e.g. Brownian and directed motion) and could help to complete the traffic modelling.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid15" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Event detection and motion classification</bodyTitle>
        <p>Protein complexes in living cells undergo multiple states of local concentration or dissociation, sometimes
associated with diffusion processes. These events can be observed at the plasma membrane with TIRF microscopy.
The difficulty arises when it becomes necessary to distinguish continuous motions due to trafficking from
sudden events due to molecule concentrations or their dissociations. Typically, plasma membrane vesicle docking,
membrane coat constitution or vesicle endocytosis are related to these issues.</p>
        <p>Several approaches can be considered for the automatic detection of appearing and vanishing particles (or spots)
in wide-field and TIRF microscopy images. Ideally this could be performed by tracking all the vesicles contained
in the cell <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Among the methods proposed to detect particles in microscopy images
<ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, none is dedicated to the detection of a small number of particles appearing
or disappearing suddenly between two time steps. Our way of handling small blob appearances/dis-appearances
originates from the observation that two successive images are redundant and that occlusions correspond to blobs
in one image which cannot be reconstructed from the other image <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
(see also <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid19" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). Furthermore, recognizing dynamic protein behaviors in
live cell fluorescence microscopy is of paramount importance to understand cell mechanisms. In our studies, it is
challenging to classify intermingled dynamics of vesicular movements, docking/tethering, and ultimately, plasma
membrane fusion of vesicles that leads to membrane diffusion or exocytosis of cargo proteins. Our aim is then to
model, detect, estimate and classify subcellular dynamic events in TIRF microscopy image sequences. We investigate
methods that exploits space-time information extracted from a couple of successive images to classify several
types of motion (directed, diffusive (or Brownian) and confined motion) or compound motion.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid16" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>From models to image data: simulation and modelling of membrane transport</bodyTitle>
      <p>Mathematical biology is a field in expansion, which has evolved into
various branches and paradigms to address problems at various scales
ranging from ecology to molecular structures. Nowadays, system
biology <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid20" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> aims at
modelling systems as a whole in an integrative perspective instead of
focusing on independent biophysical processes. One of the goals of
these approaches is the cell in silico as investigated at Harvard
Medical School (<ref xlink:href="http://vcp.med.harvard.edu/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>vcp.<allowbreak/>med.<allowbreak/>harvard.<allowbreak/>edu/</ref>) or the VCell of the
University of Connecticut Health Center (<ref xlink:href="http://www.nrcam.uchc.edu/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>nrcam.<allowbreak/>uchc.<allowbreak/>edu/</ref>).
Previous simulation-based methods have been investigated to
explain the spatial organization of microtubules <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid21" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
but the method is not integrative and a single scale is used to
describe the visual patterns. In this line of work, we propose
several contributions to combine imaging, traffic and membrane
transport modelling in cell biology.</p>
      <p>In this area, we focus on the analysis of transport
intermediates (vesicles) that deliver cellular components to
appropriate places within cells. We have
already investigated the concept of Network Tomography (NT) <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid22" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> mainly
developed for internet traffic estimation.
The idea is to determine mean traffic intensities based on statistics
accumulated over a period of time. The measurements are usually the
number of vesicles detected at each destination region
receiver. The NT concept has been investigated also
for simulation <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid23" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> since it can be used to
statistically mimic the contents of real traffic image
sequences. In the future, we plan to
incorporate more prior knowledge on dynamics to improve
representation. An important challenge is
to correlate stochastic, dynamical, one-dimensional <i>in silico</i> models
studied at the nano-scale in biophysics, to 3D images acquired in vivo at
the scale of few hundred nanometers.</p>
    </subsection>
  </fondements>
  <domaine id="uid17">
    <bodyTitle>Application Domains</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid18" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Modeling and analysis of membrane transport and molecule trafficking at the single cell scale</bodyTitle>
      <object id="uid19">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/TrafficPb.png" type="float" width="427.0pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Cargo Langerin Trafficking controlled by Rab11A/Rab11FIP2/MyoVb platform.</caption>
      </object>
      <p>In the past recent years, research carried at UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie (“Space Time imaging
of Endomembranes and organelles Dynamics” team) contributed to a
better understanding of the intracellular compartimentation of specialized model cells such as
melanocytes and Langerhans cells, the components and structural events involved in the
biogenesis of their specialized organelles: melanosomes and Birbeck granules, respectively.
These studies have started to highlight: i/
multiple sorting and structural events involved in the biogenesis of these organelles;
ii/ complexity of the endo-melanosomal network of these highly specialized cells;
iii/ complex molecular architecture organizing and coordinating their dynamics;
iv/ intracellular transport steps affected in genetic diseases, among which the Hermansky
Pudlak syndrome (HPS) or involved in viral infection (HIV and Langerin in Langerhans cells).</p>
      <p>In this context, the central aim of <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> is to understand how the different machineries
of molecular components involved are interconnected and coordinated to generate such specialized
structures. We need to address the following topics:</p>
      <orderedlist>
        <li id="uid20">
          <p noindent="true">developing new bioimaging approaches to observe and statistically analyze such
coordinated dynamics in live material;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid21">
          <p noindent="true">correlating this statistically relevant spatiotemporal organization of protein
networks with the biological architectures and at the ultrastructural level;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid22">
          <p noindent="true">modeling intracellular transport of those reference biological complex systems and
proposing new experimental plans in an iterative and virtuous circle;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid23">
          <p noindent="true">managing and analyzing the workflow of image data obtained along different
multidimensional microscopy modalities.</p>
        </li>
      </orderedlist>
      <p>These studies are essential to unravel the complexity of the endomembrane
system and how different machineries evolve together (e.g. see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid19" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>).
They help to control cell organization
and function at different scales through an integrative workflow of methodological and
technological developments.</p>
      <p>At long term, these studies will shed light on the cellular and molecular
mechanisms underlying antigen presentation, viral infection or defense mechanisms, skin
pigmentation, the pathogenesis of hereditary genetic disorders (lysosomal diseases, immune
disorders) and on the mechanisms underlying cell transformation.
Our methodological goal is also to link dynamics information
obtained through diffraction limited light microscopy,
eventually at a time regime compatible with live cell imaging. The overview of
ultrastructural organization will be achieved by complementary electron microscopical
methods. Image visualization and quantitative analysis are of course important and essential
issues in this context.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid24" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Imaging and analysis of cytokskeleton dynamics during cell migration</bodyTitle>
      <p>The ability to migrate in space is among the most fundamental functions of eukaryotic cells and thus is
one of the best-studied phenomena in biology. During embryonic development, cell movements result
in a massive reorganization of the embryo, from a simple spherical ball of cells into a multi-layered
organism; many of the cells at or near the surface of the embryo move to a new, more interior location.
Moreover, inadequate or inappropriate migration of immune cells is also critically important for the
delivery of protective immune responses to tissues and for wound healing. Finally, cell migration may
facilitate the dissemination of tumor cells in blood and organs and eventually the formation of
secondary tumors and metastases.</p>
      <p>It has been established that the cytoskeleton, composed of actin filaments, microtubules and
intermediate filaments (elongated structures with a diameter of a few dozens of nanometers), is
essential for several cell mechanisms, including cell migration, cell division and molecule trafficking:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid25">
          <p noindent="true">i/ the actin filaments promote cell protrusion, adhesion and retraction;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid26">
          <p noindent="true">ii/ the microtubules are the support of molecule traffic and cell polarization;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid27">
          <p noindent="true">iii/ the intermediate filaments are hypothesized to control microtubule organization.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p>Nevertheless, the mechanical and chemical states of migrating cells under various external conditions remain largely unknown. In the last decade, high-resolution microscopy methods led to the discovery of novel
aspects of cell migration. Most approaches and models are limited to migration in 2D, justified by the
flatness of the cell-motile mechanisms. However, the mechanical patterns that govern migration in 2D
models are often not essential for efficient migration in 3D. Accordingly, recent very challenging 3D
models of cells moving on flat surfaces have begun to emerge. The key challenge, however, is to
understand how a 3D motile cell crawls through the 3D extracellular matrix.</p>
      <p>The objective of <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> is to develop high-end signal processing and computer vision tools
to unfold the dynamical coordination of microtubules, actin filaments and intermediate filaments in 3D, involved in cell migration, cell division and molecule trafficking.</p>
    </subsection>
  </domaine>
  <highlights id="uid28">
    <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid29" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid30" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>New projects</bodyTitle>
        <p>The 4 year-ANR-DALLISH proposal (PRC / Challenge 7 / Topic 5), coordinated by the Serpico Team-Project, has been accepted in September 2016.</p>
        <p>The CytoDI Associated Team, in collaboration with University of Texas, SouthWestern Medical Center, Dallas (TX, USA) started in January 2016.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </highlights>
  <logiciels id="uid31">
    <bodyTitle>New Software and Platforms</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid32" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>TMA-Lib</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keyword:</span> Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">TMA-Lib</span> enables to jointly detect (adaptive wavelet transform), segment (parametric active contours) and restore (artifact correction and deconvolution) TMA (Tissue MicroArrays) images.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid33">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants</b>: Hoai Nam Nguyen, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid34">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Partner:</b> INNOPSYS Company.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid35">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid36">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Languages:</b>  C/C++, Matlab.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid37" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>QuantEv</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keyword:</span> Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">QuantEv</span> software is dedicated to the analysis of the spatial distribution of intracellular
events represented by any static or dynamical descriptor (e.g. detected points, segmented regions,
trajectories...), provided that the descriptors are associated with spatial coordinates. QuantEv first
computes 3D histograms of descriptors in a cylindrical coordinate system with computational cell shape
normalization, enabling comparisons between cells of different shape. Densities are obtained via
adaptive kernel density estimation, and we use the Circular Earth Mover's Distance to measure
the dissimilarity between densities associated to different experimental conditions. A statistical
analysis on these distances reliably takes into account the biological variability over replicated
experiments.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid38">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants</b>: Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann, Jean Salamero.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid39">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid40">
          <p noindent="true"><b>On-line demo:</b>  <ref xlink:href="http://mobyle-serpico.rennes.inria.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py#forms::..." location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle-serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>cgi-bin/<allowbreak/>portal.<allowbreak/>py#forms::.<allowbreak/>.<allowbreak/>.</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid41">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Languages:</b>  C/C++ and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> (plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">Icy</span>: <ref xlink:href="http://icy.bioimageanalysis.org" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>icy.<allowbreak/>bioimageanalysis.<allowbreak/>org</ref>).</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid42" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>C-CRAFT</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keyword:</span> Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">C-Craft</span> software enables to jointly segment small particles and estimate background in 2D or 3D fluorescence microscopy image sequences. The vesicle segmentation and background estimation problem is formulated as a global energy minimization problem in the Conditional Random Field framework. A patch-based image representation is used to detect spatial irregularity in the image. An iterative scheme based on graph-cut algorithm is proposed for energy minimization.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid43">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants</b>: Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann, Patrick Bouthemy, Jean Salamero.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid44">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid45">
          <p noindent="true"><b>On-line demo:</b>  <ref xlink:href="http://mobyle-serpico.rennes.inria.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py#forms::C-CRAFT" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle-serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>cgi-bin/<allowbreak/>portal.<allowbreak/>py#forms::C-CRAFT</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid46">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Languages:</b>  C/C++ and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> (plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">Icy</span>: <ref xlink:href="http://icy.bioimageanalysis.org/plugin/C-CRAFT" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>icy.<allowbreak/>bioimageanalysis.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>plugin/<allowbreak/>C-CRAFT</ref>).</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid47">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Reference:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid48" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>ATLAS</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keyword:</span> Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Atlas</span> software enables to detect spots in 2D fluorescence images. The spot size is automatically selected and the detection threshold adapts to the local image dynamics. <span class="smallcap" align="left">Atlas</span> relies on the Laplacian of Gaussian (LoG) filter, which both reduces noise and enhances spots. A multiscale representation of the image is built to automatically select the optimal LoG variance. Local statistics of the LoG image are estimated in a Gaussian window, and the detection threshold is pointwise inferred from a probability of false alarm (PFA). The user only has to specify: i/ standard deviation of the Gaussian window; ii/ PFA value. The Gaussian window must be about the size of the background structures; increasing the PFA increases the number of detections.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid49">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants</b>: Antoine Basset, Patrick Bouthemy, Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid50">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Thierry Pécot, Patrick Bouthemy, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid51">
          <p noindent="true"><b>On-line demo:</b>  <ref xlink:href="http://mobyle-serpico.rennes.inria.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py#forms::ATLAS" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle-serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>cgi-bin/<allowbreak/>portal.<allowbreak/>py#forms::ATLAS</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid52">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Language:</b>  C/C++.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid53">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Reference:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid54" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Hullkground</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Bioinformatics - Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">HullkGround</span> software decomposes a fluorescence microscopy image sequence into two dynamic components: i/ an image sequence showing mobile objects, ii/ an image sequence showing the slightly moving background. Each temporal signal of the sequence is processed individually and analyzed with computational geometry tools. The convex hull is estimated automatically for each pixel and subtracted to the original signal. The method is unsupervised, requires no parameter tuning and is a simplified version of the shape-based scale-space method.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid55">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants:</b> Anatole Chessel, Jean Salamero, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid56">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid57">
          <p noindent="true"><b>APP deposit number:</b> IDDN.FR.001.400005.000.S.P.2009.000.21000</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid58">
          <p noindent="true"><b>On-line demo:</b>  <ref xlink:href="http://mobyle-serpico.rennes.inria.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py#forms::Hullkground" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle-serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>cgi-bin/<allowbreak/>portal.<allowbreak/>py#forms::Hullkground</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid59">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Free distribution:</b>  <ref xlink:href="http://serpico.rennes.inria.fr/doku.php?id=software:hullkground:hullkground" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>doku.<allowbreak/>php?id=software:hullkground:hullkground</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid60">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Language:</b>  <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> (plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span>: <ref xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>rsbweb.<allowbreak/>nih.<allowbreak/>gov/<allowbreak/>ij/</ref>).</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid61" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Motion2D</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Image sequence - Motion model - 2D</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Motion2D</span> software is a multi-platform object-oriented library to estimate 2D parametric motion models in an image sequence. It can handle several types of motion models, namely, constant (translation), affine, and quadratic models. Moreover, it includes the possibility of accounting for a global variation of illumination and more recently for temporal image intensity decay (e.g. due to photo-bleaching decay in fluorescence microscopy). The use of such motion models has been proved adequate and efficient for solving problems such as optic flow computation, motion segmentation, detection of independent moving objects, object tracking, or camera motion estimation, and in numerous application domains (video surveillance, visual servoing for robots, video coding, video indexing), including biological imaging (image stack registration, motion compensation in videomicroscopy). Motion2D is an extended and optimized implementation of the robust, multi-resolution and incremental estimation method (exploiting only the spatio-temporal derivatives of the image intensity function). Real-time processing is achievable for motion models involving up to six parameters. Motion2D can be applied to the entire image or to any pre-defined window or region in the image.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid62">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants:</b> Patrick Bouthemy, Jean-Marc Odobez, Fabien Spindler.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid63">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Patrick Bouthemy, Fabien Spindler.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid64">
          <p noindent="true"><b>APP deposit number:</b> FR.001.520021.001.S.A.1998.000.21000 / release 1.3.11, January 2005)</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid65">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Free academic software distribution:</b>   <ref xlink:href="http://www.irisa.fr/vista/Motion2D" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>irisa.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>vista/<allowbreak/>Motion2D</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid66">
          <p noindent="true"><b>On-line demo:</b>  <ref xlink:href="http://mobyle-serpico.rennes.inria.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py#forms::Motion2D" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle-serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>cgi-bin/<allowbreak/>portal.<allowbreak/>py#forms::Motion2D</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid67">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Languages:</b>  C/C++ and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> (plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span>: <ref xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>rsbweb.<allowbreak/>nih.<allowbreak/>gov/<allowbreak/>ij/</ref>).</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid68" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>ND-SAFIR</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Biology - Health - Image analysis - Photonic imaging - Fluorescence microscopy - Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Scientific Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-Safir</span> software removes additive Gaussian and non-Gaussian noise in still 2D or 3D images or in 2D or 3D image sequences (without any motion computation) <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The method is unsupervised and is based on a pointwise selection of small image patches of fixed size (a data-driven adapted way) in spatial or space-time neighbourhood of each pixel (or voxel). The main idea is to modify each pixel (or voxel) using the weighted sum of intensities within an adaptive 2D or 3D (or 2D or 3D + time) neighbourhood and to use image patches to take into account complex spatial interactions. The
neighbourhood size is selected at each spatial or space-time position according to a bias-variance criterion. The algorithm requires no tuning of control parameters (already calibrated with statistical
arguments) and no library of image patches. The method has been applied to real noisy images (old photographs, <span class="smallcap" align="left">jpeg</span>-coded images, videos, ...) and is exploited in different biomedical application domains (time-lapse fluorescence microscopy, video-microscopy, <span class="smallcap" align="left">mri</span> imagery, <span class="smallcap" align="left">x</span>-ray imagery, ultrasound imagery, ...).</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid69">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants:</b> Jérôme Boulanger, Charles Kervrann, Patrick Bouthemy, Jean Salamero.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid70">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Partners:</b> INRA, PiCT - CNRS - Institut Curie.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid71">
          <p noindent="true"><b>APP deposit number:</b> IDDN.FR.001.190033.002.S.A.2007.000.21000 / new release 3.0 in 2013)</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid72">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Free academic software distribution:</b> Binaries of the software <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-safir</span> are freely and electronically distributed (<ref xlink:href="http://serpico.rennes.inria.fr/doku.php?id=software:nd-safir:index" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>doku.<allowbreak/>php?id=software:nd-safir:index</ref>).</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid73">
          <p noindent="true"><b>On-line demo:</b>  <ref xlink:href="http://mobyle-serpico.rennes.inria.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py#forms::NDSafir" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle-serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>cgi-bin/<allowbreak/>portal.<allowbreak/>py#forms::NDSafir</ref></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid74">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Languages:</b>  C/C++, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Matlab</span> and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> (plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span>: <ref xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>rsbweb.<allowbreak/>nih.<allowbreak/>gov/<allowbreak/>ij/</ref>). The C/C++ software has been developed under Linux using the CImg library and has been tested over several platforms such as Linux/Unix, Windows XP and Mac OS.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid75">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Commercial licence agreements:</b> Innopsys, Roper Scientfic, Photmetrics, Nikon Europe BV (2016).</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid76">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Reference:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid77" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>F2D-SAFIR</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keyword:</span> Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">F2d -safir</span> software removes mixed Gaussian-Poisson noise in large 2D images, typically <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><msup><mn>10</mn><mn>3</mn></msup><mo>×</mo><msup><mn>10</mn><mn>3</mn></msup></mrow></math></formula> pixels, in a few seconds. The method is unsupervised and is a simplified version of the method related to the <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-safir</span> software. The software dedicated to microarrays image denoising, was licensed to the INNOPSYS company which develops scanners for disease diagnosis and multiple applications (gene expression, genotyping, aCGH, ChIP-chip, microRNA, ...).</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid78">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participant</b>: Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid79">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Partner:</b> INRA.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid80">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Charles Kervrann.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid81">
          <p noindent="true"><b>APP deposit number:</b> IDDN.FR.001.190033.001.S.A.2007.000.21000</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid82">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Language:</b>  C/C++.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid83" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>TubuleJ</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Bioinformatics - Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">TubuleJ</span> software written in java (plug-in ImageJ) is devoted to the analysis of microtubules and helical structures in 2D cryo electron microscope images. The software straightens curved microtubule images by estimating automatically point locations on the microtubule axis. The estimation of microtubule principal axis relies on microtubule cylindrical shape analyzed in the Fourier domain. A user-friendly interface enables to filter straight fiber images by selecting manually the layer lines of interest in the Fourier domain. This software can be used to generate a set of 2D projection views from a single microtubule projection view and a few parameters of this microtubule structure.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid84">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants:</b> Denis Chrétien, Charles Kervrann, Sophie Blestel.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid85">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Denis Chrétien.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid86">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Partners:</b> University of Rennes 1, CNRS.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid87">
          <p noindent="true"><b>APP deposit number:</b> IDDN.FR.001.240023.000.S.P.2011.000.21000</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid88">
          <p noindent="true">
            <b>On-line demo:</b>
            <ref xlink:href="http://equipes.igdr.univ-rennes1.fr/en/tips/Software/TubuleJ/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>equipes.<allowbreak/>igdr.<allowbreak/>univ-rennes1.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>en/<allowbreak/>tips/<allowbreak/>Software/<allowbreak/>TubuleJ/</ref>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid89">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Language:</b>  <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> (plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span>: <ref xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>rsbweb.<allowbreak/>nih.<allowbreak/>gov/<allowbreak/>ij/</ref>).</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid90" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Cryo-Seg</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Keywords:</span> Bioinformatics - Biomedical imaging</p>
      <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description:</span>
 The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Cryo-Seg</span> software has been developed to detect microtubule structures and helical structures in 2D cryo electron microscope images. Cryo electron tomography allows 3D observation of biological specimens in their hydrated state. Segmentation is formulated as Maximum A Posteriori estimation problem and exploits image patches to take into account spatial contexts (Markov Random Fields). Because of the contrast anisotropy in the specimen thickness direction, the whole tomogram is segmented section by section, with an automatic update of reference patches. This algorithm has been evaluated on synthetic data and on cryo electron tomograms of in vitro microtubules. On real data, this segmentation method extracts the most contrasted regions of microtubules, and 3D visualization is improved.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid91">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Participants:</b> Denis Chrétien, Charles Kervrann, Sophie Blestel.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid92">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Denis Chrétien.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid93">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Partners:</b> University of Rennes 1, CNRS.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid94">
          <p noindent="true"><b>Languages:</b>  C/C++ and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> (plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span>: <ref xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>rsbweb.<allowbreak/>nih.<allowbreak/>gov/<allowbreak/>ij/</ref>).</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid95" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Platforms</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid96" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Mobyle@<span class="smallcap" align="left">Serpico</span> plateform and software distribution</bodyTitle>
        <object id="uid97">
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <ressource xlink:href="IMG/MobyleatSERPICO.png" type="float" width="426.79134pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <caption>Mobyle@<span class="smallcap" align="left">Serpico</span> web portal.</caption>
        </object>
        <p>The objective is to disseminate the distribution of <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> image processing software for biologists:</p>
        <p noindent="true"> </p>
        <p noindent="true"><b>Free binaries:</b> software packages have been compiled for the main operating systems (Linux, MacOS, Windows) using CMake (see <ref xlink:href="http://www.cmake.org/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>cmake.<allowbreak/>org/</ref>). They are freely available on the team website under a proprietary license (e.g. <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-Safir</span> and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Hullkground</span> are distributed this way at <ref xlink:href="http://serpico.rennes.inria.fr/doku.php?id=software:index" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>doku.<allowbreak/>php?id=software:index</ref>).</p>
        <p noindent="true"> </p>
        <p noindent="true"><i>Mobyle@</i><span class="smallcap" align="left">Serpico</span><i> web portal</i>: An on-line version of the image processing algorithms has been developped using the Mobyle framework (Institut Pasteur, see <ref xlink:href="http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle.<allowbreak/>pasteur.<allowbreak/>fr/</ref>). The main role of this web portal (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid97" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) is to demonstrate the performance of the programs developed by the team: <span class="smallcap" align="left">QuantEv</span>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">C-Craft</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Atlas</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">HotSpotDetection</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid26" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Hullkground</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid27" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">KLTracker</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid28" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Motion2D</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid29" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">MS-detect</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid30" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-Safir</span><ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">OpticalFlow</span> and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Flux Estimation</span> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The web interface makes our image processing methods available for biologists at Mobyle@SERPICO (<ref xlink:href="http://mobyle-serpico.rennes.inria.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py#welcome" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>mobyle-serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>cgi-bin/<allowbreak/>portal.<allowbreak/>py#welcome</ref>) without any installation or configuration on their own. The size of submitted images is limited to 200 MegaBytes per user and all the results are kept 15 days. The web portal and calculations run on a server with 2 CPU x 8 cores, 64 GigaBytes of RAM (500 MegaBytes for each user / Data is saved for 3 months).</p>
        <p noindent="true"> </p>
        <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span><b> plug-ins</b>: <span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span> (see <ref xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>rsb.<allowbreak/>info.<allowbreak/>nih.<allowbreak/>gov/<allowbreak/>ij/</ref>) is a widely used image visualization and analysis software for biologist users. We have developed <span class="smallcap" align="left">ImageJ</span> plug-in <span class="smallcap" align="left">Java</span> versions of the following software: <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-Safir</span> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Hullkground</span> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid27" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Motion2D</span> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid29" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">HotSpotDetection</span> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid26" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Stlas</span> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. The <span class="smallcap" align="left">C-Craft</span> algorithm <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> has been developped for the image processing ICY platform (<ref xlink:href="http://icy.bioimageanalysis.org/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>icy.<allowbreak/>bioimageanalysis.<allowbreak/>org/</ref>).</p>
        <p noindent="true"> </p>
        <p noindent="true"><b>Institut Curie CID iManage database</b>: The microscopy facility of Institut Curie has co-developped a commercial database system (CID iManage/Strand Avadis company). The database can be searched via meta-data and includes menu selections that enable to run remote processing from a cluster. We have integrated <span class="smallcap" align="left">ND-Safir</span> and <span class="smallcap" align="left">Hullkground</span> in the interface environment to allow the database users to process their images easily, and store associated results and parameters used.</p>
        <p noindent="true"> </p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid98">
            <p noindent="true"><b>Participants:</b> Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann, Charles Deltel (Inria Rennes SED).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid99">
            <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann.</p>
            <p noindent="true"> </p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid100" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>IGRIDA-Serpico cluster</bodyTitle>
        <p>The IGRIDA-Serpico cluster of 200 nodes is opened for end-users for large scale computing and data sets processing (200 TeraBytes).</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid101">
            <p noindent="true"><b>Batch Scheduler:</b> OAR</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid102">
            <p noindent="true"><b>File management:</b> Puppet / Git / Capistrano</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid103">
            <p noindent="true"><b>OS:</b> Linux Debian 7</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid104">
            <p noindent="true"><b>User connexion:</b> public ssh key</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid105">
            <p noindent="true"><b>Contact:</b> Thierry Pécot, Charles Kervrann, Charles Deltel (Inria Rennes SED).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </logiciels>
  <resultats id="uid106">
    <bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid107" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Statistical aggregation methods for image denoising and estimation</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
          <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
          <lastname>Lavancier</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>In the line of the Non-Local means <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid31" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and ND-SAFIR <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> denoising algorithms, we have proposed a novel adaptive estimator based on the weighted average of observations taken in a neighborhood with weights depending on image data. The idea is to compute adaptive weights that best minimize an upper bound of the pointwise <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msub><mi>L</mi><mn>2</mn></msub></math></formula> risk. In the framework of adaptive estimation, we show that the “oracle” weights depend on the unknown image and are optimal if we consider triangular kernels instead of the commonly-used Gaussian kernel. Furthermore, we propose a way to automatically choose the spatially varying smoothing parameter for adaptive denoising. Under conventional minimal regularity conditions, the obtained estimator converges at the usual optimal rate. The implementation of the proposed algorithm is also straightforward. The simulations show that our algorithm improves significantly the classical NL-means, and is competitive when compared to the more sophisticated NL-means filters both in terms of PSNR values and visual quality.</p>
      <p>Previously, we investigated statistical aggregation methods which optimally combine several estimators to produce a boosted solution <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid32" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In this range of work, we also introduced in <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid33" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> a general method to combine estimators in order to produce a better estimate. From a theoretical point of view, we proved that this method is optimal in some sense. It is illustrated on standard statistical problems in parametric and semi-parametric models where the averaging estimator outperforms the initial estimators in most cases. This method has been subsequently adapted in <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid34" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> to models in spatial statistics.
As part of an on-going work, we are applying this method to improve patch-based image denoising algorithms.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>References:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid33" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid34" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Qiyu Jin (School of Mathematical Science, Inner Mongolia University, China),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Ion Grama and Quansheng Liu (University of Bretagne-Sud, Vannes),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Paul Rochet (Laboratoire de Mathématiques Jean Leray (LMJL), University of Nantes).</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid108" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Algorithms for dejittering and deconvolving large fluorescence and Tissue MicroArray (TMA) images</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp109032">
          <firstname>Hoai Nam</firstname>
          <lastname>Nguyen</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2016-idp116432">
          <firstname>Giovanni</firstname>
          <lastname>Petrazzuoli</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2016-idp141280">
          <firstname>Aminata</firstname>
          <lastname>Diouf</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>In fluorescence microscopy, the image quality is limited by out-of-focus blur and high noise. Traditionally, image deconvolution is needed to estimate a good quality version of the observed image. The result of deconvolution depends heavily on the choice of the regularization term and the noise dependent fidelity term. The regularization functional should be designed to remove noise while preserving image discontinuities. Accordingly, we investigated new regularization terms to preserve fine details of underlying structures and we studied appropriate proximal algorithms. The deconvolution method has been especially dedicated to large 2D <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mn>20000</mn><mo>×</mo><mn>60000</mn></mrow></math></formula> images acquired with ISO scan imager (see Fig.<ref xlink:href="#uid109" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). The images are preliminary pre-processed to compensate non constant pixel displacement during acquisition/scanning (dejittering effect). The method has also been evaluated on 2D Vimentin filament images (UTSW, CytoDI Associated Team) to facilitate filament segmentation. The method is able to process a <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mn>512</mn><mo>×</mo><mn>512</mn></mrow></math></formula> image in 250 ms with a non optimized implementation.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Vincent Paveau and Cyril Cauchois (Innopys company),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Philippe Roudot (UTSW, Dallas, USA).</p>
      <object id="uid109">
        <table rend="inline">
          <tr style="">
            <td style="text-align:center;" halign="center">
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/TMA-Dejitter-Deconv.png" type="inline" height="192.1487pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <caption/>
        </table>
        <caption>Illustration of image dejittering and deconvolution algorithms applied to a selected fluorescence region extracted from a large TMA image (by courtesy of Innopsys).</caption>
      </object>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid110" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Quantifying the spatial distribution of intracellular events</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
          <firstname>Thierry</firstname>
          <lastname>Pécot</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <object id="uid111">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/Quantev.png" type="float" height="341.6013pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Overview of QuantEv approach.</caption>
      </object>
      <p>Automated processing of fluorescence microscopy data allows quantifying cell phenotypes
in an objective and reproducible way. However, most computational methods are based on the
complex combination of heterogeneous features such as statistical, geometrical, morphological
and frequency properties, which makes difficult to draw definitive biological conclusions. Additionally,
most experimental designs, especially at single cell level, pool together data coming
from replicated experiments of a given condition, neglecting the biological variability between
individual cells. To address these issues, we developed a generic and non-parametric
framework (QuantEv) to study the spatio-temporal distribution of moving Rab6 membranes
and the effect of actin disruption on Rab11 trafficking in coordination with cell shape.
The main advantage of QuantEv is to process robustly and accurately homogeneous and heterogeneous populations. As
demonstration, we compared the results obtained by QuantEv with those from kernel density
maps, for Rab6 positive membranes on crossbow- and disk-shaped cells.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Jean Salamero, Jérôme Boulanger and Liu Zengzhen (UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie).</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"/>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid112" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Correlation-based method for membrane diffusion estimation during exocytosis in TIRFM</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2015-idm5880">
          <firstname>Ancageorgiana</firstname>
          <lastname>Caranfil</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>The dynamics of the plasma membrane of the cell is not fully understood yet; one of the crucial aspects to clarify is the diffusion process during exocytosis. Several image acquisition modalities exist, including TIRFM (Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence Microscopy), that have successfully been used to determine the successive steps of exocytosis. However, computing characteristic values for plasma membrane dynamics is problematic, as the experimental conditions have a strong influence on the obtained data, and a general model of molecular interaction dynamics cannot be determined.</p>
      <p>This year, we have continued our study of correlation-based methods for local diffusion estimation in TIRFM images. Our original method was tested on both synthetic and real images showing an isolated diffusion event, and a robust algorithm was developed to cope with noisy data. Our first model was linear and had only two parameters to estimate. Diffusion coefficient estimation was accurate on synthetic images even with moderate to low signal-to-noise ratio, and within reasonable margins of error on real images with little noise. We have then extended our mathematical model by using a global approach subject to initial local diffusion conditions. Isolated diffusion events are well described, but this new model can also handle the case of noisy images with non-uniform background, and the case of two or more diffusion events in the region of interest. The extended model is non-linear but has few parameters to estimate. An iterative minimization method is used to fit the model parameters to the data points (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid113" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). Despite non-linearity, results are accurate on images with pure diffusion events and show robustness to background. The quality of parameters estimation is barely influenced by the length and size of the input TIRFM sequence, which is not the case with standard correlation methods. We have thus developed a correlation-based method that is able to estimate diffusion in a variety of cases in TIRFM images (Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid113" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>).</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Francois Waharte (UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie, PICT-IBiSA),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Perrine Paul-Gilloteaux (UMS 3556, IRS-UN, Nantes).</p>
      <object id="uid113">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/SpotDiffusion.png" type="float" height="213.5pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Local diffusion estimation in both synthetic (black and white spots) and real TIRF images (green spots, UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie, PICT-IBiSA). Only three frames of each sequence are shown. The computed autocorrelation values (in black) for different temporal lag values, and the fitting function for these values (in green) are given (plot in the middle) for the upper-right sequence.</caption>
      </object>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid114" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Colocalization for live cell and super-resolution imaging</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
          <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
          <lastname>Lavancier</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
          <firstname>Thierry</firstname>
          <lastname>Pécot</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>In the context of bioimaging, colocalization refers to the detection of emissions from two or more fluorescent molecules within the same pixel of the image. This approach enables to quantify the protein-protein interactions inside the cell, just at the resolution limit of the microscope. In statistics, this amounts to characterizing the joint spatial repartition and the spatial overlap between different fluorescent labels. Two distinct categories of colocalization approaches are considered to address this issue: intensity-based methods and object-based methods. The popular (intensity-based) Pearson's correlation method, which returns values between -1 and +1, is known to be sensitive to high intensity backgrounds and provides errors if the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) is typically low. The object-based method, recommended in single molecule imaging, analyses the spatial distribution of the two sets of detected spots by using point process statistics.</p>
      <p>Accordingly, we developed an original, fast, robust-to-noise and versatile approach that reconciles intensity-based and object-based methods for both conventional diffraction-limited microscopy and sub-resolved microscopy. The procedure is only controlled by a p-value and tests whether the Pearson correlation between two binary images is significantly positive. This amount to quantifying the interaction strength by the area/volume of the intersection between the two binary
images viewed as random distributions of geometrical objects. Under mild assumptions, it turns out that the appropriately normalized Pearson correlation follows a standard normal distribution under the null hypothesis if the number of image pixels is large. Unlike previous methods, the method handles 2D and 3D images, variable SNRs and any kind of cell shapes. It is able to colocalize large regions with small dots, as it is the case in TIRF-PALM experiments and to detect negative colocalization. The typical processing time is two milliseconds per image pair in 2D and a few seconds in 3D, with no dependence on the number of objects per image. Finally, the method provides maps to geocolocalize molecule interactions in specific image regions.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Jean Salamero and Liu Zengzhen (UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie).</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"/>
      <object id="uid115">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/GPSco.png" type="float" height="213.5pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Illustration of statistical spatio-temporal colocalization. a) Average intensity projection of a 3D TIRF acquisition showing m-Cherry Langerin (red channel) and GFP Rab11A proteins (green channel) (courtesy of UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie); b) test statistic value with respect to the shift between frames.</caption>
      </object>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid116" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Classification of diffusion dynamics from particle trajectories</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp112760">
          <firstname>Vincent</firstname>
          <lastname>Briane</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>In this study, we are currently interested in describing the dynamics of particles inside live cell. We assume that the motions of particles follow a certain class of random process: the diffusion processes. In 2015, we developed a statistical test to classify the intracellular motions into three groups : free diffusion (<i>i-e</i> Brownian motion), subdiffusion and superdiffusion. This method is an alternative to the commonly used Mean Square Displacement (MSD) analysis. This year, we have studied theoretical properties of our procedure. We have shown that it behaves well asymptotically, that is when we observe the particle trajectory for a very long time, for certain parametric models. The models on which we assess our procedure are representative of the three classes aforementioned and extensively used in the literature. Among them we can cite Brownian motion with drift, Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process and fractional Brownian motion. An illustration of the testing procedure is shown in Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid117" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      <p>We also extend our method to address two different questions. First, we are interested in testing a large number of trajectories. The first version of our test is a single test procedure. It is known that applying multiple times a test without care leads to a high number of false positives. Then, we modify our initial method to overcome this problem. Secondly, in the case in which we observe very long trajectories, it is likely that the particle motion changes over time. Therefore, we are currently adapting our initial procedure to detect change-point along a single trajectory.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt"><b>Collaborators:</b> Myriam Vimond (ENSAI Rennes),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Jean Salamero (UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie).</p>
      <object id="uid117">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/TOTH_SPTPalm.png" type="float" height="256.2026pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Labelling of the dynamics of trajectories in Single Particle Tracking PALM (Courtesy of Institut Interdisciplinaire de Neurosciences CNRS UMR 5297). The color code is green for subdiffusion, blue for Brownian motion and red for superdiffusion.</caption>
      </object>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid118" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Inference for spatial Gibbs point processes</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
          <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
          <lastname>Lavancier</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>Gibbs point processes are popular and widely used models in spatial statistics to describe the repartition of points or geometrical structures in space. They initially arose from statistical physics where they are models for interacting particles. They are now used in as different domains as astronomy, biology, computer science, ecology, forestry, image analysis and materials science.</p>
      <p>Assuming a parametric form of the Gibbs interaction, the natural method to estimate the parameters is likelihood inference. Since its first use in the 80’s, this method is conjectured to be consistent and efficient. However the theoretical properties of maximum likelihood for Gibbs point processes remain largely unknown. In <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid35" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we partly solved this 30 years old conjecture by proving the consistency of the likelihood procedure for a large class of Gibbs models. As important examples, we deduce the consistency of the maximum likelihood estimator for all parameters of the Strauss model, the hardcore Strauss model, the Lennard-Jones model and the area-interaction model, which are commonly used models in practice.</p>
      <p>A practical issue of likelihood estimation yet is that this method depends on an intractable normalizing constant that has to be approximated by simulation. To avoid this problem, other methods of estimation have been introduced, including pseudo-likelihood estimation. The theoretical properties of the pseudo-likelihood method are fairly well known in the case of finite-range Gibbs interactions. However this setting rules out some major Gibbs model as the Lennard-Jones model. In <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid36" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we extend the pseudo-likelihood procedure to infinite range Gibbs interactions and we prove its consistency and its asymptotic normality.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt"><b>References:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid36" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid35" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> David Dereudre (Laboratoire Paul Painlevé (UMR 8524), University of Lille 1),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Jean-François Coeurjolly (Laboratoire Jean Kutzmann, University of Grenoble).</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid119" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Statistical aspects of Determinantal Point Processes</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
          <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
          <lastname>Lavancier</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p noindent="true">Determinantal point processes (DPPs) have been introduced in their general form by Macchi (1975) and have been extensively studied from a probabilistic point of view in the 2000’s (one of the main reason being their central role in random matrix theory). In a previous work, we have demonstrated that DPPs provide useful models for the description of spatial point pattern datasets where nearby points repel each other.</p>
      <p>In <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid37" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we have addressed the question of how repulsive a stationary DPP can be, in order to assess the range of practical situations this promising class of models may model. We determine the most repulsive DPP (in some sense) and we introduce new parametric families of stationary DPPs that can cover a large range of DPPs, from the stationary Poisson process (the case of no interaction) to the most repulsive DPP.
Some theoretical aspects of inference for stationary DPPs are tackled in <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid38" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid39" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In the former study we establish the Brillinger mixing property of stationary DPPs, a first important step toward asymptotic inference. In the latter contribution, we exploit this result to deduce the consistency and asymptotic properties of contrast estimators for stationary DPPs.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>References:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid38" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid37" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid39" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Christophe Ange Napoléon Biscio (LMJL, University of Nantes),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Jesper Möller (Department of Mathematical Sciences, Aalborg University, Denmark),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Ege Rubak (Department of Mathematical Sciences, Aalborg University, Denmark).</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid120" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Modeling aggregation and regularity in spatial point pattern datasets</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
          <firstname>Frédéric</firstname>
          <lastname>Lavancier</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p noindent="true">In the spatial point process literature, analysis of spatial point pattern datasets are often classified into three main cases: (i) Regularity (or inhibition or repulsiveness), modelled by Gibbs point processes, hard core processes like Matern hard core models, and determinantal point processes; (ii) Complete spatial randomness, modelled by Poisson point processes; (iii) Aggregation (or clustering), modelled by Poisson cluster processes and Cox processes. For applications the classification (i)-(iii) can be too simplistic, and there is a lack of useful spatial point process models with, loosely speaking, aggregation on the large scale and regularity on the small scale. For instance, we may be interested in such a model for the repartition of the centres of vesicles in a cell, that exhibit some spatial clustering at large scales while having a minimal distance between them.</p>
      <p>In <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid40" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we have considered a dependent thinning of a regular point process with the aim of obtaining aggregation on the large scale and regularity on the small scale in the resulting target point process of retained points. Various parametric models for the underlying processes are suggested and the properties of the target point process are studied. Simulation and inference procedures are discussed when a realization of the target point process is observed, depending on whether the thinned points are also observed or not.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt"><b>Reference:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid40" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborator:</b> Jesper Möller (Department of Mathematical Sciences, Aalborg University, Denmark).</p>
      <p noindent="true"> </p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid121" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Multi-scale spot segmentation with automatic selection of image scales</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp110280">
          <firstname>Bertha Mayela</firstname>
          <lastname>Toledo Acosta</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
          <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
          <lastname>Bouthemy</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p noindent="true">Detecting spot-like objects of different sizes in images is required for many applications. A spot detection framework can be divided in three sub-steps : first, image preprocessing to smooth out noise; second, signal enhancement to highlight spots; third, spot detection by thresholding; the two first ones being often merged in a single operator. However, elements of interest do not all correspond to the same image scale, if the collection includes subgroups of different sizes or if perspective effects occur. Then, the need is not merely the selection of the optimal image scale, but of all the meaningful scales. We dealt with the problem of multi-scale spot detection while automatically selecting the meaningful scales. Our primary interest is to detect particles in microscopy images, but our method can be applied to other types of images as well. We defined an original criterion based on the a contrario approach and the LoG scale-space framework to automatically select the meaningful scales. We designed a coarse-to-fine multi-scale spot segmentation scheme involving a locally adaptive thresholding across scales, to come up with the final map of segmented spots. We carried out experimental results on simulated and real images of different types, and we demonstrated that our method outperforms other existing methods.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Reference:</b>  paper accepted, ICASSP'2017.</p>
      <p noindent="true"><b>Collaborator:</b> Antoine Basset (CNES, Toulouse).</p>
      <p noindent="true"> </p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid122" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Multi-modal registration for correlative light-electron microscopy</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp110280">
          <firstname>Bertha Mayela</firstname>
          <lastname>Toledo Acosta</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
          <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
          <lastname>Bouthemy</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p noindent="true">We pursue our work on correlative light-electron microscopy (CLEM), which combines the strengths of two different imaging modalities, light microscopy (LM) and electron microscopy (EM), to jointly study intracellular dynamics and ultrastructure of a biological sample. CLEM registration is an important and difficult problem given the significant differences between LM and EM images regarding resolution, field of view, image size and appearance. We designed an automated approach for retracing and registering CLEM images, by implementing a patch-based search using a common Laplacian of Gaussian (LoG) image representation of the LM and EM images. We have redefined the geometry of the patch, opting for a disk-shaped patch. The search (or retracing) step uses histogram-based methods as they are invariant to rotation, and it provides a pre-registration by producing the estimate of the translation component. Usually, there is a large disparity on the orientation of EM and LM images. To handle this problem, we have implemented a mutual information-based method to compute the rotation between the EM and LM patches and to refine the registration. We have also tackled the registration issue in both directions (LM to EM, and EM to LM), and compared our approach to a correlation-based method.</p>
      <p>We have tested our approach on a larger set of real CLEM images (provided by Institut Curie) presenting a large diversity in content, image size, and appearance, further validating our method (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid123" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). We are currently exploring how our automated CLEM registration method could be exploited to guide EM acquisition within a coarse-to-fine framework.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt"><b>Reference:</b>  <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid41" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
      <p noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Xavier Heiligenstein (UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Grégoire Malandain (Inria, Morpheme EPC, Sophia-Antipolis).</p>
      <object id="uid123">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/Regclem2016.png" type="float" height="256.2026pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Figure 1. CLEM experiment (images from UMR 144 CNRS-Institut Curie, Xavier Heiligenstein): a) EM image with Region of Interest (ROI) framed in green; b) ground-truth location of the corresponding LM patch framed in green; c) ROI delineated in the Log-EM image, framed in green; d) selected patch (SP) in the LoG-LM image, framed in blue to be comaprd with the green disk in b); f) overlay (after registration).</caption>
      </object>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid124" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Denoising and compensation of the missing wedge in cryo electron tomography</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp103904">
          <firstname>Emmanuel</firstname>
          <lastname>Moebel</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>In this study, we address two important issues in cryo electron tomography (CET) images: reduction of noise and restoration of information in the missing wedge (MW). The MW is responsible for several type of imaging artifacts, and arises because of limited angle tomography: it is observable in the Fourier domain and is depicted by a region where Fourier coefficient values are unknown (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid125" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). The proposed stochastic method tackles the restoration problem by filling up the MW by iterating following steps : adding noise into the MW (step 1) and applying a denoising algorithm (step 2). The role of the first step is to propose candidates for the missing Fourier coefficients and the second step acts as a regularizer. A constraint is added in the spectral domain by imposing the known Fourier coefficients to be unchanged through iterations.</p>
      <p>Several aspects of the method have been studied in order to gain a deeper understanding of this strategy: different kinds of noise as well as several denoising algorithms (BM3D, NL-Bayes, NL-means, Total Variation...) have been evaluated. Furthermore, different kinds of transforms have been tested in order to apply the constraint (Fourier transform, Cosine transform, pseudo-polar Fourier transform). Also, a process has been set up in order to evaluate the performance of the proposed method on experimental data. Thus, convincing results on experimental data have been achieved (see Fig. <ref xlink:href="#uid125" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) using the Fourier Shell Correlation (FSC) as an evaluation metric. In order to measure the quality of the recovered MW only, we also compute the FSC over the MW support (“constrained FSC”).</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Damien Larivière (Fondation Fourmentin-Guilbert),</p>
      <p noindent="true">                          Julio Ortiz (Max-Planck Institute, Martinsried, Germany).</p>
      <object id="uid125">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/mwrec_ribosome.png" type="float" height="384.2974pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Experimental sub-tomogram containing ribosomes attached to a membrane. (a) Top row: original data in the spectral (left) and spatial (middle) domains and 3D view of the thresholded data (right). Bottom row: denoised data shown as above. (b) FSC and constrained FSC measures of the method input (in black) and output (in red). All measures are wrt the same reference.</caption>
      </object>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid126" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Spatially-variant kernel for optical flow under low signal-to-noise ratios</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
          <firstname>Charles</firstname>
          <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
        </person>
        <p>.</p>
      </participants>
      <p>Local and global approaches can be identified as the two main classes of optical flow estimation methods. This year, we have proposed a framework to combine the advantages of these two principles, namely robustness to noise of the local approach and discontinuity preservation of the global approach. The idea is to adapt spatially the local support of the local parametric constraint in the combined local-global model <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid42" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. To this end, we jointly estimate the motion field and the parameters of the spatial support. We apply our approach to the case of Gaussian filtering, and we derive efficient minimization schemes for usual data terms. The estimation of a spatially varying standard deviation map prevents from the smoothing of motion discontinuities, while ensuring robustness to noise. We validated our method for a standard model and demonstrated how a baseline approach with pixel-wise data term can be improved when integrated in our framework. The method has been evaluated on the Middlebury benchmark with ground truth and on real fluorescence microscopy data for which noise is the main limitation for usual optical flow methods.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Collaborator:</b> Denis Fortun (EPFL-BIG, Lausanne, Switzerland)</p>
      <p noindent="true">                         Noémie Debroux (Laboratory of Mathematics, INSA Rouen, Normandie University)</p>
      <object id="uid127">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <ressource xlink:href="IMG/CLG.png" type="float" height="320.25pt" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest" media="WEB"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <caption>Visual results obtained with variants of CLG (“Combined Local-Global”) methods for several values of regularization parameters <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>λ</mi></math></formula>: CLG-A (our adaptive CLG), CLG<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msub><mrow/><mn>0</mn></msub></math></formula> (pointwise method) and CLG ( <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid42" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) on a image pair from a CElegans sequence.</caption>
      </object>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid128" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Frame-based hierarchical motion decomposition and segmentation</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp111528">
          <firstname>Juan Manuel</firstname>
          <lastname>Perez Rua</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
          <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
          <lastname>Bouthemy</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>A number of applications in video analysis rely on a per-frame motion segmentation of the scene as key preprocessing step. Moreover, different settings in video production require extracting segmentation masks of multiple moving objects and object parts in a hierarchical fashion. In order to tackle this problem, we propose to analyze and exploit the compositional structure of scene motion to provide a segmentation which is not purely driven by local image information. Specifically, we leveraged a hierarchical motion-based partition of the scene to capture a mid-level understanding of the dynamic video content. To recover the decomposition tree, we formulated the problem as a per-pixel label selection interleaved with motion models estimation. The labels represent the set of nodes from the initial proposal tree which are selected to explain globally the input correspondence field. We carried out experimental results showing the strengths of this approach in comparison to current video segmentation approaches. Indeed, they demonstrated the superior ability of our method to capture the main moving objects of the scene in the first layer of the tree, and to segment them in moving parts in deeper layers. As such, we believe our segmentation method is closer to the complex needs of video editing than current hierarchical segmentation approaches.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Reference:</b> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid43" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
      <p noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Tomas Crivelli and Patrick Pérez (Technicolor).
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid129" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Trajectory-based discovery of motion hierarchies in video sequences</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp111528">
          <firstname>Juan Manuel</firstname>
          <lastname>Perez Rua</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
          <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
          <lastname>Bouthemy</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>The dynamic content of physical scenes is largely compositional, that is, the movements of the objects and of their parts are hierarchically organized and relate through composition along this hierarchy. This structure also prevails in the apparent 2D motion that a video captures. Visual motion in the scene is roughly organized along a tree, with the dominant motion (typically induced by camera motion) at the root, and motion components adding up along the branches. Accessing this visual motion hierarchy is important to get a better understanding of dynamic scenes and is useful for video manipulation. We proposed to capture it through learned, tree-structured sparse coding of point trajectories. We found that dictionary learning and sparse coding provide appealing tools to disentangle this latent hierarchical structure. More precisely, we introduced a new tree-structured dictionary learning method that allows describing each track with a few basis functions, all but one being inherited from its parent in the structure. The sparse codes thus associated to the tracks capture the desired structure and lend themselves naturally to hierarchical clustering of the collection. We showed through experiments on motion capture data that our model is able to extract moving segments along with their organization. We also obtained competitive results on the task of segmenting objects in real video sequences from trajectories.</p>
      <p spacebefore="2.84544pt" noindent="true"><b>Reference:</b> <ref xlink:href="#serpico-2016-bid44" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
      <p noindent="true"><b>Collaborators:</b> Tomas Crivelli and Patrick Pérez (Technicolor).
</p>
    </subsection>
  </resultats>
  <contrats id="uid130">
    <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid131" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid132" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Contract with Innopsys: Tissue microarrays (TMA) image analysis</bodyTitle>
        <p><b>Participants:</b> Hoai Nam Nguyen, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        <p><b>Collaborators:</b> Vincent Paveau and Cyril Cauchois (Innopys company).</p>
        <p>A three-year contract has been established with Innopsys in 2013 to support Hoai Nam Nguyen's PhD thesis. The objective is to investigate and develop methods and algorithms dedicated to fluorescence images acquired by the scanners and devices designed by the company. In this project, we focus on
i/ localization and segmentation fluorescence tissue microarrays (TMA) cores in very large 2D images;
ii/ de-arraying of digital images and correction of grid deformation adapted to devices;
iii/ correction of scanning artifacts to improve image reconstruction;
iv/ deconvolution, denoising and superresolution of fluorescence TMA images corrupted by Poisson noise.
The algorithms will be integrated into the plateforms and devices designed by Innopsys.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid133" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Contract (CIFRE) with Technicolor: Semantically meaningful motion descriptors for video understanding</bodyTitle>
        <p><b>Participants:</b> Juan Manuel Perez Rua, Patrick Bouthemy.</p>
        <p><b>Collaborators:</b> Tomas Crivelli and Patrick Pérez (Technicolor).</p>
        <p>A three-year contract has been established with Technicolor on January 2015 for a CIFRE grant supporting Juan Manuel Perez Rua's PhD thesis. The purpose is to investigate new methods for extracting meaningful mid-level motion-related descriptors that may help for the semantic discovery of the scene. In 2015, we started with the occlusion detection problem. We have proposed a novel approach where occlusion in the next frame or not is formulated in terms of visual reconstruction.
Our approach outperforms state-of-the-art occlusion detection methods on the challenging MPI Sintel dataset.
In 2016, we have developed two hierarchical motion segmentation methods involving a compositional motion representation. The first one follows a frame-based labeling approach which amounts to the minimization of a global energy function. The second one is trajectory-based and relies on tree-structured learning and sparse coding.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid134" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Contract with OBSYS: microscope set-up control and inverse problems in microscopy</bodyTitle>
        <p><b>Participants:</b> Giovanni Petrazzuoli, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        <p><b>Collaborators:</b> Charles Gudeudry (OBSYS).</p>
        <p>A three-year contract has been established with OBSYS in 2016. The objective is to investigate and develop methods and algorithms dedicated to the control of a microscope set-up and to the analysis of fluorescence images. Fast and robust algorithms will be especially developed to improve image reconstruction of 3D-TIRF microscope images. The algorithms will be integrated into the plateforms and devices designed by OBSYS.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid135" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral grants with industry</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid136" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Fourmentin-Guilbert Foundation: Macromolecule detection in cryo electron tomograms</bodyTitle>
        <p><b>Participants:</b> Emmanuel Moebel, Charles Kervrann.</p>
        <p><b>Collaborator:</b> Damien Larivière (Fourmentin-Guilbert Foundation).</p>
        <p>The Fourmentin-Guilbert Foundation strives for building a virtual E. coli bacteria. Information about the position of macromolecules within the cell is necessary to achieve such a 3D molecularly-detailed model. The Fourmentin-Guilbert Foundation supports cutting-edge <i>in-situ</i> cryo electron tomography combined with image processing at the Max-Planck Institute of Biochemistry to map the spatial distribution of the ribosomes, and obtain structural information on the complexes they form <i>in-situ</i> with cofactors and other ribosomes. The objective of the project is to explore and evaluate novel methods from the field of 3D shape retrieval for identifying, localizing and counting macromolecules (e.g., 70S ribosome) within a tomogram. This project is also supported by “Region Bretagne”.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </contrats>
  <partenariat id="uid137">
    <bodyTitle>Partnerships and Cooperations</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid138" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Regional Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <p><b>ENSAI-CREST:</b> Statistical methods and models for image registration, Vincent Briane PhD thesis is co-funded by Inria and ENSAI-CREST and co-supervised by Myriam Vimond (ENSAI-CREST).</p>
      <p><b>Région Bretagne:</b> Identification, localization and enumeration of ribosomes within a tomogram by combining state-of-the-art denoising methods and object descriptor-based recognition (CATLAS, see Section 8.2.1).</p>
      <p><b>BioGenOuest:</b> Collaboration with S. Prigent (engineer) in charge of the organization of image processing services for Biogenouest bio-imaging facilities.</p>
      <p><b>IGDR:</b> Collaboration with J. Pecreaux, Y. Le Cunff (co-supervision of A.G. Caranfil's PhD thesis).</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid139" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>National Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid140" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>France-BioImaging project</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <firstname>Charles</firstname>
            <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
            <lastname>Bouthemy</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
            <firstname>Thierry</firstname>
            <lastname>Pécot</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="serpico-2014-idp103904">
            <firstname>Emmanuel</firstname>
            <lastname>Moebel</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="serpico-2015-idm5880">
            <firstname>Ancageorgiana</firstname>
            <lastname>Caranfil</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The goal of the project is to build a distributed coordinated French infrastructure for photonic and electronic cellular bioimaging dedicated to innovation, training and technology transfer. High-computing capacities are needed to exhaustively analyse image flows. We address the following problems: i/ exhaustive analysis of bioimaging data sets; ii/ deciphering of key steps of biological mechanisms at organ, tissular, cellular and molecular levels through the systematic use of time-lapse 3D microscopy and image processing methods; iii/ storage and indexing of extracted and associated data and metadata through an intelligent data management system. <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> is co-head of the IPDM (Image Processing and Data Management) node of the FBI network composed of 6 nodes.</p>
        <table rend="inline">
          <tr style="">
            <td style="text-align:left;" halign="left"><b>Funding:</b> Investissement d'Avenir - Infrastructures Nationales en Biologie et Santé ANR (2011-2016).</td>
          </tr>
          <tr style="">
            <td style="text-align:left;" halign="left"><b>Partners:</b> CNRS, Institut Jacques Monod, Institut Pasteur, Institut Curie, ENS Ulm, Ecole Polytechnique, INRA, INSERM.</td>
          </tr>
          <caption/>
        </table>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid141" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ANR DALLISH project (2016-2020): Data Assimilation and Lattice LIght SHeet imaging for endocytosis/exocytosis pathway modeling in the whole cell</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <firstname>Charles</firstname>
            <lastname>Kervrann</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <firstname>Patrick</firstname>
            <lastname>Bouthemy</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="serpico-2014-idp112760">
            <firstname>Vincent</firstname>
            <lastname>Briane</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="serpico-2015-idm5880">
            <firstname>Ancageorgiana</firstname>
            <lastname>Caranfil</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The Lattice Light Sheet Microscopy (LLS-M) represents at present the novel generation of
3D fluorescence microscopes dedicated to single cell analysis, generating extraordinarily high resolved
and sharp, but huge 3D images and videos: one single live cell experiment in one single
condition, imaging two molecular markers of the endocytosis pathway and using cutting-edge LLS-M
can result into up to one Terabyte of data, at the spatial resolution of 100-200
nanometers in 3D. In such a situation, it is found the usual conventional image reconstruction
algorithms and image analysis methods developed for 3D fluorescence microscopy are likely to fail to
process a deluge of voxels generated by LLS-M instruments. The goal of the project is then to develop
new paradigms and computational strategies for image reconstruction and 3D molecule
tracking/motion estimation. Furthermore, establishing correspondences between the image-based
measurements and features (e.g., motion vectors, trajectories), stochastic motion models and the underlying
biological and biophysical information remains a challenging task.</p>
        <p>The impact of the project will be three-fold. First, our new image processing paradigms and improved
algorithms (allowing faster, more resolved and more accurate results) will have direct benefits in
modern bioimaging. Second, the methods and algorithms will apply to decipher molecular mechanisms of
protein transports, here focused on endocytosis/exocytosis. Finally, in a larger perspective, the quantitative description of protein transport will be a prerequisite for understanding the functioning of a cell in
normal and pathological situations, as default in protein transport appeared over the years, as a major
contributory factor to a number of diseases, including cancer, viral infection and neurodegenerative
diseases.</p>
        <table rend="inline">
          <tr style="">
            <td style="text-align:left;" halign="left"><b>Funding:</b> ANR - Agence Nationale de la Recherche</td>
          </tr>
          <tr style="">
            <td style="text-align:left;" halign="left"><b>Partners:</b> Inria (SERPICO, BEAGLE, Fluminance), INRA MaIAGE Unit Jouy-en-Josas, Institut Curie (UMR CNRS 144 &amp; U1143 Inserm UMR 3666) Paris</td>
          </tr>
          <caption/>
        </table>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid142" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>European Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid143" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Major European Organizations with which the Team have followed Collaborations</bodyTitle>
        <p><b>ESFRI Euro-BioImaging initiative</b>:
<span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> participates in the ESFRI Euro-BioImaging project, one
of the four new biomedical science projects in the roadmap of the
European Strategic Forum on Research Infrastructures (ESFRI). The
mission of Euro-BioImaging is to provide access, service and training
to state-of-the-art imaging technologies and foster the cooperation
and networking at the national and European level including
multidisciplinary scientists, industry, regional, national and European
authorities. <span class="smallcap" align="left">serpico</span> also participates to the French counterpart, the
so-called “France-BioImaging” (FBI) network which gathers several
outstanding cellular imaging centers (microscopy, spectroscopy, probe
engineering and signal processing) as described in Section <ref xlink:href="#uid140" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid144" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid145" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Informal International Partners</bodyTitle>
        <p>Collaboration with Max-Planck Institute, Martinsried (Germany), Dr. Julio Ortiz: Detection and segmentation of macromolecules in cryo electron tomography (project in progress with Emmanuel Moebel and Charles Kervrann).</p>
        <p>Collaboration with Aalborg University (Denmark), Prof. Rasmus Waagepetersen : Estimating equations for inhomogeneous determinantal point processes (project in progress with Frédéric Lavancier).</p>
        <p>Collaboration with EPFL (M. Unser's Team, Switzerland). D. Fortun: optical flow computing (project in progress with Charles Kervrann).</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid146" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>
          <ref xlink:href="http://serpico.rennes.inria.fr/doku.php?id=research:cytodi" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">CytoDI Inria Associated-Team</ref>
        </bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid147">
            <p noindent="true">Title: Quantitative Imaging of Cytoskeleton Dynamics in 3D</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid148">
            <p noindent="true">International Partner:</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid149">
                <p noindent="true">University of Texas, SouthWestern Medical Center, Dallas (United States) - Gaudenz Danuser</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
          </li>
          <li id="uid150">
            <p noindent="true">Start year: 2016</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid151">
            <p noindent="true">See also: <ref xlink:href="http://serpico.rennes.inria.fr/doku.php?id=research:cytodi" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>serpico.<allowbreak/>rennes.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>doku.<allowbreak/>php?id=research:cytodi</ref></p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid152">
            <p noindent="true">The main scientific goal of the Associated-Team is the spatiotemporal characterization and comparison of cytoskeleton networks involved in cell migration and observed through live cell imaging in three dimensions (3D). Those networks include the cytoskeleton, i.e., microtubules (MT), intermediate filaments (IF), dynamically resolvable by Bessel Beam Light Sheet fluorescent microscopy. The goal will be achieved through the design of local and global descriptors of the spatial conformation and deformation of the cytoskeleton. Subsequently, general metrics to compare and classify the MT and IF networks will be investigated. This study will be carried out on oncogenically transformed lung cancer epithelial cells.</p>
            <p>The first meeting took place in Dallas in May 2016 as originally scheduled, to discuss and update current research direction and discuss scientific progress.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid153" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Research Visitors</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid154" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits to International Teams</bodyTitle>
        <p>Visit of 3 months of Juan Manuel Perez Rua in the Philip Torr's team (University of Oxford, UK).</p>
        <p noindent="true">Visit of 1 one week of Vincent Briane to the ESGI (European Study Group in Industry) in Dublin (Ireland, July 2016).</p>
        <p>Visit of 1 one week of Vincent Briane to the University of Limerick (K. Burke's team) (Ireland, November 2016).</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </partenariat>
  <diffusion id="uid155">
    <bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid156" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Promoting Scientific Activities</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid157" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Organisation</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid158" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Organizing Committees</bodyTitle>
          <p>Frédéric Lavancier and Charles Kervrann were head of the organizing committee of the international workshop “Spatial Statistics and Image Analysis in Biology” (SSIAB'16), Inria Rennes, May 2016.</p>
          <p>Frédéric Lavancier was head of the workshop “Spatio-Temporal Models and Statistics”, IRMAR University of Rennes 1, LMJL University of Nantes, ENSAI, University of Rennes 2, INRA Rennes, Inria Rennes, April 2016.</p>
          <p>Patrick Bouthemy and Thierry Pécot were respectively main organizer and co-organizer of the BioImage Computing workshop in conjunction with ECCV'2016, Amsterdam, October 2016.</p>
          <p>Patrick Bouthemy and Charles Kervrann were respectively main organizer and co-organizer of the mini-symposium “Image analysis advances in dynamic microscopy and live cell imaging” in SIAM Conference on Imaging Sciences, Albuquerque, New-Mexico, USA, May 2016.</p>
          <p>Charles Kervrann was member of the organization committee of the Microscopy school MiFoBio'2016, Seignosse, October 2016.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid159" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Selection</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid160" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Conference Program Committees</bodyTitle>
          <p>Charles Kervrann: member of the scientific committee of <span class="smallcap" align="left">rfia</span>'2016 (Clermont-Ferrand), Associated Editor for the conference <span class="smallcap" align="left">isbi</span>'2017, member of the scientific committee of the “Image the Cell 2017” conference (Rennes), member of the scientific committee “Journées d'Imagerie Optique Non-Conventionnelle” (<span class="smallcap" align="left">jionc</span>'2016 and <span class="smallcap" align="left">jionc</span>'2017).</p>
          <p>Patrick Bouthemy: Associate Editor for the conference <span class="smallcap" align="left">isbi</span>'2016 and <span class="smallcap" align="left">isbi</span>'2017, Area Chair of <span class="smallcap" align="left">icip</span>'2016, member of the program committee of <span class="smallcap" align="left">rfia</span>'2016.</p>
          <p>Thierry Pécot: member of the program committee of <span class="smallcap" align="left">bioimaging</span>'2016.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid161" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Reviewer</bodyTitle>
          <p>Charles Kervrann: reviewer for <span class="smallcap" align="left">icip</span>'2016, <span class="smallcap" align="left">icassp</span>'2016, <span class="smallcap" align="left">isbi</span>'2016, <span class="smallcap" align="left">icassp</span>'2017, <span class="smallcap" align="left">icip</span>'2017.</p>
          <p>Patrick Bouthemy: reviewer for <span class="smallcap" align="left">icip</span>'2016, <span class="smallcap" align="left">isbi</span>'2016.</p>
          <p>Thierry Pécot: reviewer for <span class="smallcap" align="left">isbi</span>'2016, <span class="smallcap" align="left">bioimaging</span>'2016.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid162" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Journal</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid163" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Editorial Boards</bodyTitle>
          <p>Charles Kervrann is Guest Editor of the special issue entitled “Advanced Signal Processing in Microscopy and Cell Imaging” of the IEEE Selected Topics in Signal Processing Journal, February 2016.</p>
          <p>Charles Kervrann is Associate Editor of the IEEE Signal Processing Letters journal (since January 2015).</p>
          <p>Patrick Bouthemy is co-editor in chief of the open access journal Frontiers in ICT, specialty Computer Image Analysis.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid164" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Reviewer - Reviewing Activities</bodyTitle>
          <p>Charles Kervrann: BMC Bioinformatics, IEEE Transactions on Computational Imaging, SIAM J. on Imaging Sciences, Methods, expert for the project evaluation in the framework of FONDECYT Science Council (Chile).</p>
          <p>Patrick Bouthemy: IEEE Transactions on Image Processing, Mathematical Problems in Engineering, IEEE Signal Processing Letters, IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters, Applied Soft Computing Journal, Computational Intelligence and Neuroscience.</p>
          <p>Frédéric Lavancier: Spatial Statistics, R Journal</p>
          <p>Thierry Pécot: Bioinformatics, IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid165" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Invited Talks</bodyTitle>
        <p>Charles Kervrann:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid166">
            <p noindent="true">Invited talk at the FBI seminar (Paris centre), Computational methods for diffusion, motion and
molecular interaction estimation, Pont l'Eveque, February 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid167">
            <p noindent="true">Invited talk at the Forum Mathématique Diderot, Computational analysis of intracellular membrane dynamics: from live cell images to biophysical model, Paris, March 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid168">
            <p noindent="true">Seminar UTSW, Danuser's lab, Computational analysis of intracellular membrane dynamics: from live cell images to biophysical model, Dallas, TX, USA, May 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid169">
            <p noindent="true">Invited talk at SIAM Conference on Imaging Sciences, PEWA: Patch-based Exponentially Weighted Aggregation for image denoising, Albuquerque, New-Mexico, USA, May 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Patrick Bouthemy</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid170">
            <p noindent="true">Invited talk at SIAM Conference on Imaging Sciences, A scale-adaptive method for retracing and registering in correlative light-electron microscopy, Albuquerque, New-Mexico, USA, May 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Vincent Briane:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid171">
            <p noindent="true">Invited talk at SSIAB'2016 workshop, An adaptive statistical test to detect non Brownian diffusion from particle trajectories, Inria Rennes, May 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Thierry Pécot:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid172">
            <p noindent="true">Invited talk at SSIAB'2016 workshop, A non-parametric procedure for co-localization studies in fluorescence microscopy, Inria Rennes, May 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid173">
            <p noindent="true">Talk and practical course at Microscopy school MiFoBio'2016, mage processing methods for the temporal analysis of moving particles, Seignosse, October 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid174">
            <p noindent="true">Seminar IGDR, QuantEv: Quantifying the spatial distribution of intracellular events, Rennes, November 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Frédéric Lavancier:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid175">
            <p noindent="true">Seminar of Statistics and Probability in Lille 1, Determinantal point process models and statistical inference, Lille, March 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid176">
            <p noindent="true">Seminar in Statistics of University Toulouse 1, A general procedure to combine estimators, Toulouse, June 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid177">
            <p noindent="true">Invited talk at “Journées MAS”, Determinantal point process models and statistical inference, Grenoble, August 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid178" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Expertise</bodyTitle>
        <p>Charles Kervrann:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid179">
            <p noindent="true">Member of the IEEE BISP “Biomedical Image and Signal Processing” committee.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid180">
            <p noindent="true">Member of executive board of the GdR MIV (2588 - Microscopie Fonctionnelle du Vivant) CNRS.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid181">
            <p noindent="true">Member of the scientific committee of the Interdisciplinary MiFoBio School CNRS (<ref xlink:href="http://www.mifobio.fr" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>mifobio.<allowbreak/>fr</ref>).</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Patrick Bouthemy:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid182">
            <p noindent="true">Member of the board of AFRIF (Association Française pour la Reconnaissance et l'Interprétation des Formes).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid183">
            <p noindent="true">Member of the Research Committee of Telecom Bretagne.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Frédéric Lavancier:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid184">
            <p noindent="true">Elected member of CNU section 26.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid185">
            <p noindent="true">Expert for the project evaluation in the framework of FNRS (Fonds de la Recherche Scientifique), Belgium.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid186" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Research Administration</bodyTitle>
        <p>Charles Kervrann:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid187">
            <p noindent="true">Member of the executive board of the project committee of the Inria Rennes - Bretagne Atlantique centre.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid188">
            <p noindent="true">Member of the Scientific Council of the INRA Rennes Research Centre.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid189">
            <p noindent="true">Co-head of the “BioImage Informatics” node (ANR France-BioImaging project, National Infrastructure en Biologie et Santé).</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Patrick Bouthemy:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid190">
            <p noindent="true">Head of Excellence Lab CominLabs since April 2014.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid191">
            <p noindent="true">Deputy member of the board of directors and member of the Selection and Validation Committee of the Images &amp; Réseaux competitivity cluster.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid192">
            <p noindent="true">Deputy member of the board of directors of IRT (Technological Research Institute) b&lt;&gt;com.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid193" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Teaching - Supervision - Juries</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid194" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Teaching</bodyTitle>
        <p>Charles Kervrann:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid195">
            <p noindent="true">Engineer Degree: Genomics and Informatics, 4.5 hours, Ecole Nationale Supérieure des Mines de Paris.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid196">
            <p noindent="true">Master: From Bioimage Processing to BioImage Informatics, 5 hours, coordinator of the module (30 hours), Master 2 Research IRIV, Telecom-Physique Strasbourg and University of Strasbourg.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid197">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Geometric Modeling for Shapes and Images, 6 hours, Master 2 Research SISEA, University of Rennes 1.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid198">
            <p noindent="true">Engineer Degree and Master 2 Statistics and Mathematics: Statistical Models and Image Analysis, 37 hours + 15 hours (TP, Emmanuel Moebel), 3rd year, Ecole Nationale de la Statistique et de l'Analyse de l'Information (ENSAI), Rennes.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Patrick Bouthemy:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid199">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Analysis of Image Sequences, 18 hours, Master 2 Research SISEA, ISTIC &amp; University of Rennes 1.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid200">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Video Indexing, 9 hours, Master 2 Research Computer Science, ISTIC &amp; University of Rennes 1.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid201">
            <p noindent="true">Engineer Degree and Master 2 Research IRIV: Motion Analysis, 12 hours, Telecom-Physique Strasbourg &amp; University of Strasbourg.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
        <p>Frédéric Lavancier:</p>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid202">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Linear Models, 36 hours, Master 2 Mathematics &amp; Engineering, option Statistics, University of Nantes.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid203">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Time Series, 36 hours, Master 2 Mathematics &amp; Engineering, option Statistics, University of Nantes.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid204" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Supervision</bodyTitle>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Arnaud Poinas, Inference for inhomogeneous determinantal point processes, started in September 2016, supervised by Bernard Delyon and Frédéric Lavancier</p>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Hoai Nam Nguyen, Methods and algorithms for tissue microarrays image analysis, started in October 2013, supervised by Charles Kervrann and Vincent Paveau (Innopsys).</p>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Vincent Briane, Statistical methods and models for motion analysis in microscopy, started in October 2014, supervised by Charles Kervrann and Myriam Vimond (ENSAI-CREST).</p>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Bertha Mayela Toledo Acosta, Methods and algorithms for 3D image registration and correlative microscopy, started in October 2014, supervised by Patrick Bouthemy and Charles Kervrann.</p>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Emmanuel Moebel, New strategies for the nonambiguous identification and enumeration of
macromolecules in cryo electron tomograms, started in November 2015, supervised by Charles Kervrann.</p>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Juan Manuel Perez Rua, Semantically meaningful motion descriptors for video understanding, started in January 2015, supervised by Patrick Bouthemy in collaboration with Tomas Crivelli and Patrick Pérez (Technicolor).</p>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Ancageorgiana Caranfil, Data assimilation methods for cell division mechanisms and molecule trafficking analysis, started in December 2016, supervised by Charles Kervrann and Yann Le Cunff.</p>
        <p><i>PhD in progress:</i> Sandeep Manandhar, Optical flow methods for 3D fluoresence imaging, started in October 2016, supervised by Patrick Bouthemy and Charles Kervrann.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid205" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Juries</bodyTitle>
        <p><i>Referee of PhD thesis:</i> G. Michelin (University of Côte d'Azur, supervised by G. Malandain) [P. Bouthemy], L. Azzari (Tampere University of Technology, Finland, supervised by A. Foi) [C. Kervrann], H. Robjani (University of Strasbourg, supervised by C. Ronse) [C. Kervrann].</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </diffusion>
  <biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" numero="10" titre="Bibliography">
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid25" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:basset:hal-01248290">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/TIP.2015.2450996"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01248290"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Adaptive spot detection with optimal scale selection in fluorescence microscopy images</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp107776">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Basset</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Image Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">24</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">11</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">16</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01248290" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01248290</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid9" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:boulanger:2010:inria-00541072:1">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1371/journal.pone.0013190"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A patch-based method for repetitive and transient event detection in fluorescence imaging</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alexandre</foreName>
            <surname>Gidon</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">5</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">10</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>Oct</month>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid6" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:Boulanger2007">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Space-time adaptation for patch based image sequence restoration</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">29</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2007</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1096–1102</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid23" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:Boulanger2009">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A simulation and estimation framework for intracellular dynamics and trafficking in video-microscopy and fluorescence imagery</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Medical Image Analysis</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">13</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">132–142</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid8" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:boulanger:2010:inria-00541082:1">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/TMI.2009.2033991"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Patch-based nonlocal functional for denoising fluorescence microscopy image sequences</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Peter</foreName>
            <surname>Elbau</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-Baptiste</foreName>
            <surname>Sibarita</surname>
            <initial>J.-B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">29</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>Feb</month>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">442-453</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid62" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:crivelli:hal-00931667">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1137/120872048"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00931667"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Motion Textures: Modeling, Classification, and Segmentation Using Mixed-State</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tomas</foreName>
            <surname>Crivelli</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bruno</foreName>
            <surname>Cernuschi-Frias</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jian-Feng</foreName>
            <surname>Yao</surname>
            <initial>J.-F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Imaging Sciences</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2484-2520</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00931667" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00931667</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid61" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:gidon:hal-00782005">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1111/j.1600-0854.2012.01354.x"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00782005"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Rab11A/myosin Vb/Rab11-FIP2 complex frames two late recycling steps of langerin from the ERC to the plasma membrane</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alexandre</foreName>
            <surname>Gidon</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sabine</foreName>
            <surname>Bardin</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bertrand</foreName>
            <surname>Cinquin</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Waharte</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laurent</foreName>
            <surname>Héliot</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Henri</foreName>
            <surname>De La Salle</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Daniel</foreName>
            <surname>Hanau</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bruno</foreName>
            <surname>Goud</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Traffic</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">13</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">815-833</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00782005" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00782005</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid5" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:Kervrann2006">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Optimal spatial adaptation for patch-based image denoising</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Image Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">15</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">10</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2006</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2866–2878</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid7" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:Kervrann2008">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Local adaptivity to variable smoothness for exemplar-based image denoising and representation</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">International Journal of Computer Vision</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">79</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">45–69</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid32" type="inproceedings" rend="refer" n="refercite:kervrann:hal-01103358">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01103358"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">PEWA: Patch-based Exponentially Weighted Aggregation for image denoising</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">NIPS - Neural Information Processing Systems</title>
        <loc>Montreal, Canada</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Neural Information Processing Systems Foundation</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2014</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01103358" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01103358</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid24" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:pecot:hal-01103126">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/TIP.2014.2380178"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01103126"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Background Fluorescence Estimation and Vesicle Segmentation in Live Cell Imaging with Conditional Random Fields</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
            <foreName>Thierry</foreName>
            <surname>Pécot</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anatole</foreName>
            <surname>Chessel</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sabine</foreName>
            <surname>Bardin</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Image Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">24</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">14</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01103126" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01103126</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid4" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:carlton:2010:inria-00540978:1">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1073/pnas.1004037107"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Fast live simultaneous multiwavelength four-dimensional optical microscopy</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.M.</foreName>
            <surname>Carlton</surname>
            <initial>P.M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-Baptiste</foreName>
            <surname>Sibarita</surname>
            <initial>J.-B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Gordon-Messer</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.E.</foreName>
            <surname>Haber</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Haase</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Shao</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Winoto</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Matsuda</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.</foreName>
            <surname>Kner</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Usawa</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Y.</foreName>
            <surname>Strukov</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.G.L.</foreName>
            <surname>Gustafsson</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Z.</foreName>
            <surname>Kam</surname>
            <initial>Z.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>D.</foreName>
            <surname>Agard</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Sedat</surname>
            <initial>J.W.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">107</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">37</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>Sep</month>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">16016-16022</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid38" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:biscio:hal-01179831">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01179831"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Brillinger mixing of determinantal point processes and statistical applications</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christophe Ange Napoléon</foreName>
            <surname>Biscio</surname>
            <initial>C. A. N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00518">
        <idno type="issn">1935-7524</idno>
        <title level="j">Electronic journal of statistics </title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">582-607</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01179831" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01179831</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid39" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:biscio:hal-01215582">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01215582"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Contrast estimation for parametric stationary determinantal point processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christophe Ange Napoléon</foreName>
            <surname>Biscio</surname>
            <initial>C. A. N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01748">
        <idno type="issn">0303-6898</idno>
        <title level="j">Scandinavian Journal of Statistics</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01215582" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01215582</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid37" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:biscio:hal-01003155">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01003155"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Quantifying repulsiveness of determinantal point processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christophe Ange Napoléon</foreName>
            <surname>Biscio</surname>
            <initial>C. A. N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00233">
        <idno type="issn">1350-7265</idno>
        <title level="j">Bernoulli</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">22</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2001-2028</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01003155" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01003155</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid36" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:coeurjolly:hal-01092225">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01092225"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Parametric estimation of pairwise Gibbs point processes with infinite range interaction</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-François</foreName>
            <surname>Coeurjolly</surname>
            <initial>J.-F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00233">
        <idno type="issn">1350-7265</idno>
        <title level="j">Bernoulli</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01092225" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01092225</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid35" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:dereudre:hal-01144877">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01144877"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Consistency of likelihood estimation for Gibbs point processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>David</foreName>
            <surname>Dereudre</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00146">
        <idno type="issn">0090-5364</idno>
        <title level="j">The Annals of Statistics</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01144877" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01144877</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid50" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:fortun:hal-01408771">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s10851-016-0664-6"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01408771"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Variational Aggregation Framework for Patch-Based Optical Flow Estimation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Fortun</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01196">
        <idno type="issn">0924-9907</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Imaging and Vision</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">56</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">280 - 299</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01408771" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01408771</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid49" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:fortun:hal-01001758">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.cviu.2015.11.020"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01001758"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Aggregation of local parametric candidates with exemplar-based occlusion handling for optical flow</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Fortun</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00409">
        <idno type="issn">1077-3142</idno>
        <title level="j">Computer Vision and Image Understanding</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">17</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01001758" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01001758</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid60" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:jain:hal-01401833">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.3389/fict.2015.00028"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401833"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Improved Motion Description for Action Classification </title>
        <author>
          <persName key="linkmedia-2014-idp116480">
            <foreName>Mihir</foreName>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="linkmedia-2014-idp85792">
            <foreName>Hervé</foreName>
            <surname>Jégou</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid03130">
        <idno type="issn">2297-198X</idno>
        <title level="j">Frontiers in information and communication technologies</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401833" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401833</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid59" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:kervrann:hal-01251394">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/JSTSP.2015.2511299"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01251394"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Introduction to the issue on Advanced Signal Processing in Microscopy and Cell Imaging</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Scott T.</foreName>
            <surname>Acton</surname>
            <initial>S. T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Olivo-Marin</surname>
            <initial>J.-C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Carlos Oscar S.</foreName>
            <surname>Sorzano</surname>
            <initial>C. O. S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael</foreName>
            <surname>Unser</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00690">
        <idno type="issn">1932-4553</idno>
        <title level="j">IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Signal Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">3-5</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01251394" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01251394</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid56" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:kervrann:hal-01246375">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01246375"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Guided Tour of Selected Image Processing and Analysis Methods for Fluorescence and Electron Microscopy</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Carlos Oscar S.</foreName>
            <surname>Sorzano</surname>
            <initial>C. O. S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Scott T.</foreName>
            <surname>Acton</surname>
            <initial>S. T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Olivo-Marin</surname>
            <initial>J.-C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael</foreName>
            <surname>Unser</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00690">
        <idno type="issn">1932-4553</idno>
        <title level="j">IEEE Selected Topics in Signal Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">6-30</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01246375" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01246375</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid40" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:lavancier:hal-01155646">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01155646"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Modelling aggregation on the large scale and regularity on the small scale in spatial point pattern datasets</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jesper</foreName>
            <surname>Møller</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01748">
        <idno type="issn">0303-6898</idno>
        <title level="j">Scandinavian Journal of Statistics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">43</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">587-609</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01155646" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01155646</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid33" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:lavancier:hal-00936024">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00936024"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A general procedure to combine estimators</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Paul</foreName>
            <surname>Rochet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00385">
        <idno type="issn">0167-9473</idno>
        <title level="j">Computational Statistics and Data Analysis</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">94</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">175-192</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00936024" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00936024</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid58" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:pecot:hal-01417147">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01417147"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Counting-based particle flux estimation for traffic analysis in live cell imaging</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
            <foreName>Thierry</foreName>
            <surname>Pécot</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00690">
        <idno type="issn">1932-4553</idno>
        <title level="j">IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Signal Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">10</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">203-216</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01417147" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01417147</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid51" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:basset:hal-01416868">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416868"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Modélisation et estimation de la diffusion de protéines à l’exocytose dans des séquences d’images de microscopie TIRF</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp107776">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Basset</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Waharte</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="no" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Reconnaissance des Formes et l'Intelligence Artificielle (RFIA'16)</title>
        <loc>Clermont-Ferrand, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Association Française de Reconnaissance et d'Interprétation des Formes (AFRIF), Association Française d'Intelligence Artificielle (AFIA)</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1-8</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416868" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416868</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid54223">
          <title>Congrès Francophone de Reconnaissance des Formes et Intelligence Artificielle</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">RFIA</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid57" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bouthemy:hal-01400895">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/ICIP.2016.7533059"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01400895"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Robust selection of parametric motion models in image sequences</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp110280">
            <foreName>Bertha Mayela</foreName>
            <surname>Toledo Acosta</surname>
            <initial>B. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bernard</foreName>
            <surname>Delyon</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">2016 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)</title>
        <loc>Phoenix, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">3743 - 3747</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01400895" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01400895</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid83858">
          <title>IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</title>
          <num>23</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICIP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid53" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:briane:hal-01416862">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416862"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Test statistique pour détecter les diffusions non browniennes</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp112760">
            <foreName>Vincent</foreName>
            <surname>Briane</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Myriam</foreName>
            <surname>Vimond</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="no" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">48e Journées de Statistique</title>
        <loc>Montpellier, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">SFdS</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1-6</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416862" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416862</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid348420">
          <title>Journées de Statistique</title>
          <num>48</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">JDS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid54" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:briane:hal-01416855">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416855"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">An adaptive statistical test to detect non Brownian diffusion from particle trajectories</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp112760">
            <foreName>Vincent</foreName>
            <surname>Briane</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Myriam</foreName>
            <surname>Vimond</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">ISBI 2016 - IEEE Symposium on Biomedical Imaging</title>
        <loc>Prague, Czech Republic</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">IEEE</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1-4</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416855" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416855</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid88475">
          <title>IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging : From Nano to Macro</title>
          <num>13</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISBI</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid55" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:briane:hal-01416812">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416812"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">An adaptive statistical test to detect non Brownian diffusion from particle trajectories</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp112760">
            <foreName>Vincent</foreName>
            <surname>Briane</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Myriam</foreName>
            <surname>Vimond</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="yes" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">Workshop SSIAB - Spatial Statistics and Image Analysis in Biology</title>
        <loc>Rennes, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416812" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416812</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625523">
          <title>Workshop on Spatial Statistics and Image Analysis in Biology</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SSIAB</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid52" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:kervrann:hal-01416847">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416847"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">PEWA: Patch-Based Exponentially Weighted Aggregation for Image Denoising</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="yes" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">SIAM Imaging Science</title>
        <loc>Albuquerque, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">SIAM</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416847" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416847</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid47911">
          <title>Conference on Imaging Sciences</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SIAM IS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid46" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:moebel:hal-01416801">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416801"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Denoising and compensation of the missing wedge in cryo electron tomography</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp103904">
            <foreName>Emmanuel</foreName>
            <surname>Moebel</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">16th European Microscopy Congress</title>
        <loc>Lyon, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">European Microscopy Society</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416801" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416801</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625522">
          <title>European Microscopy Congress</title>
          <num>16</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">EMC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid47" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:pecot:hal-01416844">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416844"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A non-parametric procedure for co-localization studies in fluorescence microscopy</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
            <foreName>Thierry</foreName>
            <surname>Pécot</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="yes" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">Workshop SSIAB - Spatial Statistics and Image Analysis in Biology</title>
        <loc>Rennes, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416844" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416844</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625523">
          <title>Workshop on Spatial Statistics and Image Analysis in Biology</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SSIAB</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid45" subtype="nonparu-n" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:perezrua:hal-01307703">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01307703"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Determining occlusions from space and time image reconstructions</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Juan-Manuel</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez-Rúa</surname>
            <initial>J.-M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tomas</foreName>
            <surname>Crivelli</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">2016 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)</title>
        <loc>Las Vegas, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01307703" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01307703</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid82398">
          <title>IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CVPR</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">Peer-reviewed paper accepted for presentation at the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition 2016, in Las Vegas, USA</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid44" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:perezrua:hal-01358454">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01358454"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Discovering motion hierarchies via tree-structured coding of trajectories</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Juan-Manuel</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez-Rúa</surname>
            <initial>J.-M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tomas</foreName>
            <surname>Crivelli</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Proceedings of the British Machine Vision Conference 2016</title>
        <loc>York, United Kingdom</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">BMVA</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01358454" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01358454</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid38519">
          <title>British Machine Vision Conference</title>
          <num>27</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">BMVC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid43" subtype="nonparu-n" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:perezrua:hal-01314095">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01314095"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Hierarchical Motion Decomposition for Dynamic Scene Parsing </title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Juan-Manuel</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez-Rúa</surname>
            <initial>J.-M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tomas</foreName>
            <surname>Crivelli</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">2016 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)</title>
        <loc>Phoenix, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">IEEE</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01314095" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01314095</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid83858">
          <title>IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</title>
          <num>23</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICIP</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">Peer-reviewed paper accepted for presentation at the IEEE International Conference on Image Processing 2016</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid41" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:toledoacosta:hal-01400854">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/ISBI.2016.7493258"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01400854"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Common Image Representation And A Patch-Based Search For Correlative Light-Electron-Microscopy (Clem) Registration</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp110280">
            <foreName>Bertha Mayela</foreName>
            <surname>Toledo Acosta</surname>
            <initial>B. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">2016 IEEE 13th International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging (ISBI)</title>
        <loc>Prague, Czech Republic</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">257- 260</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01400854" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01400854</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid88475">
          <title>IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging : From Nano to Macro</title>
          <num>13</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISBI</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid48" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:toledoacosta:hal-01416850">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01416850"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A scale-adaptive method for retracing and registering in correlative light-electron microscopy</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp110280">
            <foreName>Bertha Mayela</foreName>
            <surname>Toledo Acosta</surname>
            <initial>B. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="no" x-invited-conference="yes" x-editorial-board="no">
        <title level="m">SIAM Imaging Science</title>
        <loc>Albuquerque, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">SIAM</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01416850" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01416850</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid47911">
          <title>Conference on Imaging Sciences</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SIAM IS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid34" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:Lavancier:hal-01341125">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01341125"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">A tutorial on estimator averaging in Spatial Statistics models</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp102320">
            <foreName>Frédéric</foreName>
            <surname>Lavancier</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Paul</foreName>
            <surname>Rochet</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01341125" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01341125</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid2" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Axelrod2004">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Total Internal Reflection Fluorescent Microscopy in cell biology</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>D.</foreName>
            <surname>Axelrod</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Traffic</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2004</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">4658–4668</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid0" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Betzig2006">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Imaging intracelluar fluorescent proteins at nanometer resolution</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>E.</foreName>
            <surname>Betzig</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>G.H.</foreName>
            <surname>Patterson</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Sougrat</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>O.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Lindwasser</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Olenych</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.S.</foreName>
            <surname>Bonifacino</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Davidson</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>H.F.</foreName>
            <surname>Hess</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">313</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2006</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1642–1645</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid42" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Bruhn2005">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Lucas/Kanade meets Horn/jaqaSchunck: combining local and global optic flow methods</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andrés</foreName>
            <surname>Bruhn</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Joachim</foreName>
            <surname>Weickert</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Schnörr</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">International Journal of Computer Vision</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">61</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2005</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">211–231</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid31" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Buades2005">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A review of image denoising algorithms, with a new one</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Buades</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Coll</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.-M.</foreName>
            <surname>Morel</surname>
            <initial>J.-M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">SIAM J. Multiscale Modeling &amp; Simulation</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2005</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">490–530</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid19" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:chessel:2010:inria-00541102:1">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1109/ISBI.2010.5490230"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A detection-based framework for the analysis of recycling in TIRF microscopy</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anatole</foreName>
            <surname>Chessel</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Cinquin</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sabine</foreName>
            <surname>Bardin</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Boulanger</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes">
        <title level="m">IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging: From Nano to Macro (ISBI 2010)</title>
        <loc>Pays-Bas Rotterdam</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">IEEE Signal Processing Society</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>Apr</month>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1281-1284</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid27" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:Chessel09">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Computational geometry-based scale-space and modal image decomposition: application to light video-microscopy imaging</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anatole</foreName>
            <surname>Chessel</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Cinquin</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sabine</foreName>
            <surname>Bardin</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Conf. on Scale Space and Variational Methods (SSVM'09)</title>
        <loc>Voss, Norway</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">770–781</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid14" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Corpetti2002">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Dense estimation fluid flows</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T.</foreName>
            <surname>Corpetti</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="fluminance-2014-idm14192">
            <foreName>E.</foreName>
            <surname>Mémin</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">24</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2002</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">365–380</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid30" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Crivelli2011">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Simultaneous motion detection and background reconstruction with a conditional mixed-state Markov random field</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tomas</foreName>
            <surname>Crivelli</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bruno</foreName>
            <surname>Cernuschi-Frias</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.-F.</foreName>
            <surname>Yao</surname>
            <initial>J.-F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">International Journal of Computer Vision</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">94</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">295–316</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid16" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Genovesio2006">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Multiple particle tracking in 3D+t microscopy: method and application to the tracking of endocytosed quantum dots</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Genovesio</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T.</foreName>
            <surname>Liedl</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>V.</foreName>
            <surname>Emiliani</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>W.J.</foreName>
            <surname>Parak</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>Coppey-Moisan</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Olivo-Marin</surname>
            <initial>J.-C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Trans. Image Processing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">15</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">5</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2006</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1062–1070</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid1" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Gustafsson2008">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">3D resolution doubling in wide-filed fluorescence microscopy by structured illumination</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.G.L.</foreName>
            <surname>Gustafsson</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Shao</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.M.</foreName>
            <surname>Carlton</surname>
            <initial>P.M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>R.C.J.</foreName>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>I.N.</foreName>
            <surname>Golubovskaya</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>W.Z.</foreName>
            <surname>Cande</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>D.</foreName>
            <surname>Agard</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Sedat</surname>
            <initial>J.W.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Biophysical J.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">94</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">4957–4970</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid15" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Haussecker2001">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Computing optical flow with physical models of brightness variation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>H.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Haussecker</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>D.J.</foreName>
            <surname>Fleet</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">23</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2001</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">661–673</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid10" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Klar2000">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Fluorescence microscopy with diffraction resolution barrier broken by stimulated emission</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T.A.</foreName>
            <surname>Klar</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Jakobs</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>Dyba</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Egner</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Hell</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">97</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2000</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">8206–8210</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid20" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Lavelle2008">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">From molecules to organisms: towards multiscale integrated model of biological systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>C.</foreName>
            <surname>Lavelle</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="beagle-2014-idp66048">
            <foreName>H.</foreName>
            <surname>Berry</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="beagle-2014-idm26144">
            <foreName>G.</foreName>
            <surname>Beslon</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Ginelli</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.L.</foreName>
            <surname>Giavitto</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Z.</foreName>
            <surname>Kapoula</surname>
            <initial>Z.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Le Bivic</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>N.</foreName>
            <surname>Peyrieras</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>O.</foreName>
            <surname>Radulescu</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Six</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>V.</foreName>
            <surname>Thomas-Vaslin</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.</foreName>
            <surname>Bourgine</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Theoretical Biology Insights</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">13–22</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid21" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Nedelec2002">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Computer simulations reveal motor properties generating stable antiparallel microtubule interactions</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Nédélec</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">The Journal of Cell Biology</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">158</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2002</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1005–1015</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid29" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:Ozere13">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Robust parametric stabilization of moving cells with intensity correction in light microscopy image sequences</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Ozere</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp100880">
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Bouthemy</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="lagadic-2014-idp72528">
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Spindler</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp115248">
            <foreName>Perrine</foreName>
            <surname>Paul-Gilloteaux</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">10th International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging (ISBI)</title>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">IEEE</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">468–471</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid26" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:Pecot08">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Patch-based Markov models for event detection in fluorescence bioimaging</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp105192">
            <foreName>Thierry</foreName>
            <surname>Pécot</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sabine</foreName>
            <surname>Bardin</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Goud</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean</foreName>
            <surname>Salamero</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Int. Conf. on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention (MICCAI'08)</title>
        <loc>New York City, USA</loc>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">95–103</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid11" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Perez2004">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Data fusion for visual tracking with particles</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Pérez</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Vermaak</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Blake</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Proc. IEEE</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">92</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2004</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">495–513</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid28" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:pinot:hal-inserm-00717415">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1073/pnas.1121583109"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="inserm-00717415"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Confinement induces actin flow in a meiotic cytoplasm</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>Pinot</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>V.</foreName>
            <surname>Steiner</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.</foreName>
            <surname>Dehapiot</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>B.-K.</foreName>
            <surname>Yoo</surname>
            <initial>B.-K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>F.</foreName>
            <surname>Chesnel</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>L.</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchoin</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="serpico-2014-idp99400">
            <foreName>Charles</foreName>
            <surname>Kervrann</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Z.</foreName>
            <surname>Gueroui</surname>
            <initial>Z.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="j">Proceedings National Academy of Sciences USA</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">109</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">29</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">11705–11710</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/inserm-00717415" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>inserm-00717415</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid13" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Sbalzarini2005">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Feature point tracking and trajectory analysis for video Imaging in cell biology</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>I.F.</foreName>
            <surname>Sbalzarini</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.</foreName>
            <surname>Koumoutsakos</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">J. Structural Biology</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">151</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2005</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">182–195</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid18" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Smal2010">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Quantitative comparison of spot detection methods in fluorescence microscopy</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>I.</foreName>
            <surname>Smal</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.</foreName>
            <surname>Loog</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>W.</foreName>
            <surname>Niessen</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Erik</foreName>
            <surname>Meijering</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Trans. Medical Imaging</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">29</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">282–301</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid12" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Smal2008">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Multiple object tracking in molecular bioimaging by Rao-Blackwellized marginal particle filtering,</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>I.</foreName>
            <surname>Smal</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Erik</foreName>
            <surname>Meijering</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>K.</foreName>
            <surname>Draegestein</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>N.</foreName>
            <surname>Galjart</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>I.</foreName>
            <surname>Grigoriev</surname>
            <initial>I.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Akhmanova</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.E.</foreName>
            <surname>van Royen</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.B.</foreName>
            <surname>Houtsmuller</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>W.</foreName>
            <surname>Niessen</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Medical Image Analysis</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">764–777</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid17" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Thomann2002">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Automatic fluorescent tag detection in 3D with super-resolution: application to the analysis of chromosome movement</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>D.</foreName>
            <surname>Thomann</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>D.R.</foreName>
            <surname>Rines</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.K.</foreName>
            <surname>Sorger</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>G.</foreName>
            <surname>Danuser</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">J. Microscopy</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">298</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">Part 1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2002</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">49–64</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid22" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Vardi1996">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Network tomography: estimating source-destination traffic intensities from link data</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Y.</foreName>
            <surname>Vardi</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">J. American Statistical Association</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">91</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1996</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">365–377</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="serpico-2016-bid3" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:Walter2010">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Visualization of image data from cells to organisms</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>T.</foreName>
            <surname>Walter</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>D.W.</foreName>
            <surname>Shattuck</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Baldock</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.E.</foreName>
            <surname>Bastin</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.E.</foreName>
            <surname>Carpenter</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Duce</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>Ellenberg</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Fraser</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>N.</foreName>
            <surname>Hamilton</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>S.</foreName>
            <surname>Pieper</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>M.A.</foreName>
            <surname>Ragan</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.E.</foreName>
            <surname>Schneider</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>P.</foreName>
            <surname>Tomancak</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.K.</foreName>
            <surname>Heriche</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Nature Methods</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">7</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3 (Suppl)</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">S26–41</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
  </biblio>
</raweb>
