<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2016">
  <identification id="tosca" isproject="true">
    <shortname>TOSCA</shortname>
    <projectName>TO Simulate and CAlibrate stochastic models</projectName>
    <theme-de-recherche>Stochastic approaches</theme-de-recherche>
    <domaine-de-recherche>Applied Mathematics, Computation and Simulation</domaine-de-recherche>
    <urlTeam>http://team.inria.fr/tosca/</urlTeam>
    <structure_exterieure type="Labs">
      <libelle>Institut Elie Cartan de Lorraine (IECL)</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>CNRS</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>Université de Lorraine</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <header_dates_team>Creation of the Project-Team: 2007 January 01</header_dates_team>
    <LeTypeProjet>Project-Team</LeTypeProjet>
    <keywordsSdN>
      <term>6.1.2. - Stochastic Modeling (SPDE, SDE)</term>
      <term>6.1.3. - Discrete Modeling (multi-agent, people centered)</term>
      <term>6.1.4. - Multiscale modeling</term>
      <term>6.2.2. - Numerical probability</term>
      <term>6.2.3. - Probabilistic methods</term>
      <term>6.2.4. - Statistical methods</term>
      <term>6.4.2. - Stochastic control</term>
    </keywordsSdN>
    <keywordsSecteurs>
      <term>1.1.8. - Evolutionnary biology</term>
      <term>1.1.10. - Mathematical biology</term>
      <term>1.2. - Ecology</term>
      <term>1.3.1. - Understanding and simulation of the brain and the nervous system</term>
      <term>3.2. - Climate and meteorology</term>
      <term>3.3.4. - Atmosphere</term>
      <term>4.3.2. - Hydro-energy</term>
      <term>4.3.3. - Wind energy</term>
      <term>9.4.2. - Mathematics</term>
      <term>9.9.1. - Environmental risks</term>
      <term>9.9.2. - Financial risks</term>
    </keywordsSecteurs>
    <UR name="Sophia"/>
    <UR name="Nancy"/>
  </identification>
  <team id="uid1">
    <person key="tosca-2014-idm26736">
      <firstname>Denis</firstname>
      <lastname>Talay</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
      <firstname>Madalina</firstname>
      <lastname>Deaconu</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Deputy leader, Inria, Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
      <firstname>Mireille</firstname>
      <lastname>Bossy</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
      <firstname>Nicolas</firstname>
      <lastname>Champagnat</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria,
Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="neuromathcomp-2014-idm29208">
      <firstname>Olivier</firstname>
      <lastname>Faugeras</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Emeritus Senior
Researcher, also member of the team <span class="smallcap" align="left">MathNeuro</span></moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
      <firstname>Antoine</firstname>
      <lastname>Lejay</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
      <firstname>Etienne</firstname>
      <lastname>Tanré</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
      <firstname>Denis</firstname>
      <lastname>Villemonais</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="neurosys-2014-idp80760">
      <firstname>Laurence</firstname>
      <lastname>Benini</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until July 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="camus-2014-idp77224">
      <firstname>Isabelle</firstname>
      <lastname>Blanchard</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, from Aug. 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp74528">
      <firstname>Christine</firstname>
      <lastname>Faber</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="modemic-2014-idp74808">
      <firstname>Coralie</firstname>
      <lastname>Fritsch</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Ecole Polytechnique</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2015-idp77288">
      <firstname>Paolo</firstname>
      <lastname>Pigato</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp77000">
      <firstname>Alexandre</firstname>
      <lastname>Richard</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PostDoc</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, until January 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp78248">
      <firstname>Maxime</firstname>
      <lastname>Bonelli</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Koris International, CIFRE, until Sep. 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="mathneuro-2016-idp145968">
      <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
      <lastname>Helson</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Nice, from Oct. 2016, internship April-August 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp81928">
      <firstname>Benoit</firstname>
      <lastname>Henry</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, until Nov. 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2016-idp190560">
      <firstname>Kouadio Jean Claude</firstname>
      <lastname>Kouaho</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Cotutelle Univ. Lorraine
and Univ. F. Houphouët Boigny (Abidjan), from Mar. 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp83160">
      <firstname>Radu</firstname>
      <lastname>Maftei</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Nice</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp86976">
      <firstname>Khaled</firstname>
      <lastname>Salhi</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, until Dec. 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2015-idp84672">
      <firstname>Milica</firstname>
      <lastname>Tomasevic</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2016-idp200448">
      <firstname>Roberto Amaru</firstname>
      <lastname>Cortez Milan</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Sep 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp90680">
      <firstname>Samuel</firstname>
      <lastname>Herrmann</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Bourgogne, Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp92136">
      <firstname>Jean-Francois</firstname>
      <lastname>Jabir</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>University of Valparaíso, until March and in September and December</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp93520">
      <firstname>Sylvain</firstname>
      <lastname>Maire</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Toulon, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2014-idp94776">
      <firstname>Nadia</firstname>
      <lastname>Maïzi</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>ENSM Paris</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2016-idp213328">
      <firstname>Dai</firstname>
      <lastname>Taguchi</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Ritsumeikan University, Japan, Ph.D. student, Mar. 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2015-idp87160">
      <firstname>Philip</firstname>
      <lastname>Protter</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Visiteur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Columbia University, June 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2016-idp218336">
      <firstname>Areski</firstname>
      <lastname>Cousin</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lyon I, Maître de
Conférences, from Sep 2016</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="tosca-2016-idp221280">
      <firstname>Hamid</firstname>
      <lastname>Oudghiri-Idrissi</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Sophia</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria,
internship, from Jul 2016 until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
  </team>
  <presentation id="uid2">
    <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid3" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> aims to significantly contribute to discern and
explore new horizons for stochastic modeling. To this end we need to
better understand the issues of stochastic modeling and the
objectives pursued by practitioners who need them: we thus need to deeply
understand other scientific fields than ours (e.g., Fluid Mechanics,
Ecology, Biophysics) and to take scientific risks.
Indeed, these risks are typified by the facts that often new and complex models do not behave as expected, mathematical and numerical difficulties are harder to overcome than forecast, and the increase of our knowledge in target fields is slower than wished.</p>
      <p>In spite of these risks we think that our scientific approach is relevant
for the following reasons:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid4">
          <p noindent="true">On the one hand, physicists, economists, biologists and engineers use
a stochastic model because they cannot
describe the physical, economical, biological, etc., experiment under
consideration with deterministic
systems, either because the experiment has a huge complexity, or because
accurate calibrations
of the parameters of the models would be impossible. However it is far from
being enough to add noise to a dynamical system or to substitute random
variables as parameters: the probability distribution of the random noises
and parameters themselves is a modeling issue and, in addition, the qualitative
behavior of the model may dramatically change as a function of this choice;
in other terms, adding randomness to capture uncertainties may increase
uncertainty instead of aiding. This issue is not so well understood in the
literature, where most often probabilistic structures are
given <span class="smallcap" align="left">a priori</span> rather than studied as questionable choices.
<b>Therefore our works, which concern application fields
where stochastic modeling is still in its very beginning, include
analysis of the limitations of the models we are elaborating. This analysis
is based, either on theoretical estimates, or on our unique experience
in stochastic simulations.</b></p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid5">
          <p noindent="true">On the other hand, <span class="smallcap" align="left">stochastic computational models</span> are
being developed here and there, including by our team, with a fully different
point of view from classical modeling approaches: these models are aimed
to approximate complex physical laws (e.g. Fluid Mechanics laws
for turbulent flows or folding processes for proteins) by statistical properties
of artificial objects
(e.g. particles interacting with turbulent flows or low dimensional
stochastic systems having suitable correlation structures).
The design of the stochastic
dynamics of these objects is part of the problem to deal with, and the
complexity of the underlying physical phenomena leads to huge simulation
difficulties. <b>Therefore we are exploring
new frontiers for stochastic numerical methods and developing advanced
techniques far beyond our previous works and most of the literature.</b></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p>To bring relevant analytical and numerical answers to the preceding
problems, we feel necessary to attack in parallel several problems arising
from different fields. Each one of these problems contributes to our
better understanding of the advantages and limitations of stochastic
models and algorithms.</p>
      <p>Of course, this strategy allows each researcher in the team to have
her/his own main topic. However
<b>we organize the team in order to maximize internal collaborations</b>.
We consider this point, which justifies the existence of
Inria project-teams, as essential to the success of our programme
of research. It relies on the fact that,
to develop our mathematical and numerical studies, we share
a common interest for collaborations with engineers, practitioners,
physicists, biologists and numerical analysts, and we also share
the following common toolbox:</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid6">
          <p noindent="true">Stochastic differential calculus;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid7">
          <p noindent="true">Mathematical combinations of both partial differential equations (PDEs) analysis and stochastic
analysis for deterministic non-linear
PDEs, notably stochastic control equations
and McKean-Vlasov-Fokker-Planck equations;</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid8">
          <p noindent="true">Original stochastic numerical analysis techniques
to get theoretical estimates on stochastic numerical methods,
and numerical experiments to calibrate these methods.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
      <p>We finally emphasize that the unifying theme of our research is
to develop analytical tools that can be effectively applied to
various problems that come from extremely diverse subjects. For
example, as described in more detail below, we study: branching
processes and their simulation with the view of advancing our
understanding of population dynamics, molecular dynamics, and
cancer models; the theory and numerical analysis of McKean-Vlasov interacting particle systems in order to develop our
models in biology, computational fluid dynamics, coagulation and
fragmentation; hitting times of domains by stochastic processes
so that we can improve on the current methods and theory used in
finance and neuroscience.</p>
    </subsection>
  </presentation>
  <fondements id="uid9">
    <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid10" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
      <p>Most often physicists, economists, biologists and engineers need a stochastic model because
they cannot describe the physical, economical, biological, etc., experiment under
consideration with deterministic systems, either because of its complexity and/or its
dimension or because precise measurements are impossible. Therefore, they abandon trying to get
the exact description of the state of the system at future times given its initial
conditions, and try instead to get a statistical description of the evolution of the system.
For example, they desire to compute occurrence probabilities for critical events such as the
overstepping of a given thresholds by financial losses or neuronal electrical potentials, or
to compute the mean value of the time of occurrence of interesting events such as the
fragmentation to a very small size of a large proportion of a given population of particles.
By nature such problems lead to complex modelling issues: one has to choose appropriate
stochastic models, which require a thorough knowledge of their qualitative properties, and
then one has to calibrate them, which requires specific statistical methods to face the lack
of data or the inaccuracy of these data. In addition, having chosen a family of models and
computed the desired statistics, one has to evaluate the sensitivity of the results to the
unavoidable model specifications. The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> team, in collaboration with specialists of
the relevant fields, develops theoretical studies of stochastic models, calibration
procedures, and sensitivity analysis methods.</p>
      <p>In view of the complexity of the experiments, and thus of the stochastic models, one cannot
expect to use closed form solutions of simple equations in order to compute the desired
statistics. Often one even has no other representation than the probabilistic definition
(e.g., this is the case when one is interested in the quantiles of the probability law of the
possible losses of financial portfolios). Consequently the practitioners need Monte Carlo
methods combined with simulations of stochastic models. As the models cannot be simulated
exactly, they also need approximation methods which can be efficiently used on computers. The
<span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> team develops mathematical studies and numerical experiments in order to determine
the global accuracy and the global efficiency of such algorithms.</p>
      <p>The simulation of stochastic processes is not motivated by stochastic models only. The
stochastic differential calculus allows one to represent solutions of certain deterministic
partial differential equations in terms of probability distributions of functionals of
appropriate stochastic processes. For example, elliptic and parabolic linear equations are
related to classical stochastic differential equations (SDEs), whereas nonlinear equations such as
the Burgers and the Navier–Stokes equations are related to McKean stochastic differential
equations describing the asymptotic behavior of stochastic particle systems. In view of such
probabilistic representations one can get numerical approximations by using discretization
methods of the stochastic differential systems under consideration. These methods may be more
efficient than deterministic methods when the space dimension of the PDE is large or when the
viscosity is small. The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> team develops new probabilistic representations in order
to propose probabilistic numerical methods for equations such as conservation law equations,
kinetic equations, and nonlinear Fokker–Planck equations.</p>
    </subsection>
  </fondements>
  <domaine id="uid11">
    <bodyTitle>Application Domains</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid12" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Domain</bodyTitle>
      <p><span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> is interested in developing stochastic models and probabilistic numerical methods. Our present motivations come from
models with singular coefficients, with applications in Geophysics, Molecular Dynamics and Neurosciences; Lagrangian modeling in
Fluid Dynamics and Meteorology; Population Dynamics, Evolution and Genetics; Neurosciences; and Financial Mathematics.</p>
      <subsection id="uid13" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Stochastic models with singular coefficients: Analysis and simulation</bodyTitle>
        <p>Stochastic differential equations with discontinuous coefficients arise in Geophysics, Chemistry, Molecular Dynamics,
Neurosciences, Oceanography, etc. In particular, they model changes of diffusion of fluids, or diffractions of particles, along
interfaces.</p>
        <p>For practioners in these fields, Monte Carlo methods are popular as they are easy to interpret — one follows particles — and are
in general easy to set up. However, dealing with discontinuities presents many numerical and theoretical challenges. Despite its
important applications, ranging from brain imaging to reservoir simulation, very few teams in mathematics worldwide are currently
working in this area. The Tosca project-team has tackled related problems for several years providing rigorous approach. Based on
stochastic analysis as well as interacting with researchers in other fields, we developed new theoretical and numerical approaches
for extreme cases such as Markov processes whose generators are of divergence form with discontinuous diffusion coefficient.</p>
        <p>The numerical approximation of singular stochastic processes can be combined with backward stochastic differential equations (BSDEs)
or branching diffusions to obtain Monte Carlo methods for quasi-linear PDEs with discontinuous coefficients. The theory of BSDEs has
been extensively developed since the 1980s, but the general assumptions for their existence can be quite restrictive. Although the
probabilistic interpretation of quasi-linear PDEs with branching diffusions has been known for a long time, there have been only a
few works on the related numerical methods.</p>
        <p>Another motivation to consider stochastic dynamics in a discontinuous setting came to us from time evolution of fragmentation and
coagulation phenomena, with the objective to elaborate stochastic models for the avalanche formation of soils, snow, granular
materials or other geomaterials. Most of the models and numerical methods for avalanches are deterministic and involve a wide variety
of physical parameters such as the density of the snow, the yield, the friction coefficient, the pressure, the basal topography, etc.
One of these methods consists in studying the safety factor (or limit load) problem, related to the shallow flow of a visco-plastic
fluid/solid with heterogeneous thickness over complex basal topography. The resulting nonlinear partial differential equation of this
last theory involves many singularities, which motivates us to develop an alternative stochastic approach based on our past works on
coagulation and fragmentation. Our approach consists in studying the evolution of the size of a typical particle in a particle system
which fragments in time.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid14" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Stochastic Lagrangian modeling in Computational Fluid Dynamics</bodyTitle>
        <p>Stochastic Lagrangian models were introduced in the eighties to simulate complex turbulent flows, particularly two-phase flows. In
Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD), they are intensively used in the so-called Probability Density Functions (PDF) methods in order
to model and compute the reaction-phase terms in the fundamental equations of fluid motions. The PDF methods are currently developed
in various laboratories by specialists in scientific computation and physicists. However, to our knowledge, we are innovating in two
ways:</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid15">
            <p noindent="true">our theoretical studies are the pioneering mathematical analysis of Lagrangian stochastic models in CFD;</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid16">
            <p noindent="true">our work on the Stochastic Downscaling Method (SDM) for wind simulation is the first attempt to solve the fundamental equations
themselves by a fully 3D stochastic particle method.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <p>We emphasize that our numerical analysis is essential to the SDM development which takes benefits from our deep expertise on
numerical schemes for McKean-Vlasov-non-linear SDEs.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid17" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Population Dynamics, Evolution and Genetics</bodyTitle>
        <p>The activity of the team on stochastic modeling in population dynamics and genetics mainly concerns application in adaptive dynamics,
a branch of evolutionary biology studying the interplay between ecology and evolution, ecological modeling, population genetics in
growing populations, and stochastic control of population dynamics, with applications to cancer growth modeling. Stochastic modeling
in these areas mainly considers individual-based models, where the birth and death of each individual is described. This class of
model is well-developed in Biology, but their mathematical analysis is still fragmentary. Another important topic in population
dynamics is the study of populations conditioned to non-extinction, and of the corresponding stationary distributions, called
quasi-stationary distributions (QSD). This domain has been the object of a lot of studies since the 1960’s, but we made recently
significant progresses on the questions of existence, convergence and numerical approximation of QSDs using probabilistic tools
rather than the usual spectral tools.</p>
        <p>Our activity in population dynamics also involves a fully new research project on cancer modeling at the cellular level by means of
branching processes. In 2010 the International Society for Protons Dynamics in Cancer was launched in order to create a critical mass
of scientists engaged in research activities on Proton Dynamics in Cancer, leading to the facilitation of international collaboration
and translation of research to clinical development. Actually, a new branch of research on cancer evolution is developing
intensively; it aims in particular to understand the role of proteins acting on cancerous cells' acidity, their effects on glycolysis
and hypoxia, and the benefits one can expect from controlling pH regulators in view of proposing new therapies.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid18" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Stochastic modeling in Neuroscience</bodyTitle>
        <p>It is generally accepted that many different neural processes that take place in the brain involve noise. Indeed,
one typically observes experimentally underlying variability in the spiking times of an individual neuron in response to an
unchanging stimulus, while a predictable overall picture emerges if one instead looks at the average spiking time over a whole group
of neurons. Sources of noise that are of interest include ionic currents crossing the neural membrane, synaptic noise, and the global
effect of the external environment (such as other parts of the brain).</p>
        <p>It is likely that these stochastic components play an important role in the function of both the neurons and the networks they form.
The characterization of the noise in the brain, its consequences at a functional level and its role at both a microscopic (individual
neuron) level and macroscopic level (network of thousands of neurons) is therefore an important step towards understanding the
nervous system.</p>
        <p>To this end, a large amount of current research in the neuroscientific literature has involved the addition of noise to classical
purely deterministic equations resulting in new phenomena being observed. The aim of the project is thus to rigorously study these
new equations in order to be able to shed more light on the systems they describe.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid19" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Stochastic modeling in Financial Mathematics</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid20" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Technical Analysis</bodyTitle>
          <p>In the financial industry, there are three main approaches to investment: the fundamental approach, where strategies are based on
fundamental economic principles; the technical analysis approach, where strategies are based on past price behavior; and the
mathematical approach where strategies are based on mathematical models and studies. The main advantage of technical analysis is that
it avoids model specification, and thus calibration problems, misspecification risks, etc. On the other hand, technical analysis
techniques have limited theoretical justifications, and therefore no one can assert that they are risk-less, or even efficient.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid21" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Financial Risks Estimation and Hedging</bodyTitle>
          <p>Popular models in financial mathematics usually assume that markets are perfectly liquid. In particular, each trader can buy or sell
the amount of assets he/she wants at the same price (the “market price”). They moreover assume that the decision taken by the trader
does not affect the price of the asset (the small investor assumption). In practice, the assumption of perfect liquidity is never
satisfied but the error due to liquidity is generally negligible with respect to other sources of error such as model error or
calibration error, etc.</p>
          <p>Derivatives of interest rates are singular for at least two reasons: firstly the underlying (interest rate) is not directly
exchangeable, and secondly the liquidity costs usually used to hedge interest rate derivatives have large variation in times.</p>
          <p>Due to recurrent crises, the problem of risk estimation is now a crucial issue in finance. Regulations have been enforced (Basel
Committee II). Most asset management software products on the markets merely provide basic measures (VaR, Tracking error, volatility)
and basic risk explanation features (e.g., “top contributors” to risk, sector analysis, etc).</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid22" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Energy and Carbon Markets</bodyTitle>
          <p>With the rise of renewable energy generation (from solar, wind, waves...), engineers face new challenges which heavily rely on stochastic
and statistical problems.</p>
          <p>Besides, in the context of the beginning of the second phase (the Kyoto phase) in 2008 of the European carbon market, together with
the fact that French carbon tax was scheduled to come into law on Jan. 1, 2010, the year 2009 was a key year for the carbon price
modeling. Our research approach adopts the point of view of the legislator and energy producers. We used both financial mathematical
tools and a game theory approach. Today, with the third phase of the EU-ETS, that didn’t yet start, and the report form the Cour des
Comptes (October 2013) that pointed out (among many others point) the lack of mathematical modeling on such carbon market design, we
continue our research in this direction.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid23" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Optimal Stopping Problems</bodyTitle>
          <p>The theory of optimal stopping is concerned with the problem of taking a decision at the best time, in order to maximise an
expected reward (or minimise an expected cost). We work on the general problem of optimal stopping with random discounting and
additional cost of observation.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid24" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>First hitting times distributions</bodyTitle>
          <p>Diffusion hitting times are of great interest in finance (a typical example is the study of barrier options) and also in Geophysics
and Neurosciences. On the one hand, analytic expressions for hitting time densities are well known and studied only in some very
particular situations (essentially in Brownian contexts). On the other hand, the study of the approximation of the hitting times for
stochastic differential equtions is an active area of research since very few results still are available in the literature.</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </domaine>
  <logiciels id="uid25">
    <bodyTitle>New Software and Platforms</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid26" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>AGH</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>AGH (for Analysis of Galton-Watson Harris paths) is a Matlab toolbox providing methods for statistical analysis of ordered trees from their Harris paths in a user-friendly environment. More precisely it allows to easily compute estimators of the relative scale of trees which share the same shape. These estimators have been introduced for Galton-Watson trees conditioned on their number of nodes but may be computed for any ordered tree.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid27">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Romain Azaïs, Alexandre Genadot, Benoît Henry</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid28">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Benoît Henry</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid29">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://agh.gforge.inria.fr/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>agh.<allowbreak/>gforge.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid30" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>ExitBM</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>The exitbm library provides methods to simulate random variables related to the first exit time and position of the Brownian motion from simple domains, namely intervals, squares and rectangles.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid31">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Madalina Deaconu and Antoine Lejay</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid32">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Antoine Lejay</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid33">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://exitbm.gforge.inria.fr/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>exitbm.<allowbreak/>gforge.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid34" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>SDM-WindPoS</bodyTitle>
      <p>Stochastic Downscaling Method and Wind Power Simulation</p>
      <p noindent="true">
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>The computation of the wind at small scale and the estimation of its uncertainties is of particular importance for applications
such as wind energy resource estimation. To this aim, we have developed a computer code belonging to the family of codes of
atmospheric flow calculation, in the atmospheric boundary layer. SDM-windpos especially concerns the simulation of wind at small space
scales (meaning that the horizontal resolution is one kilometer or less), based on the combination of an existing Numerical Weather
Prediction model providing a coarse prediction, and a Lagrangian Stochastic Model for turbulent flows.</p>
      <p>The ability of SDM-WindPoS to regamma the wind computation in the
horizontal scale but also in the vertical scale is of particular
interest for wind farm power production assessment.
WindPoS couples direct actuator disk approach and SDM Atmospheric Boundary Layer (ABL) model for wind farm simulation.</p>
      <p>This year we start to introduce more accurate ABL convection models in SDM. Moreover, we start to add the possibility to introduce more accurate topography when SDM is running with some coarse scale atmospheric input data. Our dedicated GUI was also improved (better rendering for the 2D and 3D views).</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid35">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Mireille Bossy</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid36">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Mireille Bossy</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid37">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://windpos.inria.fr" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>windpos.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </logiciels>
  <resultats id="uid38">
    <bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid39" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Probabilistic numerical methods, stochastic modelling and applications</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
          <firstname>Mireille</firstname>
          <lastname>Bossy</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
          <firstname>Nicolas</firstname>
          <lastname>Champagnat</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
          <firstname>Madalina</firstname>
          <lastname>Deaconu</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="modemic-2014-idp74808">
          <firstname>Coralie</firstname>
          <lastname>Fritsch</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="mathneuro-2016-idp145968">
          <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
          <lastname>Helson</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp81928">
          <firstname>Benoît</firstname>
          <lastname>Henry</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2016-idp190560">
          <firstname>Kouadio Jean Claude</firstname>
          <lastname>Kouaho</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
          <firstname>Antoine</firstname>
          <lastname>Lejay</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp83160">
          <firstname>Radu</firstname>
          <lastname>Maftei</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp93520">
          <firstname>Sylvain</firstname>
          <lastname>Maire</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2015-idp77288">
          <firstname>Paolo</firstname>
          <lastname>Pigato</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp77000">
          <firstname>Alexandre</firstname>
          <lastname>Richard</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idm26736">
          <firstname>Denis</firstname>
          <lastname>Talay</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
          <firstname>Etienne</firstname>
          <lastname>Tanré</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2015-idp84672">
          <firstname>Milica</firstname>
          <lastname>Tomasevic</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
          <firstname>Denis</firstname>
          <lastname>Villemonais</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid40" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Published works and preprints</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid41">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy with H. Quinteros (UChile) studied the rate of convergence of a symmetrized version of the Milstein scheme applied to
the solution of one dimensional CEV type processes. They prove a strong rate of convergence of order one, recovering the
classical result of Milstein for SDEs with smooth diffusion coefficient. In contrast with other recent results, the proof does not
relies on Lamperti transformation, and it can be applied to a wide class of drift functions. Some numerical experiments and
comparison with various other schemes complement the theoretical analysis that also applies for the simple projected Milstein
scheme with same convergence rate (<ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> accepted for publication in Bernoulli Journal).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid42">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy, R. Maftei, J.-P. Minier and C. Profeta worked on numerically determining the rate of convergence of the weak
error for the discretised Langevin system with specular reflection conditions. The article <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> presents a
discretisation scheme and offers a conjecture for the rate of convergence of the bias produced. Numerically, these conjectures are
confirmed for the specular reflection scheme but also for the absorption scheme, which models perfect agglomeration. The scheme
numerically follows a linear decrease. The Richardson-Romberg extrapolation is also presented with a quadratic decrease.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid43">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy, A. Rousseau (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Lemon</span> Inria team), JĖspina, JṀorice and C. Paris (Inria Chile) studied the computation of
the wind circulation around mills, using a Lagrangian stochastic approach. They present the SDM numerical method and numerical
experiments in the case of non rotating and rotating actuator disc models in <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. First, for validation
purpose they compare some numerical experiments against wind tunnel measurements. Second, they perform numerical experiments at the
atmospheric scale and present some features of the numerical method, in particular the computation of the probability distribution
of the wind in the wake zone, as a byproduct of the fluid particle model and the associated PDF method.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid44">
            <p noindent="true">Together with M. Baar and A. Bovier (Univ. Bonn), N. Champagnat studied the adaptive dynamics of populations under the
assumptions of large population, rare and small mutations <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. In this work, the three limits are taken
simultaneously, contrary to the classical approach, where the limits of large population and rare mutations are taken first, and
next the limit of small mutations  <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. We therefore obtain the precise range of parameters under which these limits
can be taken, and provide explicit biological conditions for which our approximation is valid.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid45">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and J. Claisse (Ecole Polytechnique) studied the ergodic and infinite horizon controls of discrete population
dynamics with almost sure extinction in finite time. This can either correspond to control problems in favor of survival or of
extinction, depending on the cost function. They have proved that these two problems are related to the QSD of the processes
controled by Markov controls <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid46">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and C. Fritsch worked with F. Campillo (Inria Sophia-Antipolis, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Lemon</span> team) on the links between a
branching process and an integro-differential equation of a growth-fragmentation-death model <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. They
proved that the two representations of the model lead to the same criteria of invasion of a population in a given environment. They
also studied the variations of the principal eigenvalue (resp. the survival probability) of an integro-differential equation
(resp. branching process) of growth-fragmentation models with respect to an environmental parameter
in <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid47">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and D. Villemonais consider, for general absorbed Markov processes, the notion of quasi-stationary distributions
(QSD), which is a stationary distribution conditionally on
non-absorbtion, and the associated <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>Q</mi></math></formula>-process, degammad as the
original
Markov process conditioned to never be absorbed. They prove that, under the conditions of <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, in
addition to the uniform exponential convergence of conditional distributions to a unique QSD and the uniform exponential ergodicity
of the <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>Q</mi></math></formula>-process, one also has the uniform convergence of the law of the process contionned to survival up to time <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>T</mi></math></formula>, when
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>T</mi><mo>→</mo><mo>+</mo><mi>∞</mi></mrow></math></formula>. This allows them to obtain conditional ergodic theorems <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid48">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat, K. Coulibaly-Pasquier (Univ. Lorraine) and D. Villemonais obtained general criteria for existence, uniqueness
and exponential convergence in total variation to QSD for multi-dimensional diffusions in a domain absorbed at its
boundary <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid10" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. These results improve and simplify the existing results and methods.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid49">
            <p noindent="true">Using a new method to compute the expectation of an integral with respect to a random measure, N. Champagnat and B. Henry
obtained explicit formulas for the moments of the frequency spectrum in the general branching processes known as Splitting Trees,
with neutral mutations and under the infinitely-many alleles model <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. This allows them to obtain a law
of large numbers for the frequency spectrum in the limit of large time.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid50">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and D. Villemonais obtained criteria for existence, uniqueness and exponential convergence in total variation to
QSD for discrete population processes with unbounded absorption rate, using a non-linear Lyapunov
criterion <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. For logistic multidimensional birth and death processes absorbed when one coordinate gets
extinct, they show that their criterion covers cases stronger intra-spectific competition than inter-specific competition.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid51">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and D. Villemonais extended their work <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> to general penalized processes, including
time-inhomogeneous Markov processes with absorption and Markov processes in varying environments <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
Their method allows to improve significantly the former results of  <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid15" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid52">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu worked with L. Beznea and O. Lupaşcu (Bucharest, Romania) and analyzed the description of rupture phenomena like
avalanches, by using fragmentation models. The main physical properties of the model are deeply involved in this study. They
obtained new results on a stochastic equation of fragmentation and branching processes related to
avalanches <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid53">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu and S. Herrmann continued and completed the study of the simulation of hitting times of given boundaries for Bessel
processes. These problems are of great interest in many application fields, such as finance and neurosciences. In a previous work,
the authors introduced a new method for the simulation of hitting times for Bessel processes with integer dimension. The method was
based mainly on explicit formula for the distribution of the hitting times and on the connexion between the Bessel process and the
Euclidean norm of the Brownian motion. The method does not apply for a non-integer dimension. In this new work they consider the
simulation of the hitting time of Bessel processes with non integer dimension and provide a new algorithm by using the additivity
property of the laws of squared Bessel processes. Each simulation step is splitted in two parts: one is using the integer dimension
case and the other one exhibits hitting time of a Bessel process starting from zero <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid54">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu and S. Herrmann studied the Initial-Boundary Value Problem for the heat equation and solved it by using a new
algorithm based on a random walk on heat balls <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Even if it represents a sophisticated and challenging
generalization of the Walk on Spheres (WOS) algorithm introduced to solve the Dirichlet problem for Laplace's equation, its
implementation is rather easy. The definition of the random walk is based on a new mean value formula for the heat equation. The
convergence results and numerical examples allow to emphasize the efficiency and accuracy of the algorithm.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid55">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu, B. Dumortier and E. Vincent (EPI <span class="smallcap" align="left">Multispeech</span> are working with the Venathec SAS on the acoustic control of
wind farms. They constructed a new approach to control wind farms based on real-time source separation. They expressed the problem
as a non-linear knapsack problem and solve it using an efficient branch-and-bound algorithm that converges asymptotically to the
global optimum. The algorithm is initialised with a greedy heuristic that iteratively downgrades the turbines with the best
acoustical to electricity loss ratio. The solution is then regammad
using a depth-first search strategy and a bounding stage based
on a continuous relaxation problem solved with an adapted gradient algorithm. The results are evaluated using data from 28 real
wind farms <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid19" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid56">
            <p noindent="true">C. Fritsch and B. Cloez (INRA, Montpellier) proved central limit theorems for chemostat models in finite and infinite
dimensions in <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid20" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. From these theorems, they obtianed gaussian approximations of individual-based models and
made a numerical analysis for the model in finite dimension in order to discuss the validity of these approximations in different
contexts.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid57">
            <p noindent="true">Together with R. Azaïs (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Bigs</span> Inria team) and A. Genadot (Univ. Bordeaux), B. Henry studied an estimation problem for a
forest of size-constrained Galton-Watson trees <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid21" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Using the asymptotic behavior of the Harris contour
process, they constructed estimators for the inverse standard deviation of the birth distribution. In addition to the theoretical
convergence results obtained in this work, they used the method to study the evolution of Wikipedia webpages in order, for
instance, to detect vandalism.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid58">
            <p noindent="true">In <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid22" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, B. Henry showed a central limit theorem for the population counting process of a supercritical
Splitting Tree in the limit of large time. Thanks to the results of <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, he also obtained a central
limit theorem for the frequency spectrum of Splitting Trees with neutral mutations and under the infinitely-many alleles model.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid59">
            <p noindent="true">In collaboration with Laure Coutin, A. Lejay have studied the sensitivity of solution of rough differential equations with
respect to their parameters using a Banach space version of the implicit function theorem. This result unifies and extends all the
similar results on the subject <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid23" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid60">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay have studied the parametric estimation of the bias coefficient of skew random walk, as a toy model for the problem of
estimation of the parameter of the Skew Brownian motion <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid61">
            <p noindent="true">P. Pigato has continued with V. Bally (Univ. Marne-la-Vallée) and L. Caramellino (Univ. Roma Tor Vergata) his PhD work on the
regularity of diffusions under Hörmander-type conditions <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid26" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid62">
            <p noindent="true">A. Richard and D. Talay ended their work on the sensitivity of the first hitting time of fractional SDEs, when <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>H</mi><mo>&gt;</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mrow></math></formula>
<ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid27" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. This study is being completed by the rough case <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>H</mi><mo>∈</mo><mo>(</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac><mo>,</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo>]</mo></mrow></math></formula>. In relation to
fractional SDEs, another short work on accurate Gaussian-like upper
bounds on density of one-dimensional fractional SDEs is almost
finished.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid63">
            <p noindent="true">In <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid28" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, S. Herrmann and E. Tanré propose a new algorithm to simulate the first hitting times of a
deterministic continuous function by a one-dimensional Brownian motion. They give explicit rate of convergence of the algorithm.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid64">
            <p noindent="true">E. Tanré and Pierre Guiraud (Univ. of Valparaiso) have studied the synchronization in a model of neural network with noise.
Using a large deviation principle, they prove the stability of the synchronized state under stochastic perturbations. They also
give a lower bound on the probability of synchronization for networks which are not initially synchronized. This bound shows the
robustness of the emergence of synchronization in presence of small stochastic perturbations. <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid29" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid65">
            <p noindent="true">V. Reutenauer and E. Tanré have worked on extensions of the exact simulation algorithm introduced by Beskos et
al.  <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid30" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. They propose an unbiased algorithm to approximate the two first derivatives with respect to the initial
condition <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>x</mi></math></formula> of quantities with the form <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>𝔼</mi><mi>Ψ</mi><mo>(</mo><msubsup><mi>X</mi><mi>T</mi><mi>x</mi></msubsup><mo>)</mo></mrow></math></formula>, where <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>X</mi></math></formula> is a one-dimensional diffusion process and
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>Ψ</mi></math></formula> any test-function. They also propose an efficient modification of Beskos et al. algorithm. <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid31" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/></p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid66">
            <p noindent="true">During his internship supervised by E. Tanré, A. Papic worked on multi scales generator of Markov processes. He presents a
method to approximate such processes with an application in neuroscience for noisy Hodgkin-Huxley model <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid32" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid67">
            <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais worked with P. Del Moral (Univ. Sydney) on the conditional ergodicity of time inhomogeneous diffusion
processes <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid33" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. They proved that, conditionally on non extinction, an elliptic time-inhomogeneous diffusion
process forgets its initial distribution exponentially fast. An interacting particle scheme to numerically approximate the
conditional distribution is also provided.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid68">
            <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais worked with his Research Project student William Oçafrain (École des Mines de Nancy) on an original
mean-field particle system <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid34" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. They proved that the mean-field particle system converges in full
generality toward the distribution of a conditioned Markov process, with applications to the approximation of the quasi-stationary
distribution of piecewise deterministic Markov processes.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid69" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Other works in progress</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid70">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy and R. Maftei are working on determining the rate of convergence of the weak error of a discretised scheme for the
Langevin system with specular boundary reflection on the position. The velocity process allows for a bounded and smooth drift. In
order to determine the optimal rate of convergence, the regularity of the associated PDE is required and also regularity results
for the derivative of flow of the process w.r.t. the initial conditions.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid71">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and B. Henry are studying limits of small mutations in Lokta-Volterra type PDEs of population dynamics using
probabilistic representations and large deviations.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid72">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat, C. Fritsch and S. Billiard (Univ. Lille) are working on food web modeling.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid73">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu and S. Herrmann are working on numerical approaches for hitting times of general stochastic differential equations.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid74">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu, O. Lupaşcu and L. Beznea (Bucharest, Romania) worked on the numerical scheme for the simulation of an avalanche
by using the fragmentation model. This work will be submitted soon.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid75">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu, B. Dumortier and E. Vincent (EPI <span class="smallcap" align="left">Multispeech</span>) work on handling uncertainties in the model of acoustic control
of wind farms they develop, in order to design a stochastic algorithm based on filtering methods. They will submit another article
to IEEE transaction on sustainable energy.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid76">
            <p noindent="true">C. Fritsch is working with F. Campillo (Inria Sophia-Antipolis, <span class="smallcap" align="left">Lemon</span> team) and O. Ovaskainen (Univ. Helsinki) about a
numerical approach to determine mutant invasion fitness and evolutionary singular strategies using branching processes and
integro-differential models. They illustrate this method with a mass-structured individual-based chemostat model.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid77">
            <p noindent="true">C. Fritsch is working with A. Gégout-Petit (Univ. Lorraine and sc Bigs team), B. Marçais (INRA, Nancy) and
M. Grosdidier (INRA, Nancy) on a statistical analysis of a <i>Chalara fraxinea</i> model.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid78">
            <p noindent="true">B. Cloez (INRA Montpellier) and B. Henry started a work on the asymptotic behavior of splitting trees in random environment. In
addition, they begin the study of scaling limits of splitting trees in varying environment.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid79">
            <p noindent="true">Together with Ernesto Mordecki (Universidad de la República, Uruguay) and Soledad Torres (Universidad de Valparaíso), A. Lejay
is working on the estimation of the parameter of the Skew Brownian motion.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid80">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay, and P. Pigato are working on the estimation of the parameters of diffusions with discontinuous coefficients, with
application to financial data.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid81">
            <p noindent="true">Together with Laure Coutin and Antoine Brault (Université Toulouse 3), A. Lejay is studying application of the Trotter-Kato
theorem in the context of rough differential equations, in order to solve some Stochastic Partial Differential Equations.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid82">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay and H. Mardones are working on a Monte Carlo simulation of the Navier-Stokes equations which is based on a novel
probabilistic representation due to F. Delbaen <i>et al.</i>  <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid35" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid83">
            <p noindent="true">In a research visit to Chile, P. Pigato has worked with R. Rebolledo and S. Torres on the estimation of parameters of
diffusions from the occupation time and the local time of the process.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid84">
            <p noindent="true">Together with Laure Coutin and Antoine Brault (Université Toulouse 3), A. Lejay is studying application of the Trotter-Kato
theorem in the context of rough differential equations, in order to
solve some Stochastic Partial Differential Equations.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid85">
            <p noindent="true">C. Graham (École Polytechnique) and D. Talay are polishing
thesecond volume of their series on Mathematical
Foundation of Stochastic Simulation to be published by Springer.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid86">
            <p noindent="true">In collaboration with J. Bion-Nadal (CNRS and École
Polytechnique) D. Talay ended the first paper on an innovating
calibration method for stochastic models belonging to a family of
solutions to martingale problems. The methodology involves the
introduction of a new Wasserstein-type distance and stochastic control
problems. The manuscript is being finished.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid87">
            <p noindent="true">Motivated by the study of systems of non-linear PDE's by stochastic methods, M. Tomasevic and D. Talay studied a system of
differential equations interacting through a singular kernel, depending on all the past of the solutions. They have proved the
existence of a solution in the space of Lipschitz functions in short time interval and performed numerical simulations. In the same
time, they studied a non-linear stochastic differential equation whose drift is given as a convolution of a singular kernel with
the unknown one dimensional time marginals both in time and space. Combining probabilistic and PDE techniques, they are currently
finishing the proof of the existence and uniqueness of a weak solution up to an arbitrary finite time horizon. Properties of the
corresponding particle system (well-posedness and propagation of chaos) are also studied.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid88">
            <p noindent="true">A. Richard and E. Tanré's work with Patricio Orio (CINV, Chile) on the modelling and measurement of long-range dependence in
neuronal spike trains is almost completed. They exhibit evidence of memory effect in genuine neuronal data and compared their
fractional integrate-and-fire model with the existing Markovian models. A. Richard and E. Tanré are still working on the
convergence of the statistical estimator that measures this phenomenon.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid89">
            <p noindent="true">A. Richard, E. Tanré are working with S. Torres (Universidad de Valparaíso, Chile) on a one-dimensional fractional SDE
reflected on the line. The existence and uniqueness of this process is known in the case <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>H</mi><mo>&gt;</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mrow></math></formula>. In addition, they have
proved the existence of a penalization scheme (suited to numerical approximation) to approach this object. When
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mi>H</mi><mo>∈</mo><mo>(</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac><mo>,</mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo></mrow></math></formula>, they have proved the existence in the elliptic case and are working on the question of uniqueness
and on the relaxation of ellipticity.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid90">
            <p noindent="true">During his internship supervised by E. Tanré and Romain Veltz (<span class="smallcap" align="left">Mathneuro</span> team), Pascal Helson studied numerically and
theoretically a model of spiking neurons in interaction with plasticity. He showed that a simple model without plasticity could
reproduce biological phenomena such as oscillations. In order to add plasticity, he enabled synaptic weights to evolve in a
probabilistic way, in agreement with biological laws. He is now studying the convergence of this model and the existence of
separable time scales, which is part of his thesis.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid91">
            <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais started a collaboration with Camille Coron (Univ. Paris Sud) and Sylvie Méléard (École Polytechnioque) on the
question of simultaneous/non-simultaneous extinction of traits in a structured population</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid92">
            <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais currently works on the computation of lower bounds for the Wasserstein curvature of interacting particle
systems.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid93">
            <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais started a collaboration with Éliane Albuisson (CHRU of Nancy), Athanase Benetos (CHRU of Nancy), Simon
Toupance (CHRU of Nancy), Daphné Germain (École des Mines de Nancy) and Anne Gégout-Petit (Inria <span class="smallcap" align="left">Bigs</span> team). The aim of
this collaboration is to conduct a statistical study of the time evolution of telomere's length in human cells.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid94" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Financial Mathematics</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp78248">
          <firstname>Maxime</firstname>
          <lastname>Bonelli</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
          <firstname>Mireille</firstname>
          <lastname>Bossy</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
          <firstname>Nicolas</firstname>
          <lastname>Champagnat</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
          <firstname>Madalina</firstname>
          <lastname>Deaconu</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
          <firstname>Antoine</firstname>
          <lastname>Lejay</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp93520">
          <firstname>Sylvain</firstname>
          <lastname>Maire</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp86976">
          <firstname>Khaled</firstname>
          <lastname>Salhi</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idm26736">
          <firstname>Denis</firstname>
          <lastname>Talay</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
          <firstname>Etienne</firstname>
          <lastname>Tanré</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid95" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Published works and preprints</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid96">
            <p noindent="true">K. Salhi, M. Deaconu, A. Lejay and N. Champagnat worked with N. Navet (University of Luxembourg) <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid36" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
They construct a regime switching model for the univariate Value-at-Risk estimation. Extreme value theory (EVT) and hidden Markov
models (HMM) are combined to estimate a hybrid model that takes volatility clustering into account. In the first stage, HMM is used
to classify data in crisis and steady periods, while in the second stage, EVT is applied to the previously classified data to rub
out the delay between regime switching and their detection. This new model is applied to prices of numerous stocks exchanged on
NYSE Euronext Paris over the period 2001-2011. The relative performance of the regime switching model is benchmarked against other
well-known modeling techniques, such as stable, power laws and GARCH models.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid97">
            <p noindent="true">K. Salhi wrote a survey paper about option pricing and risk management under exponential Lévy models <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid37" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
He detailed some notions that are not well explained in the literature and he proposed new trends in the risk management of
derivatives.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid98">
            <p noindent="true">In <ref xlink:href="#tosca-2016-bid38" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, D. Talay, E. Tanré, Christophe Michel (CA-CIB) and Victor Reutenauer (fotonower) have studied
a model in financial mathematics including bid-ask spread cost. They study the optimal strategy to hedge an interest rate swap that
pays a fixed rate against a floating rate. They present a methodology using a stochastic gradient algorithm to optimize strategies.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid99" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Other works in progress</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid100">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy and M. Bonelli (Koris International) are working on the optimal portfolio investment problem under the drawdown
constraint that the wealth process never falls below a fixed fraction of its running maximum. They derive optimal allocation
programs by solving numerically the Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation that characterizes the finite horizon expected utility
maximization problem, for investors with power utility as well as S-shape utility. Using numerical experiments they show that
implementing the drawdown constraint can be gainful in optimal portfolios for the power utility, for some market configurations and
investment horizons. However, their study reveals different results in a prospect theory context.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid101">
            <p noindent="true">When the underlying asset price is given by a exponential Lévy model, the market is almost incomplete. Under this hypothesis,
K. Salhi works on derivatives hedging under a budget constraint on the initial capital. He considers, as criterion of optimization,
the CVaR of the terminal hedging risk. First, he rewrites the problem an optimisation problem on the random fraction of the payoff
that permits to respect the budget constraint. Then, he approximates the problem by relaxing the constraint and considering only a
specific equivalent martingale measure. This approximate problem is solved using Neyman-Pearson's Lemma and, in the case of
European options, a numerical valuation of the approximated minimal CVaR based on fast Fourier transform. The article will be
submitted soon.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </resultats>
  <contrats id="uid102">
    <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid103" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid104">
          <p noindent="true"><span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> Sophia is involved in a Cifre convention with Koris International. M. Bossy supervises M. Bonelli's Ph.D. thesis.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid105">
          <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu is involved in a bilateral contract with Venathec. She is supervising, with E. Vincent (EPI <span class="smallcap" align="left">Multispeech</span>), the
Ph.D. thesis of B. Dumortier on the acoustic control of wind farms noise.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid106" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Bilateral Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid107">
          <p noindent="true">Mireille Bossy is the Coordinator of the PEPS from AMIES granted with the SME Seatopic, on the wind downscaling, using finer
local topography, for coastal activities.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid108">
          <p noindent="true">Mireille Bossy is the Coordinator of the TER project from the PGMO (FMJH) granted with the SME METIGATE, on the statistical
description of coupled regional temperatures.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </contrats>
  <partenariat id="uid109">
    <bodyTitle>Partnerships and Cooperations</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid110" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>National Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid111" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ANR</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid112">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat is member of the ANR NONLOCAL (Phénomènes de propagation et équations non locales, 2014–2018)
coordinated by F. Hamel (Univ. Aix-Marseille).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid113">
            <p noindent="true">E. Tanré is member of the ANR SloFaDyBio (Slow Fast Dynamics in Biology, ANR-14-CE25-0019, 2015-2017) coordinated by M.
Desroches (EPI <span class="smallcap" align="left">Mathneuro</span>, Inria Sophia Antipolis).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid114" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid115" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria International Labs</bodyTitle>
        <p>
          <b>Inria Chile</b>
        </p>
        <p noindent="true">Associate Team involved in the International Lab:</p>
        <subsection id="uid116" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>
            <ref xlink:href="http://www.incidechile.cl/anestoc/teams-involved/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">ANESTOC-TOSCA </ref>
          </bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid117">
              <p noindent="true">Title: Stochastic modelling of biology and renewable energies</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid118">
              <p noindent="true">International Partner (Institution - Laboratory - Researcher):</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid119">
                  <p noindent="true">Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile (Chile)
- ANESTOC Center (ANESTOC) - Rebolledo Rolando</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid120">
              <p noindent="true">Start year: 2014</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid121">
              <p noindent="true">See also: <ref xlink:href="http://www.incidechile.cl/anestoc/teams-involved/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>incidechile.<allowbreak/>cl/<allowbreak/>anestoc/<allowbreak/>teams-involved/</ref></p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid122">
              <p noindent="true">This French-Chilean Associated Team deals with stochastic modeling
and simulation issues for renewable energies (wind and waves)
and neurosciences. It is a follow-up of a long collaboration
in which each of the side takes benefit from the other side know-how
and structures. In particular, this Associated Team is
strongly related to the CIRIC project “Stochastic Analysis
of Renewable Energy”. This project aims at transfering and
valuing to Chilean companies the results of researches on
renewable energies, mainly wind prediction at the windfarm's scale
and waves energy potential of a site using video.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid123" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Participation in Other International Programs</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid124" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid125">
              <p noindent="true">
                <b>ECOS Discrelongmem</b>
              </p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid126">
              <p noindent="true">Title: On discretization procedures in Non-Gaussian long memory processes with applications in non parametric statistics and time series analysis</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid127">
              <p noindent="true">International Partner (Institution - Laboratory - Researcher):</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid128">
                  <p noindent="true">Universidad de Valparaiso (Chile)
- CIMFAV – Facultad de
Ingenieria</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid129">
              <p noindent="true">PI: E. Tanré (France), S. Torrès (Chile)</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid130">
              <p noindent="true">Duration: 2016 - 2018</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid131">
              <p noindent="true">Start year: 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid132">
              <p noindent="true">Keywords: Approximations of non-Gaussian long-memory processes. Fractional Poisson processes (fPp). Skew Fractional Process (SfP).</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid133" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Research Visitors</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid134" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits of International Scientists</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid135">
            <p noindent="true">L. Beznea (Simion Stoilow Institute of Mathematics of the Romanian Academy, Bucarest) has been visiting <span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> Nancy for
11 days in July.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid136">
            <p noindent="true">O. Lupaşcu (Simion Stoilow Institute of Mathematics of the Romanian Academy, Bucarest) has been visiting <span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> Nancy
for one week in October.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid137">
            <p noindent="true">The <span class="smallcap" align="left">Tosca</span> seminar organized by A. Richard in
Sophia Antipolis has received the following speakers:
Pierre-Emmanuel Jabin (University of Maryland), Christophe Henry
(Institute of Lluid Flow Machinery, Polish Academy of Sciences), Tony
Lelièvre (ENPC), D. Alberici (University of Bologna), Nicolas
Fournier (Université Pierre et Marie Curie),
Philip Protter (Columbia University),
Jean-François Jabir (CIMFAV – Valparaiso, Chile),
Roberto Cortez Milan (CIMFAV – Valparaiso, Chile),
Areski Cousin (ISFA, Lyon).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <subsection id="uid138" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Internships</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid139">
              <p noindent="true">BICHAT Antoine</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid140">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: Modélisation de populations de cellules irradiées: une approche par processus de branchement</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid141">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: Sep. 2015 - June 2016 (projet recherche)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid142">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Écoles des Mines de Nancy.</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid143">
              <p noindent="true">CORMIER Quentin</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid144">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: Study of invariants associated to the dynamic of a neuron network subject to STDP</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid145">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: Oct. 2015 - Feb. 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid146">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: ENS Lyon</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid147">
              <p noindent="true">DUPRE Aurore</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid148">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: Analyse et évaluation de l’adjonction de la modélisation de phénomènes convectifs dans un modèle numérique
lagrangien de la couche limite atmosphérique</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid149">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: April 2016 - Oct. 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid150">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Université de Reims Champagne-Ardenne</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid151">
              <p noindent="true">GEORGES Thomas</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid152">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: Single Particle Tracking Techniques</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid153">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: Sept. 2016 - June 2017 (research project)</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid154">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Écoles des Mines de Nancy.</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid155">
              <p noindent="true">GUERBAB Ismail</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid156">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: Sums of Pareto distributions</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid157">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: June 2016 - Aug. 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid158">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Écoles des Mines de Nancy.</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid159">
              <p noindent="true">HELSON Pascal</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid160">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: Spikking Neurons in interaction with Plasticity</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid161">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: April 2016 - Aug. 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid162">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Ecole des Ponts et chaussées.</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid163">
              <p noindent="true">KANTASSI Ameni</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid164">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: Processus du plus récent ancêtre commun dans des arbres de Galton-Watson</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid165">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: April 2015 - Aug. 2015</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid166">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. Lorraine et École Supérieure des Sciences et Technologies d'Hammam Sousse (Tunisie).</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
            <li id="uid167">
              <p noindent="true">PAPIC Alexis</p>
              <sanspuceslist>
                <li id="uid168">
                  <p noindent="true">Subject: States Reduction on Markov Processes</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid169">
                  <p noindent="true">Date: Mai 2016 - Aug. 2016</p>
                </li>
                <li id="uid170">
                  <p noindent="true">Institution: Univ. Pierre et Marie Curie.</p>
                </li>
              </sanspuceslist>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid171" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits to International Teams</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid172" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Research Stays Abroad</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid173">
              <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and D. Villemonais spent one week in Neuchâtel (Switzerland) in September, to work with Michel Benaïm.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid174">
              <p noindent="true">P. Pigato has spent two weeks in Valparaiso and Santiago (Chile) in March, working with R. Rebolledo and S. Torres.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid175">
              <p noindent="true">P. Pigato has spent one week in Padova (Italy), in June, for a collaboration with P. Dai Pra.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid176">
              <p noindent="true">A. Richard and E. Tanré have spent one week in Valparaíso and one week in Santiago (Chile) in December within the ECOS
program (PIs: E. Tanré, S. Torres, C. Tudor), working with S. Torres
(Univ. of Valparaiso).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid177">
              <p noindent="true">D. Talay spent ten days at Columbia University in October.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </partenariat>
  <diffusion id="uid178">
    <bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid179" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Promoting Scientific Activities</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid180" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Promotion of Mathematics in the industry</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid181">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu and A. Lejay were invited to give a talk at ILAC,
Luxembourg in March 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid182">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay has been appointed as representative of Inria
Nancy-Grand Est in the Agence Mathématiques et Entreprise (AMIES).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid183">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay continued to serve as the Vice-President of the Fondation d'Entreprise Natixis which aims to contribute to develop
research in quantitative finance. He also serves as a member of the Scientific Committee of the Foundation.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid184">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay continued to serve as a member of the Scientific Committee of the AMIES National Agency aimed to promote interactions
between Mathematics and Industry.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid185" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Organisation</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid186">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat and M. Deaconu organized the mini-symposium “Un panorama de progrès récents sur les méthodes numériques
probabilistes” at CANUM 2016 (Congrès d'Analyse Numérique) at Obernai in July 2016.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
        <subsection id="uid187" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Organizing Committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid188">
              <p noindent="true">A. Lejay was member of the conference organizing committees of <i>CANUM 2016</i> (Obernai, France).</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid189" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Events Selection</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid190" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Conference Program Committees</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid191">
              <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat served as a member of the program committee of CARI 2016 (13ème Colloque Africain sur la Recherche en
Informatique et Mathématiques Appliquées), Tunis, 10–14 octobre 2016.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid192">
              <p noindent="true">A. Lejay is member of the conference program committees of <i>CANUM 2016</i> (Obernai, France) and <i>Journées de
Probabilités 2016</i> (Le Mans, France).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid193">
              <p noindent="true">D. Talay served as a member of the XIIIth France-Romania
Colloquium in Applied Mathematics.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid194">
              <p noindent="true">E. Tanré served as a member of the program committee of the International Conference on Mathematical NeuroScience (ICMNS
2016), Juan les Pins.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid195" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Journal</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid196" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Editorial Boards</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid197">
              <p noindent="true">M. Bossy served as an Associate Editor of <i>Annals of Applied Probability</i>.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid198">
              <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat served as an Associate Editor of <i>Stochastic Models</i>.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid199">
              <p noindent="true">A. Lejay is one of the three editors of the <i>Séminaire de
Probabilités</i>.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid200">
              <p noindent="true">D. Talay served as an Associate Editor of:
<i>Stochastic Processes and their Applications</i>,
<i>ESAIM Probability and Statistics</i>,
<i>Stochastics and Dynamics</i>,
<i>Journal of Scientific Computing</i>,
<i>Monte Carlo Methods and Applications</i>,
<i>Oxford IMA Journal of Numerical Analysis</i>,
<i>SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing</i>,
<i>Communications in Applied Mathematics and Computational Science</i>,
<i>Éditions de l'École Polytechnique</i>. He also served as
the Co-editor in chief of <i>MathematicS in Action</i>.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid201" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Reviewer - Reviewing Activities</bodyTitle>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid202">
              <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu wrote reviews for manuscripts submitted to <i>Journal of Computational and Applied Mathematics</i>.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid203">
              <p noindent="true">A. Lejay wrote reviews for manuscripts submitted to <i>Journal of Computational Mathematics</i>, <i>Mathematics and
Computers in Simulation</i>, <i>Mathematical Reports</i>, <i>SIAM Journal of Control and Optimization</i>, <i>Communications in
Mathematical Physics,</i>, <i>Real Analysis Exchange </i>, <i>Annals of Probability</i>, <i>Electronic Journal of Probability</i>.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid204">
              <p noindent="true">E. Tanré wrote reviews for manuscripts submitted to <i>Applied Mathematical Finance</i>, <i>Bernoulli</i>, <i>European
Journal of Applied Mathematics</i>.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid205">
              <p noindent="true">E. Tanré serves has a permanent reviewer of <i>Mathematical Reviews of the American Mathematical Society (MathSciNet)</i></p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid206">
              <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais wrote reviews for <i>Mathematical Reviews of the American Mathematical Society (MathSciNet)</i> and for
manuscripts submitted to <i>Stochastic processes and applications</i> and <i>Theoretical Population Biology</i>.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid207" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Invited Talks</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid208">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy has been invited to give a talk at the seminar of the Laboratoire Jacques-Louis Lions, in May.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid209">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy has been invited to give a seminar talk at the Rencontre Niçoise de Mécanique des Fluides, at the Observatoire de la
Côte d'Azur in Nice, June</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid210">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy has been invited to give a talk at the symposium <i>SDE approximation</i> at the International Conference on Monte
Carlo techniques, In Paris, July.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid211">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat has been invited to give talks at the conference <i>Stochastic PDE's, Large Scale Interacting Systems and
Applications to Biology</i> in Orsay in March, to the CMO-BIRS workshop <i>Stochastic and Deterministic Models for Evolutionary
Biology</i> in Oaxaca, Mexico, in August and at the conference <i>Probabilistic structures in deterministic population genetics</i>
in Vienna in November.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid212">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat has been invited to give seminar talks at <i>TOSCA seminar</i> in Inria Sophia Antipolis in April, at the
<i>MAPMO probability seminar</i> in October and at the seminar <i>Méthodes probabilistes et statistiques en dynamique des
populations</i> in Grenoble in December.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid213">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat has been invited to give a lecture at the CIMPA School <i>Mathématiques pour la Biologie</i> (4h) in Tunis in October.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid214">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu was invited to give a talk at the <i>Colloque Franco Roumain de Mathématiques Appliquées</i>, Iaşi (Romania)
in August 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid215">
            <p noindent="true">C. Fritsch has been invited to give talks at the <i>Workshop on “Approche Interdisciplinaire en Evolution”</i> in
Saint-Martin-de-Londres in December.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid216">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay has been invited to give talk at the <i>Workshop on Numerical Schemes of SDE and SPDE</i> in Lille in June 2016, and
at the <i>International Conference on Monte Carlo techniques</i> in Paris in July 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid217">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay has ben invited to give a seminair talk at the Université de Reims in February 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid218">
            <p noindent="true">P. Pigato gave talks at the Probability Seminar of Luxembourg University, in January, at the Seminar of TOSCA-Sophia Antipolis,
in February, at the Seminar of CIMFAV (Valparaíso) in March, at the Journées de Probabilités 2016, in May, at the Probability
Seminar of Università degli studi di Padova, in June, and at the London-Paris Bachelier Workshop on Mathematical Finance in
September.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid219">
            <p noindent="true">A. Richard gave seminar talks at the LPMA (Paris 6) Probability seminar and the IMT (Toulouse) probability seminar in February, at the
Groupe de Travail on stochastic models in finance at Ecole Polytechnique and at the Barcelona probability seminar in April.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid220">
            <p noindent="true">A. Richard had an accepted talk at ICMNS 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid221">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay gave a lecture at the Mean-field and population-level
descriptions of brain dynamics Meeting in February at the EITN, Paris,
the opeing lecture at the conference in V. Konokov's honor in Moscow in
June, a mini-course at Lille University in June, and an invited lecture
at the Workshop on the
Numerics for Stochastic Partial Differential Equations and their
Applications at RICAM, Linz (Austria) in December.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid222">
            <p noindent="true">E. Tanré gave talks at LPMA (Paris 6) and at the workshop on Numerical schemes for SDEs and SPDEs in Lille in June.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid223">
            <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais has been invited to give talks at the workshop <i>Stochastic processes under constraints</i> in July in
Augsburg, Germany, at the conference <i>Colloque franco-roumain de mathématiques</i> in August in Iaşi, Romania, and at the
<i>School on Information and Randomness</i> in December in Santiago, Chile.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid224">
            <p noindent="true">D. Villemonais has been invited to give seminar talks at <i>Institut Montpelliérain Alexander Grothendieck</i> in February, at
the <i>Institut de Recherche Mathématique Avancée</i> in Strasbourg in November, and at the <i>Modal'X seminar</i> in Nanterre in
December.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid225" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Leadership within the Scientific Community</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid226">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay is the head of the Probability and Statistics team of
the Institut Élie Cartan since September 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid227">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay was a member of the Administration Council of the SMAI
until June 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid228">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay continued to chair the Scientific Council of the French
Applied Math. Society SMAI.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid229">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay served as a member of the scientific council of the
Complex System academy of the UCA Idex.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid230">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay is serveing as a member of the committee in charge of
preparing the application of Paris to the International Congress of
Mathematicians 2022.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid231" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Expertise</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid232">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat reported on an application submitted to CONICYT (Chilean Funding Agency).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid233">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu has been a member of the Committee for junior permanent research positions of Inria Nancy - Grand Est.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid234">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay reported on applications to National Science Centre of Poland.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid235">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay participated in a Professor position recruitment committee at Université de Lorraine.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid236" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Research Administration</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid237">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy is an elected member of the Inria Evaluation Board.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid238">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy has been a member of the DTK-Committee.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid239">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat is a member of the <i>Commission de Développement Technologique</i> and the <i>Commission Information
Scientifique et Technique</i> of Inria Nancy - Grand Est, a subsitute member of the <i>Comité de Centre</i> of Inria Nancy - Grand
Est (until Nov. 2016), <i>Responsable Scientifique</i> for the library of Mathematics of the IECL, member of the <i>Conseil du
laboratoire</i> of IECL (as <i>responsable scientifique</i> of the library). He is also local correspondent of the COERLE
(<i>Comité Opérationel d'Évaluation des Risques Légaux et Éthiques</i>) for the Inria Research Center of Nancy - Grand
Est. This year, together with Aline Wagner (Inria Nancy - Grand Est), he finished to write the new version of the application form
for research approval by the COERLE.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid240">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu is a member of the <i>Bureau du Comité de Projets</i> of Inria Nancy - Grand Est, and of the <i>Comité de
Projet</i> of Inria Nancy - Grand Est.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid241">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay is a member of the COMIPERS of Inria Nancy Grand-Est and of <i>Commission des thèses</i> of the Institut Élie Cartan
(Nancy).</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid242" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Teaching - Supervision - Juries</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid243" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Teaching</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid244">
            <p noindent="true">Master: M. Bossy, <i>Continuous time stochastic models for quantitative Finance</i>, 30h, M2 IMAFA (Informatique et
Mathématiques Appliquées à la Finance et à l'Assurance), École Polytechnique Universitaire, Univ. Nice - Sophia
Antipolis, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid245">
            <p noindent="true">Master : M. Bossy, <i>Risk on energetic financial markets</i>, 27h, Master Spécialisé, Ingénierie et Gestion de
l'Énergie, Mine ParisTech, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid246">
            <p noindent="true">Master : M. Bossy <i>Stochastic Particle Methods for PDEs</i>, 18h, M2 Probabilité et Applications, Université Pierre
et Marie Curie, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid247">
            <p noindent="true">PhD-level lectures : M. Bossy <i>McKean SDEs and related stochastic methods for PDEs</i>, 18h, University of Edinburgh (UK).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid248">
            <p noindent="true">PhD-level lectures : M. Bossy <i>Stochastic numerical methods for turbulence</i>, Winter school Numerics for Stochastic Partial
Differential Equations and their Applications, 10h, at RICAM - University of Linz.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid249">
            <p noindent="true">Master: N. Champagnat, <i>Introduction
to Quantitative Finance</i>, 18h, M1, École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid250">
            <p noindent="true">Master: N. Champagnat, <i>Introduction to Quantitative Finance</i>, 13.5h, M2, École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid251">
            <p noindent="true">Master: N. Champagnat, <i>Chaînes de Markov</i>, 22.5h, M2 “double diplôme” Mathématiques et Applications - École
Supérieure des Sciences et de Technologie de Hammam Sousse, Tunisie (lieu des cours) - Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid252">
            <p noindent="true">Master: M. Deaconu, <i>Équations différentielles stochastiques : résolution numérique et applications</i>, 21h, M2,
École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid253">
            <p noindent="true">Master: M. Deaconu, <i>Modélisation stochastique</i>, 30h, M2, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid254">
            <p noindent="true">Master: M. Deaconu, <i>Simulation Monte Carlo</i>, 24h, M1, Faculté de Droit, Sciences Economiques et Gestion, Université
de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid255">
            <p noindent="true">Master: C. Fritsch, <i>Introduction à la finance quantitative</i>, 3h, M1, École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid256">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: C. Fritsch, <i>Décision et Prévision Statistiques</i>, 20h, L3, École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid257">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: C. Fritsch, <i>Supervision d'un projet de recherche</i>, 6h, M2, École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid258">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: B. Henry, <i>Statistiques</i>, 20h, L3, École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid259">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: B. Henry, <i>Probabilités</i>, 36h, L3, École des Mines de Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid260">
            <p noindent="true">Master: A. Lejay, <i>Simulation des marchés financiers</i>, 28.5h, M2, Université de Lorraine (Metz), France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid261">
            <p noindent="true">Master: P. Pigato, <i>Calcul Intégral</i>, 15h, M1, Université de Lorraine (Nancy), France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid262">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: K. Salhi, <i>Mathématiques Appliquées et Probabilités</i>, 24h, L3, Télécom Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid263">
            <p noindent="true">Master: K. Salhi, <i>Statistiques et analyse de données</i>, 20h, M1, Télécom Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid264">
            <p noindent="true">Master: K. Salhi, <i>Probabilités et Statistiques</i>, 20h, M1,
ENSEM Nancy, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid265">
            <p noindent="true">Master: D. Talay <i>Invariant measures of diffusion
processes</i>, 18h, M2 Probabilité et Applications, Université
Paris 6, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid266">
            <p noindent="true">Master: E. Tanré (courses) and M. Tomasevic (exercices), <i>Advanced Numerics for Computational Finance</i>, 30h (20h + 10h),
M2, UCA (Mathmods Erasmus Mundus), France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid267">
            <p noindent="true">Master: E. Tanré, <i>Mathematical Methods for Neurosciences</i>, 37h, M2, ENS - Master MVA / Paris 6 - Master Maths-Bio,
France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid268">
            <p noindent="true">Master: E.Tanré (courses) and A. Richard (practical classes) <i>Numerical probability for mathematical finance</i>, 20h (8h +
12h), M2, EPU (Master IMAFA), France.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid269" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Supervision</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid270">
            <p noindent="true">PhD: Maxime Bonelli, <i>Behavioral finance approach to risk assessment in quantitative portfolio management</i>, Univ. Nice
Sophia Antipolis, September 2016, M. Bossy.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid271">
            <p noindent="true">PhD : Benoît Henry, <i>Processus de branchements non markoviens en dynamique et génétique des populations</i>, Univ.
Lorraine, 17/11/2016, Nicolas Champagnat, D. Ritchie (EPI <span class="smallcap" align="left">Capsid</span>).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid272">
            <p noindent="true">PhD : Khaled Salhi, <i>Risques extrêmes en finance : analyse et modélisation</i>, Univ. Lorraine, 05/12/2016, M. Deaconu and
A. Lejay.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid273">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Antoine Brault, <i>Formules de Trotter-Kato pour les trajectoires rugueuses</i>, Université Toulouse 3, L.
Coutin (U. Toulouse 3), A. Lejay.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid274">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Baldwin Dumortier, <i>Contrôle acoustique des éoliennes</i>, October 2014, M. Deaconu and E. Vincent (EPI
<span class="smallcap" align="left">Multispeech</span>).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid275">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Pascal Helson, <i>Plasticity in networks of spikking neurons in interaction</i>, October 2016, E. Tanré and
R. Veltz (<span class="smallcap" align="left">MathNeuro</span> Inria team).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid276">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Kouadio Jean Claude Kouaho, <i>Modélisations stochastique et déterministe de croissance de tumeurs
cancéreuses</i>, Mar. 2016, N. Champagnat, Pierre Vallois (EPI <span class="smallcap" align="left">Bigs</span>, Modest N'Zi (UFHB, Abidjan).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid277">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Radu Maftei, <i>A stochastic approach to colloidal particle agglomeration in turbulent flows</i>, November
2014, M. Bossy.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid278">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Hernán Mardones, <i>Numerical solutions of stochastic differential equations with multiplicative noise</i>,
Universidad de Concepción, A. Lejay, C. Mora (U. Concepción).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid279">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Milica Tomasevic, <i>Stochastic approaches
to
Keller–Segel equations</i>, October 2015, D. Talay.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid280" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Juries</bodyTitle>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid281">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy served as a referee for the Ph.D. theses of Anthony LE CAVIL, <i>Représentation probabiliste de type progressif
d'EDP nonlinéaires nonconservatives et algorithmes particulaires associés. </i>Université Paris Saclay, December 9, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid282">
            <p noindent="true">M. Bossy served as an examiner for the Ph.D. thesis of Ahmed MTIRAOUI , <i>EDS Progressives Rétrogrades couplées
contrôlées, EDDS Rétrogrades et EDP Stochastiques</i>. Université de Toulon, November the 25th, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid283">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat served as a referee for the Ph.D. theses of Elma Nessar, <i>Modèles probabilistes de l'évolution d'une
population dans un environnement variable</i>, Univ. Aix-Marseille, July 4, 2016, and of Joseba Dalmau, <i>La quasi-espèce pour
une population finie</i>, Univ. Orsay, November 25, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid284">
            <p noindent="true">N. Champagnat served as an examiner for the Ph.D. thesis of Lucas Mercier, <i>Grands graphes et grand arbres aléatoires :
Analyse du comportement asymptotique</i>, Univ. Lorraine, May 11, 2016, and of Benoît Henry, <i>Processus de branchements non
markoviens en dynamique et génétique des populations</i>, Univ. Lorraine, November 17, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid285">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay served as a referee for the Ph.D. theses of Sarav Mazzonetto, <i>On the exact simulation of (Skew) Brownian
Diffusions with Discontinuous Drift</i>, Potsdam Universität / Université Lille 1, November 2016, of Anis Al Gerbi,
<i>Ninomiya-Victoir scheme: strong convergence, asymptotics for the normalized error and multilevel Monte Carlo methods</i>,
Université Paris-Est, October 2016, and of Joseph El Maalouf, <i>Méthodes de Monte Carlo stratifiées pour la simulation des
chaînes de Markov</i>, Université de Grenoble / Université Saint Joseph de Beyrouth, December 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid286">
            <p noindent="true">A. Lejay served as an examiner for the Habilitation Thesis of Pierre Étoré, <i>Quelques contributions à l'étude et à la
simulation des diffusions asymétriques</i>, Université de Grenoble, December 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid287">
            <p noindent="true">M. Deaconu and A. Lejay served as examiners for the Ph.D. thesis of Khaled Salhi, <i>Risques extrêmes en finance : analyse
et modélisation</i>, Université de Lorraine, December 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid288">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay chaired the Ph.D. thesis jury of Ahmed Mtiraoui,
<i>Equations différentielles stochastique rétrogrades
progressives et leurs applications aux théories de contrôles</i>,
Université de Toulon.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid289">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay served as a referee for the Ph.D. theses of Daoud
Ounaissi, <i>Méthodes Quasi Monte-Carlo et Monte-Carlo 
applications aux calculs des estimateurs Lasso et Lasso bayésien</i>,
université de Lille I; and of Ahmed Bel Hadj Ayed <i>Robustesse de
la stratégie de trading optimale</i>, École Centrale Paris;</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid290">
            <p noindent="true">D. Talay chaired the Habilitation à Diriger les Recherches
juries of Christophette Blanhet-Scalliet, <i>Contribution à
l'analyse des risques financiers : risque de crédit, asymétrie
d'information, analyse chartiste</i>, École Centrale de Lyon, and of
Pierre Étoré, <i>Quelques contributions à l'étude et à la
simulation des diffusions asymétriques</i>, INP Grenoble.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid291" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Popularization</bodyTitle>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid292">
          <p noindent="true">D. Talay participated in a scientific France Culture radio
program in December.</p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </diffusion>
  <biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" numero="10" titre="Bibliography">
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid50" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:beznea:hal-00948876">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.spa.2014.11.016"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00948876"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Branching processes for the fragmentation equation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Lucian</foreName>
            <surname>Beznea</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp75760">
            <foreName>Oana</foreName>
            <surname>Lupascu</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Stochastic Processes and their Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">125</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1861-1885</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00948876" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00948876</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid51" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:bossy:hal-00875040">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00875040"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Lagrangian stochastic models with specular boundary condition</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
            <foreName>Mireille</foreName>
            <surname>Bossy</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp92136">
            <foreName>Jean-Francois</foreName>
            <surname>Jabir</surname>
            <initial>J.-F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="j">Journal of Functional Analysis</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">268</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1309–1381</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00875040" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00875040</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid52" type="incollection" rend="refer" n="refercite:bossy:hal-01162832">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-1-4939-2733-3_13"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01162832"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Game theory analysis for carbon auction market through electricity market coupling</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
            <foreName>Mireille</foreName>
            <surname>Bossy</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp94776">
            <foreName>Nadia</foreName>
            <surname>Maïzi</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="hephaistos-2014-idm25520">
            <foreName>Odile</foreName>
            <surname>Pourtallier</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael</foreName>
            <surname>Ludkovski</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ronnie</foreName>
            <surname>Sircar</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rene</foreName>
            <surname>Aid</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Commodities, Energy and Environmental Finance</title>
        <title level="s">Fields Institute Communications</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">74</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">335-370</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal-mines-paristech.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01162832" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal-mines-paristech.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01162832</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid53" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:MR2834712">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00440-010-0292-9"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Polymorphic evolution sequence and evolutionary branching</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sylvie</foreName>
            <surname>Méléard</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Probab. Theory Related Fields</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">151</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1-2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">45–94</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00440-010-0292-9" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>dx.<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1007/<allowbreak/>s00440-010-0292-9</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid54" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:champagnat:hal-00973509">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00440-014-0611-7"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00973509"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Exponential convergence to quasi-stationary distribution and Q-process</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="j">Probability Theory and Related Fields</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00973509" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00973509</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">46 pages</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid55" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:coutin:hal-00722900">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00722900"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Perturbed linear rough differential equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laure</foreName>
            <surname>Coutin</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Annales mathématiques Blaise Pascal</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">21</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2014</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">103-150</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00722900" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00722900</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid56" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:deaconu:hal-00636056">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1214/12-AAP900"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Hitting time for Bessel processes—walk on moving spheres algorithm (WoMS)</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp90680">
            <foreName>Samuel</foreName>
            <surname>Herrmann</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Ann. Appl. Probab.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">23</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2259–2289</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1214/12-AAP900" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>dx.<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1214/<allowbreak/>12-AAP900</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid57" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:delarue:hal-00747565">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00747565"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Global solvability of a networked integrate-and-fire model of McKean-Vlasov type</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp89232">
            <foreName>François</foreName>
            <surname>Delarue</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="neuromathcomp-2014-idp65832">
            <foreName>James</foreName>
            <surname>Inglis</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp98528">
            <foreName>Sylvain</foreName>
            <surname>Rubenthaler</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
            <foreName>Etienne</foreName>
            <surname>Tanré</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="j">Annals of Applied Probability</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">25</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2096–2133</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00747565" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00747565</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">Version 4: shortened version</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid59" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:inglis:hal-01069398">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1137/140989042"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01069398"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Mean-field limit of a stochastic particle system smoothly interacting through threshold hitting-times and applications to neural networks with dendritic component</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="neuromathcomp-2014-idp65832">
            <foreName>James</foreName>
            <surname>Inglis</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm26736">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Talay</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Mathematical Analysis</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">47</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">15</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">3884–3916</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01069398" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01069398</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid58" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:lejay:hal-00781447">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00781447"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">The snapping out Brownian motion</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Annals of Applied Probability</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00781447" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00781447</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid3" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:baar:hal-01188189">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01188189"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">From stochastic, individual-based models to the canonical equation of adaptive dynamics - In one step</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Martina</foreName>
            <surname>Baar</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anton</foreName>
            <surname>Bovier</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00134">
        <idno type="issn">1050-5164</idno>
        <title level="j">The Annals of Applied Probability : an official journal of the institute of mathematical statistics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">Online first</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01188189" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01188189</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid16" subtype="nonparu-n" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:beznea:hal-01216137">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01216137"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Stochastic equation of fragmentation and branching processes related to avalanches</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Lucian</foreName>
            <surname>Beznea</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp75760">
            <foreName>Oana</foreName>
            <surname>Lupascu</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01268">
        <idno type="issn">0022-4715</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Statistical Physics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">162</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">824-841</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01216137" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01216137</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">Accepté pour publication</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid2" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:bossy:hal-01401140">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.5802/smai-jcm.13"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401140"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Modeling the wind circulation around mills with a Lagrangian stochastic approach </title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
            <foreName>Mireille</foreName>
            <surname>Bossy</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jose</foreName>
            <surname>Espina</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jacques</foreName>
            <surname>Morice</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Cristian</foreName>
            <surname>Paris</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="moise-2014-idp92432">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Rousseau</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid03021">
        <idno type="issn">2426-8399</idno>
        <title level="j">SMAI Journal of Computational Mathematics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">177-214</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401140" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401140</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid0" subtype="nonparu-v" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:bossy:hal-01185353">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01185353"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Strong convergence of the symmetrized Milstein scheme for some CEV-like SDEs</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
            <foreName>Mireille</foreName>
            <surname>Bossy</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Hector Olivero</foreName>
            <surname>Quinteros</surname>
            <initial>H. O.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00233">
        <idno type="issn">1350-7265</idno>
        <title level="j">Bernoulli</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01185353" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01185353</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid6" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:campillo:hal-01205467">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00285-016-1012-6"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01205467"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Links between deterministic and stochastic approaches for invasion in growth-fragmentation-death models</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="lemon-2014-idp63056">
            <foreName>Fabien</foreName>
            <surname>Campillo</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="modemic-2014-idp74808">
            <foreName>Coralie</foreName>
            <surname>Fritsch</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01193">
        <idno type="issn">0303-6812</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Biology</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01205467" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01205467</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid11" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01202732">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1214/16-EJP4577"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01202732"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Moments of the frequency spectrum of a splitting tree with neutral Poissonian mutations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp81928">
            <foreName>Benoît</foreName>
            <surname>Henry</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00517">
        <idno type="issn">1083-6489</idno>
        <title level="j">Electronic Journal of Probability</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">21</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">53</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1-34</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01202732" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01202732</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid8" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-00973509">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00440-014-0611-7"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00973509"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Exponential convergence to quasi-stationary distribution and Q-process</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01607">
        <idno type="issn">0178-8051</idno>
        <title level="j">Probability Theory and Related Fields</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">164</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">243-283</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00973509" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00973509</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">46 pages</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid49" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:claisse:hal-01108657">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1137/151004252"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01108657"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A pseudo-Markov property for controlled diffusion processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp80704">
            <foreName>Julien</foreName>
            <surname>Claisse</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm26736">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Talay</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Xiaolu</foreName>
            <surname>Tan</surname>
            <initial>X.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01729">
        <idno type="issn">0363-0129</idno>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Control and Optimization</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">54</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1017-1029</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01108657" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01108657</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid46" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:deluigi:hal-00746872">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00746872"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Adaptive numerical integration and control variates for pricing Basket Options</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>De Luigi</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="mathrisk-2014-idp76808">
            <foreName>Jérôme</foreName>
            <surname>Lelong</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp93520">
            <foreName>Sylvain</foreName>
            <surname>Maire</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00170">
        <idno type="issn">0168-9274</idno>
        <title level="j">Applied Numerical Mathematics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">100</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">17</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00746872" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00746872</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid17" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:deaconu:hal-00933198">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00933198"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Simulation of hitting times for Bessel processes with non integer dimension</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp90680">
            <foreName>Samuel</foreName>
            <surname>Herrmann</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00233">
        <idno type="issn">1350-7265</idno>
        <title level="j">Bernoulli journal</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00933198" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00933198</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid28" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:herrmann:hal-01110387">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1137/151006172"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01110387"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">The first-passage time of the Brownian motion to a curved boundary: an algorithmic approach</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp90680">
            <foreName>Samuel</foreName>
            <surname>Herrmann</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
            <foreName>Etienne</foreName>
            <surname>Tanré</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01739">
        <idno type="issn">1064-8275</idno>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">38</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">20</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01110387" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01110387</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid43" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:inglis:hal-01169697">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1137/15M102856X"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01169697"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A general framework for stochastic traveling waves and patterns, with application to neural field equations</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="neuromathcomp-2014-idp65832">
            <foreName>James</foreName>
            <surname>Inglis</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="neuromathcomp-2014-idp69792">
            <foreName>James</foreName>
            <surname>Maclaurin</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01731">
        <idno type="issn">1536-0040</idno>
        <title level="j">SIAM Journal on Applied Dynamical Systems</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">15</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">195-234</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01169697" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01169697</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">43 pages, 3 figures</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid39" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:lejay:hal-00781447">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1214/15-AAP1131"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00781447"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">The snapping out Brownian motion</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00134">
        <idno type="issn">1050-5164</idno>
        <title level="j">Annals of Applied Probability</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">26</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1727-1742</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00781447" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00781447</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid40" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:lejay:hal-01003853">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.jcp.2016.03.003"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01003853"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Simulating Diffusion Processes in Discontinuous Media: Benchmark Tests</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="sage-2014-idp65592">
            <foreName>Géraldine</foreName>
            <surname>Pichot</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01098">
        <idno type="issn">0021-9991</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Computational Physics</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">314</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">348-413</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01003853" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01003853</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid44" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:maire:hal-00809203">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.matcom.2015.09.008"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00809203"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Stochastic finite differences for elliptic diffusion equations in stratified domains</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp93520">
            <foreName>Sylvain</foreName>
            <surname>Maire</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="opale-2014-idm26928">
            <foreName>Giang</foreName>
            <surname>Nguyen</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01399">
        <idno type="issn">0378-4754</idno>
        <title level="j">Mathematics and Computers in Simulation</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">121</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00809203" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00809203</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid38" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:michel:hal-01098096">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1080/1350486X.2016.1164608"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01098096"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Liquidity costs: a new numerical methodology and an empirical study</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Michel</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Victor</foreName>
            <surname>Reutenauer</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm26736">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Talay</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
            <foreName>Etienne</foreName>
            <surname>Tanré</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid02827">
        <idno type="issn">1350-486X</idno>
        <title level="j">Applied Mathematical Finance</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01098096" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01098096</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid47" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:richard:hal-01236156">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1214/16-ECP4727"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01236156"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Increment stationarity of <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mi>L</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></math></formula>-indexed stochastic processes: spectral representation and characterization</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp77000">
            <foreName>Alexandre</foreName>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00513">
        <idno type="issn">1083-589X</idno>
        <title level="j">Electronic Communications in Probability</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">21</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">15</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01236156" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01236156</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid36" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:salhi:hal-01095299">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.physa.2016.05.002"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01095299"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Regime switching model for financial data: empirical risk analysis</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp86976">
            <foreName>Khaled</foreName>
            <surname>Salhi</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Navet</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01579">
        <idno type="issn">0378-4371</idno>
        <title level="j">Physica A</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">461</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">148–157</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01095299" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01095299</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid1" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bossy:hal-01400678">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01400678"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A stochastic approach to colloidal particle collision/agglomeration</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp65448">
            <foreName>Mireille</foreName>
            <surname>Bossy</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp83160">
            <foreName>Radu</foreName>
            <surname>Maftei</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Profeta</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Minier</surname>
            <initial>J.-P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">ICMF</title>
        <loc>Firenze, Italy</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01400678" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01400678</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625409">
          <title>International Conference on Multiphase Flow</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICMF</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid45" type="techreport" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01305032">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01305032"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Méthodes de calcul de la Value-at-Risk et de la Conditional Value-at-Risk</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="institution">Inria Nancy - Grand Est (Villers-lès-Nancy, France)</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>January</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01305032" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01305032</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Contract</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid21" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:azais:hal-01360650">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01360650"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Inference for conditioned Galton-Watson trees from their Harris path</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="virtual_plants-2014-idp128736">
            <foreName>Romain</foreName>
            <surname>Azaïs</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="cqfd-2015-idp65304">
            <foreName>Alexandre</foreName>
            <surname>Genadot</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp81928">
            <foreName>Benoît</foreName>
            <surname>Henry</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01360650" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01360650</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid25" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:bally:hal-01407409">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01407409"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Diffusions under a local strong Hörmander condition. Part I: density estimates</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="mathrisk-2014-idp69672">
            <foreName>Vlad</foreName>
            <surname>Bally</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Lucia</foreName>
            <surname>Caramellino</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2015-idp77288">
            <foreName>Paolo</foreName>
            <surname>Pigato</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01407409" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01407409</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid26" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:bally:hal-01407420">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01407420"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Diffusions under a local strong Hörmander condition. Part II: tube estimates</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="mathrisk-2014-idp69672">
            <foreName>Vlad</foreName>
            <surname>Bally</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Lucia</foreName>
            <surname>Caramellino</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2015-idp77288">
            <foreName>Paolo</foreName>
            <surname>Pigato</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01407420" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01407420</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid48" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:bonino:hal-01408495">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01408495"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">A multivariate model for financial indices and an algorithm for detection of jumps in the volatility</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mario</foreName>
            <surname>Bonino</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Matteo</foreName>
            <surname>Camelia</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2015-idp77288">
            <foreName>Paolo</foreName>
            <surname>Pigato</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01408495" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01408495</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">20 pages, 22 figures</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid7" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:campillo:hal-01254053">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01254053"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">On the variations of the principal eigenvalue and the probability of survival with respect to a parameter in growth-fragmentation-death models</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="lemon-2014-idp63056">
            <foreName>Fabien</foreName>
            <surname>Campillo</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="modemic-2014-idp74808">
            <foreName>Coralie</foreName>
            <surname>Fritsch</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01254053" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01254053</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid5" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01349663">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01349663"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">On the link between infinite horizon control and quasi-stationary distributions</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp80704">
            <foreName>Julien</foreName>
            <surname>Claisse</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01349663" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01349663</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid10" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01293622">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01293622"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Exponential convergence to quasi-stationary distribution for multi-dimensional diffusion processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Abdoulaye</foreName>
            <surname>Coulibaly-Pasquier</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01293622" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01293622</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid12" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01395731">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01395731"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Population processes with unbounded extinction rate conditioned to non-extinction</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01395731" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01395731</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid41" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01166960">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01166960"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Uniform convergence of conditional distributions for absorbed one-dimensional diffusions</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01166960" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01166960</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid13" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01290222">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01290222"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Uniform convergence of penalized time-inhomogeneous Markov processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01290222" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01290222</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid9" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:champagnat:hal-01395727">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01395727"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Uniform convergence to the Q-process</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01395727" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01395727</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid20" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:cloez:hal-01371591">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01371591"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Gaussian approximations for chemostat models in finite and infinite dimensions</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="modemic-2014-idp66832">
            <foreName>Bertrand</foreName>
            <surname>Cloez</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="modemic-2014-idp74808">
            <foreName>Coralie</foreName>
            <surname>Fritsch</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01371591" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01371591</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid23" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:coutin:hal-00875670">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-00875670"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Sensitivity of rough differential equations: an approach through the Omega lemma</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laure</foreName>
            <surname>Coutin</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-00875670" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-00875670</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid18" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:deaconu:hal-01380365">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01380365"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Initial-boundary value problem for the heat equation - A stochastic algorithm</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp90680">
            <foreName>Samuel</foreName>
            <surname>Herrmann</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01380365" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01380365</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct subtype="nonparu-n" id="tosca-2016-bid33" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:delmoral:hal-01083297">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01083297"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Exponential mixing properties for time inhomogeneous diffusion processes with killing</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="cqfd-2016-idp114784">
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Del Moral</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01083297" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01083297</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">To appear in Bernoulli Journal</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid19" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:dumortier:hal-01393125">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01393125"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Efficient optimisation of wind power under acoustic constraints</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="multispeech-2014-idp84320">
            <foreName>Baldwin</foreName>
            <surname>Dumortier</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="multispeech-2014-idp68752">
            <foreName>Emmanuel</foreName>
            <surname>Vincent</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm28208">
            <foreName>Madalina</foreName>
            <surname>Deaconu</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrice</foreName>
            <surname>Cornu</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01393125" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01393125</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid42" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:fritsch:hal-01413638">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01413638"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">A numerical approach to determine mutant invasion fitness and evolutionary singular strategies</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="modemic-2014-idp74808">
            <foreName>Coralie</foreName>
            <surname>Fritsch</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="lemon-2014-idp63056">
            <foreName>Fabien</foreName>
            <surname>Campillo</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Otso</foreName>
            <surname>Ovaskainen</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>December</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01413638" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01413638</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid29" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:guiraud:hal-01370609">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01370609"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Stability of synchronization under stochastic perturbations in leaky integrate and fire neural networks of finite size</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Guiraud</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
            <foreName>Etienne</foreName>
            <surname>Tanré</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01370609" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01370609</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid22" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:henry:hal-01202095">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01202095"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Central limit theorem for supercritical binary homogeneous Crump-Mode-Jagers processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp81928">
            <foreName>Benoît</foreName>
            <surname>Henry</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01202095" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01202095</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid24" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:lejay:hal-01319319">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01319319"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Estimation of the biais parameter of the Skew Random Walk and application to the Skew Brownian motion</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp69352">
            <foreName>Antoine</foreName>
            <surname>Lejay</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01319319" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01319319</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid34" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:ocafrain:hal-01338421">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01338421"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Non-failable approximation method for conditioned distributions</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>William</foreName>
            <surname>Oçafrain</surname>
            <initial>W.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp72040">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Villemonais</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01338421" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01338421</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid32" type="mastersthesis" rend="year" n="cite:papic:hal-01369707">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01369707"/>
      <monogr x-international-audience="yes">
        <title level="m">States Reduction on Markov Processes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alexis</foreName>
            <surname>Papic</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Inria Sophia Antipolis ; Université Pierre et Marie Curie</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01369707" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01369707</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Masters thesis</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid31" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:reutenauer:hal-01371448">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01371448"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">An unbiased Monte Carlo estimator for derivatives. Application to CIR</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Victor</foreName>
            <surname>Reutenauer</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp70792">
            <foreName>Etienne</foreName>
            <surname>Tanré</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01371448" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01371448</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid27" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:richard:hal-01323288">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01323288"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Hölder continuity in the Hurst parameter of functionals of Stochastic Differential Equations driven by fractional Brownian motion</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp77000">
            <foreName>Alexandre</foreName>
            <surname>Richard</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idm26736">
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Talay</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01323288" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01323288</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid37" type="unpublished" rend="year" n="cite:salhi:hal-01322698">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01322698"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">European options pricing and risk measurement under Exponential Lévy models - a practical guide</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp86976">
            <foreName>Khaled</foreName>
            <surname>Salhi</surname>
            <initial>K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>November</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01322698" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01322698</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">working paper or preprint</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid30" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:BPR06">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Retrospective exact simulation of diffusion sample paths with applications</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>A.</foreName>
            <surname>Beskos</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>O.</foreName>
            <surname>Papaspiliopoulos</surname>
            <initial>O.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>G. O.</foreName>
            <surname>Roberts</surname>
            <initial>G. O.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Bernoulli</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">6</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2006</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">1077–1098</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid4" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:MR2834712">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00440-010-0292-9"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Polymorphic evolution sequence and evolutionary branching</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="tosca-2014-idp66856">
            <foreName>Nicolas</foreName>
            <surname>Champagnat</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sylvie</foreName>
            <surname>Méléard</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Probab. Theory Related Fields</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">151</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1-2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">45–94</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00440-010-0292-9" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>dx.<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1007/<allowbreak/>s00440-010-0292-9</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid14" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:MR1819122">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/S0246-0203(00)01064-5"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">On the stability of interacting processes with applications to filtering and genetic algorithms</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="cqfd-2016-idp114784">
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Del Moral</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alice</foreName>
            <surname>Guionnet</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Ann. Inst. H. Poincaré Probab. Statist.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">37</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2001</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">155–194</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0246-0203(00)01064-5" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>dx.<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1016/<allowbreak/>S0246-0203(00)01064-5</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid15" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:MR1988460">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">On the stability of nonlinear Feynman-Kac semigroups</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="cqfd-2016-idp114784">
            <foreName>Pierre</foreName>
            <surname>Del Moral</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Laurent</foreName>
            <surname>Miclo</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Ann. Fac. Sci. Toulouse Math. (6)</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">11</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2002</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">135–175</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://www.numdam.org/item?id=AFST_2002_6_11_2_135_0" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>numdam.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>item?id=AFST_2002_6_11_2_135_0</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="tosca-2016-bid35" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:MR3332847">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.spa.2015.02.014"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Forward-backward stochastic differential systems associated to Navier-Stokes equations in the whole space</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Freddy</foreName>
            <surname>Delbaen</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jinniao</foreName>
            <surname>Qiu</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Shanjian</foreName>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Stochastic Process. Appl.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">125</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">7</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2516–2561</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.spa.2015.02.014" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>dx.<allowbreak/>doi.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>10.<allowbreak/>1016/<allowbreak/>j.<allowbreak/>spa.<allowbreak/>2015.<allowbreak/>02.<allowbreak/>014</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
  </biblio>
</raweb>
