<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<raweb xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="en" year="2016">
  <identification id="veridis" isproject="true">
    <shortname>VERIDIS</shortname>
    <projectName>Modeling and Verification of Distributed Algorithms and Systems</projectName>
    <theme-de-recherche>Proofs and Verification</theme-de-recherche>
    <domaine-de-recherche>Algorithmics, Programming, Software and Architecture</domaine-de-recherche>
    <urlTeam>http://veridis.loria.fr/</urlTeam>
    <structure_exterieure type="Labs">
      <libelle>Laboratoire lorrain de recherche en informatique et ses applications (LORIA)</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>CNRS</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>Max Planck Institut für Informatik de Saarbrücken</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <structure_exterieure type="Organism">
      <libelle>Université de Lorraine</libelle>
    </structure_exterieure>
    <header_dates_team>Creation of the Team: 2010 January 01, updated into Project-Team: 2012 July 01</header_dates_team>
    <LeTypeProjet>Project-Team</LeTypeProjet>
    <keywordsSdN>
      <term>2.1.7. - Distributed programming</term>
      <term>2.1.11. - Proof languages</term>
      <term>2.4. - Verification, reliability, certification</term>
      <term>2.4.1. - Analysis</term>
      <term>2.4.2. - Model-checking</term>
      <term>2.4.3. - Proofs</term>
      <term>7.4. - Logic in Computer Science</term>
      <term>7.6. - Computer Algebra</term>
    </keywordsSdN>
    <keywordsSecteurs>
      <term>6.1. - Software industry</term>
      <term>6.3.2. - Network protocols</term>
      <term>6.6. - Embedded systems</term>
    </keywordsSecteurs>
    <UR name="Nancy"/>
  </identification>
  <team id="uid1">
    <person key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
      <firstname>Jasmin Christian</firstname>
      <lastname>Blanchette</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, Starting Research Position</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
      <firstname>Stephan</firstname>
      <lastname>Merz</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Inria, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idm25184">
      <firstname>Thomas</firstname>
      <lastname>Sturm</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>CNRS, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp67056">
      <firstname>Uwe</firstname>
      <lastname>Waldmann</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Max-Planck Institut für Informatik, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
      <firstname>Christoph</firstname>
      <lastname>Weidenbach</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Chercheur</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Team leader, Max-Planck Institut für Informatik, Senior Researcher</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp69864">
      <firstname>Marie</firstname>
      <lastname>Duflot-Kremer</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
      <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
      <lastname>Fontaine</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Associate Professor</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
      <firstname>Dominique</firstname>
      <lastname>Méry</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, Professor</moreinfo>
      <hdr>oui</hdr>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2016-idp162592">
      <firstname>Martin</firstname>
      <lastname>Strecker</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Enseignant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Toulouse III, Associate Professor, Inria secondment since Sep 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="algorille-2014-idp109184">
      <firstname>Gabriel</firstname>
      <lastname>Corona</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="deducteam-2014-idp99360">
      <firstname>Simon</firstname>
      <lastname>Cruanes</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="algorille-2014-idp116736">
      <firstname>Matthieu</firstname>
      <lastname>Nicolas</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2015-idp78232">
      <firstname>Martin</firstname>
      <lastname>Riener</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Technique</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, MSR-Inria Joint Centre</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2015-idp79464">
      <firstname>Gabor</firstname>
      <lastname>Alági</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. des Saarlandes, since Nov 2012</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp75064">
      <firstname>Noran</firstname>
      <lastname>Azmy</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. des Saarlandes, until Aug 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp76312">
      <firstname>Haniel</firstname>
      <lastname>Barbosa</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, since Dec 2013</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp77544">
      <firstname>Martin</firstname>
      <lastname>Bromberger</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. des Saarlandes, since Jul 2014</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2016-idp184800">
      <firstname>Margaux</firstname>
      <lastname>Duroeulx</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, since Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2015-idp86936">
      <firstname>Mathias</firstname>
      <lastname>Fleury</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. des Saarlandes, since Oct 2015</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2015-idp89424">
      <firstname>Souad</firstname>
      <lastname>Kherroubi</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. Lorraine, since Jan 2015</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp81320">
      <firstname>Marek</firstname>
      <lastname>Košta</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. des Saarlandes, until Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="madynes-2016-idp224432">
      <firstname>Nicolas</firstname>
      <lastname>Schnepf</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria, since Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp85200">
      <firstname>Marco</firstname>
      <lastname>Voigt</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. des Saarlandes, since Nov 2013</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp86448">
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
      <lastname>Wand</lastname>
      <categoryPro>PhD</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Univ. des Saarlandes, since Feb 2011</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2016-idp201920">
      <firstname>Ilina</firstname>
      <lastname>Stoilkovska</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>TU Wien, visitor, Sep–Oct 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2016-idp204432">
      <firstname>Tung</firstname>
      <lastname>Vu Xuan</lastname>
      <categoryPro>AutreCategorie</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>JAIST, visitor, since May 2016</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp99584">
      <firstname>Sophie</firstname>
      <lastname>Drouot</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Inria</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="carte-2014-idp104592">
      <firstname>Martine</firstname>
      <lastname>Kuhlmann</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>CNRS</moreinfo>
    </person>
    <person key="veridis-2014-idp103288">
      <firstname>Jennifer</firstname>
      <lastname>Müller</lastname>
      <categoryPro>Assistant</categoryPro>
      <research-centre>Nancy</research-centre>
      <moreinfo>Max-Planck Institut für Informatik</moreinfo>
    </person>
  </team>
  <presentation id="uid2">
    <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid3" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Overall Objectives</bodyTitle>
      <p>The VeriDis project team includes members of the MOSEL group at LORIA, the
computer science laboratory in Nancy, and members of the research group
<i>Automation of Logic</i> at Max-Planck-Institut für Informatik in
Saarbrücken. It is headed by Stephan Merz and Christoph Weidenbach. VeriDis
was created in 2010 as a local research group of Inria Nancy – Grand Est and
has been an Inria project team since July 2012.</p>
      <p>The objectives of VeriDis are to contribute to advances in verification
techniques, including automated and
interactive theorem proving, and to make them available for the formal
development and analysis of concurrent and distributed algorithms and systems, within the
framework of mathematically precise and practically applicable development
methods. We intend to assist designers of algorithms and systems in carrying out
formally proved developments, where proofs of relevant properties, as well as
bugs, can be found with a high degree of automation.</p>
      <p>Verification techniques based on theorem proving are already having
substantial impact. In particular, they have been successfully applied to the
verification and analysis of sequential programs, often in combination with
static analysis and software model checking. Ideally, systems and their
properties would be specified in high-level, expressive languages, errors in
specifications would be discovered automatically, and finally, full
verification could also be performed completely automatically. Due to the
inherent complexity of the problem, this cannot be achieved in general.
We have, however, observed significant advances in
theorem proving in recent years. We are particularly interested in the
integration of different deduction techniques and tools, such as automated
theorem proving for relevant theories, such as different fragments of
arithmetic. These advances suggest that a substantially higher degree of
automation can be achieved in system verification than what is available in
today's verification tools.</p>
      <p>VeriDis aims at exploiting and further developing automation in system
verification, and at applying its techniques within the context of concurrent and
distributed algorithms, which are by now ubiquitous and whose verification
is a big challenge. Concurrency problems are central for the development and
verification of programs for multi- and many-core architectures, and
distributed computation underlies the paradigms of grid and cloud computing.
The potential of distributed systems for increased resilience to component
failures makes them attractive in many contexts, but also makes formal
verification important and challenging. We aim at moving current research in
this area to a new level of productivity and quality. To give a concrete
example: today the designer of a new distributed protocol may validate it
using testing or model checking. Model checking will help finding bugs, but
can only guarantee properties of a high-level model of the protocol, usually
restricted to finite instances. Testing distributed systems and protocols is
notoriously difficult because corner cases are hard to establish and
reproduce. Also, many testing techniques require an executable, whose
production is expensive and time-consuming, and since an implementation is
needed, errors are found only when they are
expensive to fix. The techniques that we develop aim at automatically
proving significant properties of the protocol already during the design phase.
Our methods mainly target designs and algorithms at high levels of
abstraction; we aim at
components of operating systems, distributed services, and down to the
(mobile) network systems industry.</p>
    </subsection>
  </presentation>
  <fondements id="uid4">
    <bodyTitle>Research Program</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid5" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Automated and Interactive Theorem Proving</bodyTitle>
      <p>The VeriDis team gathers experts in techniques and tools for automatic
deduction and interactive theorem proving, and specialists in methods and
formalisms designed for the development of trustworthy concurrent and
distributed systems and algorithms. Our common objective is twofold: first, we
wish to advance the state of the art in automated and interactive theorem
proving, and their combinations. Second, we work on making the resulting
technology available for the computer-aided verification of distributed
systems and protocols. In particular, our techniques and tools are intended to
support sound methods for the development of trustworthy distributed systems
that scale to algorithms relevant for practical applications.</p>
      <p>VeriDis members from Saarbrücken are developing
<span class="smallcap" align="left">Spass</span> <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid0" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, one of the leading automated theorem
provers for first-order logic based on the superposition calculus
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid1" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
The group also studies general
frameworks for the combination of theories such as the locality principle
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid2" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and automated reasoning mechanisms these
induce.</p>
      <p>In a complementary approach to automated deduction, VeriDis members from Nancy
work on techniques for integrating reasoners for specific theories. They
develop veriT <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid3" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, an SMT (Satisfiability Modulo
Theories <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid4" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) solver that combines decision procedures for
different fragments of first-order logic and that integrates an automatic
theorem prover for full first-order logic. The veriT solver is designed to
produce detailed proofs; this makes it particularly suitable as a component of
a robust cooperation of deduction tools.</p>
      <p>Finally, VeriDis members design effective quantifier elimination
methods and decision procedures for algebraic theories, supported by their
efficient implementation in the Redlog system <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid5" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      <p>An important objective of this line of work is the integration of theories
in automated deduction. Typical theories of interest, including fragments of
arithmetic, are not expressible in first-order logic. We therefore explore
efficient, modular techniques for integrating semantic and syntactic reasoning
methods, develop novel combination results and techniques for quantifier
instantiation. These problems are addressed from both sides, e.g. by
embedding a decision procedure into the superposition framework or by allowing
an SMT solver to accept axiomatizations for plug-in theories. We also develop
specific decision procedures for theories such as non-linear real arithmetic
that are important when reasoning about certain classes of (e.g., real-time)
systems but that also have interesting applications beyond verification.</p>
      <p>We rely on interactive theorem provers for reasoning about specifications at a
high level of abstraction when fully automatic verification is not (yet)
feasible. An interactive proof platform should help verification engineers lay
out the proof structure at a sufficiently high level of abstraction; powerful
automatic plug-ins should then discharge the resulting proof steps. Members of
VeriDis have ample experience in the specification and subsequent
machine-assisted, interactive verification of algorithms. In particular, we
participate in a project at the joint Microsoft Research-Inria Centre in Saclay on the
development of methods and tools for the formal proof of TLA<sup>+</sup> <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid6" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> specifications. Our prover relies on a declarative
proof language, and calls upon several automatic backends
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid7" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. Trust in the correctness of the overall
proof can be ensured when the backends provide justifications that can be
checked by the trusted kernel of a proof assistant. During the development of
a proof, most obligations that are passed to the prover actually fail – for
example, because necessary information is not present in the context or
because the invariant is too weak, and we are interested in explaining failed
proof attempts to the user, in particular through the construction of
counter-models.
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid6" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Formal Methods for Developing and Analyzing Algorithms and Systems</bodyTitle>
      <p>Theorem provers are not used in isolation, but they support the
application of sound methodologies for modeling and verifying systems. In this
respect, members of VeriDis have gained expertise and recognition in making
contributions to formal methods for concurrent and distributed algorithms and
systems <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid8" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid9" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, and in applying them to
concrete use cases. In particular, the concept of <i>refinement</i>
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid10" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid11" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid12" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> in state-based
modeling formalisms is central to our approach because it allows us to present
a rational (re)construction of system development. An important goal in
designing such methods is to establish precise proof obligations many of which
can be discharged by automatic tools. This requires taking into account
specific characteristics of certain classes of systems and tailoring the model
to concrete computational models. Our research in this area is supported by
carrying out case studies for academic and industrial developments. This
activity benefits from and influences the development of our proof tools.</p>
      <p>In this line of work, we investigate specific development and verification
patterns for particular classes of algorithms, in order to reduce the work
associated with their verification. We are also interested in
applications of formal methods and their associated tools to the development
of systems that underlie specific certification requirements in the sense of,
e.g., Common Criteria. Finally, we are interested in the adaptation of model
checking techniques for verifying actual distributed programs, rather than
high-level models.</p>
      <p>Today, the formal verification of a new algorithm is typically the subject of
a PhD thesis, if it is addressed at all. This situation is not sustainable
given the move towards more and more parallelism in mainstream systems:
algorithm developers and system designers must be able to productively use
verification tools for validating their algorithms and implementations. On a
high level, the goal of VeriDis is to make formal verification standard
practice for the development of distributed algorithms and systems, just as
symbolic model checking has become commonplace in the development of embedded
systems and as security analysis for cryptographic protocols is becoming
standard practice today. Although the fundamental problems in distributed
programming are well-known, they pose new challenges in the context of modern
system paradigms, including ad-hoc and overlay networks or peer-to-peer
systems, and they must be integrated for concrete applications.</p>
    </subsection>
  </fondements>
  <domaine id="uid7">
    <bodyTitle>Application Domains</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid8" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Application Domains</bodyTitle>
      <p>Distributed algorithms and protocols are found at all levels of computing
infrastructure, from many-core processors and systems-on-chip to wide-area
networks. We are particularly interested in the verification of algorithms
that are developed for supporting novel computing paradigms, including ad-hoc
networks that underly mobile and low-power computing or overlay networks and
peer-to-peer networking that provide services for telecommunication or cloud
computing services. Computing infrastructure must be highly available and is
ideally invisible to the end user, therefore correctness is crucial. One
should note that standard problems of distributed computing such as consensus,
group membership or leader election have to be reformulated for the dynamic
context of these modern systems. We are not ourselves experts in the design of
distributed algorithms, but we work together with domain experts on designing
formal models of these protocols, and on verifying their properties. These
cooperations help us focus on concrete algorithms and ensure that our work is
relevant to the distributed algorithm community.</p>
      <p>Formal verification techniques can contribute to certifying the
correctness of systems. In particular, they help assert under which
assumptions an algorithm or system functions as required. For example, the
highest levels of the Common Criteria for Information Technology Security
Evaluation encourage the use of formal methods.
While initially the requirements of certified development have mostly been
restricted to safety-critical systems, the cost of unavailable services due to
malfunctioning system components and software provides wider incentives for
verification. For example, we are working on modeling and verifying medical
devices that require closed-loop models of both the system and its
environment.</p>
    </subsection>
  </domaine>
  <highlights id="uid9">
    <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid10" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Highlights of the Year</bodyTitle>
      <p>Jasmin Blanchette was awarded an ERC Starting Grant for his Matryoshka project
aiming at fast interactive verification through strong automation for
higher-order constructs.</p>
      <p>As part of a European network, Pascal Fontaine and Thomas Sturm participate in
a new H2020 Coordination and Support Action. <footnote id="uid11" id-text="1">H2020-FETOPEN-2015-CSA-712689,
<ref xlink:href="http://www.sc-square.org/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>sc-square.<allowbreak/>org/</ref></footnote> In accordance with the distributed
character of Veridis, we are operating nodes at LORIA as well as MPI. Further
nodes are located in Austria (University of Linz), Germany (RWTH Aachen;
University of Kassel), Italy (Fondazione Bruno Kessler; University of Genova),
and the UK (Universties of Bath, Coventry, and Oxford; Maplesoft Europe Ltd.).
The CSA aims at improving the integration of communities, methods, and
software from SMT solving and symbolic computation
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid13" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      <p>Jasmin Blanchette and Stephan Merz were PC chairs and organizers of the 7th
International Conference on Interactive Theorem Proving in Nancy (August
22–27), the main conference of developers and users of proof assistants.</p>
      <subsection id="uid12" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Awards</bodyTitle>
        <p>Mathias Fleury, together with his two supervisors, received the
Best Paper Award at IJCAR 2016 for their work on a formalized SAT solver.</p>
        <p>Together with Andrew J. Reynolds at the University of Iowa, Jasmin Blanchette was
invited to submit a short version of his CADE 2015 paper on a decision
procedure for (co)datatypes to the Sister Conference Best Paper Track of
IJCAI 2016.</p>
        <best>
          <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
        </best>
        <best>
          <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid15" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
        </best>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </highlights>
  <logiciels id="uid13">
    <bodyTitle>New Software and Platforms</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid14" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>The Nunchaku Higher-Order Model Finder</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>Nunchaku is a model finder for higher-order logic, with dedicated support
for various definitional principles. It is designed to work as a backend for
various proof assistants and to use state-of-the-art model finders and other
solvers as backends.</p>
      <p>In 2016, the first three versions of the tools were released (0.1 through
0.3). The Isabelle2016-1 release includes Nunchaku as well as the frontend
that bridges the gap between the proof assistant and the model finder. Work
has commenced on a Coq frontend <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and a TLA<sup>+</sup>
frontend. Currently, the backends CVC4, Kodkod, and Paradox are supported.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid15">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Jasmin Blanchette and Simon Cruanes</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid16">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Jasmin Blanchette</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid17">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://github.com/nunchaku-inria" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>github.<allowbreak/>com/<allowbreak/>nunchaku-inria</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid18" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>The Redlog Computer Logic System</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>Redlog is an integral part of the interactive computer algebra system Reduce.
It supplements Reduce's comprehensive collection of powerful methods from
symbolic computation by supplying more than 100 functions on first-order
formulas.</p>
      <p>Redlog generally works with interpreted first-order logic in contrast to free
first-order logic. Each first-order formula in Redlog must exclusively contain
atoms from one particular Redlog-supported theory, which corresponds to a
choice of admissible functions and relations with fixed semantics.
Redlog-supported theories include Nonlinear Real Arithmetic (Real Closed
Fields), Presburger Arithmetic, Parametric QSAT, and many more.</p>
      <p>In 2016 there was significant progress with the generation of models for
real satisfiability problems <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. When obtained via quantifier
elimination by virtual substitutions, such models contain in general
non-standard numbers like positive infinitesimal and infinite values. In an
efficient post-processing step Redlog now generates standard models.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid19">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Thomas Sturm and Marek Kosta</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid20">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Thomas Sturm</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid21">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://www.redlog.eu/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>redlog.<allowbreak/>eu/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid22" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>The SPASS automated theorem prover</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>The classic SPASS is an automated theorem prover based on superposition that
handles first-order logic with equality and several extensions for particular
classes of theories. With version SPASS 3.9 we have stopped the development of
the classic prover and have started the bottom-up development of SPASS 4.0 that
will actually be a workbench of automated reasoning tools.</p>
      <p>In 2016 we have made available for the first time our LIA solver SPASS-IQ.
Furthermore, we have developed a state-of-the-art SAT solver SPASS-SATT that
will be available in 2017.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid23">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Christoph Weidenbach</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid24">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://www.spass-prover.org/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>spass-prover.<allowbreak/>org/</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid25" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>TLAPS, the TLA<sup>+</sup> Proof System</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>TLAPS, the TLA<sup>+</sup> proof system developed at the Joint MSR-Inria Centre, is
a platform for developing and mechanically verifying proofs about TLA<sup>+</sup> specifications. The TLA<sup>+</sup> proof language is hierarchical and explicit,
allowing a user to decompose the overall proof into independent proof steps.
TLAPS consists of a <i>proof manager</i> that interprets the proof language
and generates a collection of proof obligations that are sent to <i>backend
verifiers</i>. The current backends include the tableau-based prover Zenon for
first-order logic, Isabelle/TLA<sup>+</sup>, an encoding of TLA<sup>+</sup> as an object
logic in the logical framework Isabelle, an SMT backend designed for use with
any SMT-lib compatible solver, and an interface to a decision procedure for
propositional temporal logic.</p>
      <p>The current version 1.4.3 of TLAPS was released in June 2015, it is
distributed under a BSD-like license.
The prover fully handles the non-temporal part of TLA<sup>+</sup>. Basic temporal
logic reasoning is supported through an interface with a decision procedure
for propositional temporal logic that performs on-the-fly abstraction of
first-order subformulas. Symmetrically, subformulas whose main operator is a
connective of temporal logic are abstracted before being sent to backends for
first-order logic.</p>
      <p>A complete rewrite of the proof manager is ongoing. Its objectives are a
cleaner interaction with the standard TLA<sup>+</sup> front-ends, in particular
SANY, the standard parser and semantic analyzer. This is necessary for
extending the scope of the fragment of TLA<sup>+</sup> that is handled by TLAPS,
such as full temporal logic and module instantiation.</p>
      <p>TLAPS has been used in several case studies, including the proof of
determinacy of PharOS <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and the
verification of the Pastry routing protocol <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid19" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.
These case studies feed back into the development of the proof system and of
its standard library.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid26">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Stephan Merz</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid27">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="https://tla.msr-inria.inria.fr/tlaps/content/Home.html" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>tla.<allowbreak/>msr-inria.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>tlaps/<allowbreak/>content/<allowbreak/>Home.<allowbreak/>html</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid28" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>The veriT Solver</bodyTitle>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Scientific Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>veriT comprises a SAT solver, a congruence closure based decision procedure
for uninterpreted symbols, a simplex-based decision procedure for linear
arithmetic, and instantiation-based quantifier handling.</p>
      <p>
        <span class="smallcap" align="left">Functional Description</span>
      </p>
      <p>VeriT is an open, trustable and efficient SMT (Satisfiability Modulo
Theories) solver, featuring efficient decision procedure for uninterpreted
symbols and linear arithmetic, and quantifier reasoning.</p>
      <p>Efforts in 2016 have been focused on non-linear arithmetic reasoning and quantifier handling.
The reasoning capabilities of veriT have been significantly improved along those two axes, but
non-linear arithmetic reasoning is not yet stable.</p>
      <p>The veriT solver participated in the SMT competition
<ref xlink:href="http://www.smtcomp.org" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">SMT-COMP 2016</ref> with good results.</p>
      <p>We target applications where validation of formulas is crucial, such as the
validation of TLA<sup>+</sup> and B specifications, and work together with the
developers of the respective verification platforms to make veriT even more
useful in practice. The solver is available as a plugin for the Rodin platform,
it is integrated within the Atelier B.</p>
      <simplelist>
        <li id="uid29">
          <p noindent="true">Participants: Pascal Fontaine, David Déharbe and Haniel Barbosa</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid30">
          <p noindent="true">Partners: Université de Lorraine - Federal University of Rio Grande do
Norte</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid31">
          <p noindent="true">Contact: Pascal Fontaine</p>
        </li>
        <li id="uid32">
          <p noindent="true">URL: <ref xlink:href="http://www.veriT-solver.org" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>www.<allowbreak/>veriT-solver.<allowbreak/>org</ref></p>
        </li>
      </simplelist>
    </subsection>
  </logiciels>
  <resultats id="uid33">
    <bodyTitle>New Results</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid34" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Automated and Interactive Theorem Proving</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="veridis-2015-idp79464">
          <firstname>Gabor</firstname>
          <lastname>Alági</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp76312">
          <firstname>Haniel</firstname>
          <lastname>Barbosa</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
          <firstname>Jasmin Christian</firstname>
          <lastname>Blanchette</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp77544">
          <firstname>Martin</firstname>
          <lastname>Bromberger</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="deducteam-2014-idp99360">
          <firstname>Simon</firstname>
          <lastname>Cruanes</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2015-idp86936">
          <firstname>Mathias</firstname>
          <lastname>Fleury</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
          <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
          <lastname>Fontaine</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp81320">
          <firstname>Marek</firstname>
          <lastname>Košta</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
          <firstname>Stephan</firstname>
          <lastname>Merz</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2015-idp78232">
          <firstname>Martin</firstname>
          <lastname>Riener</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2016-idp162592">
          <firstname>Martin</firstname>
          <lastname>Strecker</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idm25184">
          <firstname>Thomas</firstname>
          <lastname>Sturm</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp85200">
          <firstname>Marco</firstname>
          <lastname>Voigt</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp67056">
          <firstname>Uwe</firstname>
          <lastname>Waldmann</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp86448">
          <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
          <lastname>Wand</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
          <firstname>Christoph</firstname>
          <lastname>Weidenbach</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid35" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>IsaFoL: Isabelle Formalization of Logic</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with
Heiko Becker (MPI-SWS Saarbrücken),
Peter Lammich (TU München),
Andrei Popescu (Middlesex University London),
Anders Schlichtkrull (DTU Copenhagen),
Dmitriy Traytel (ETH Zürich),
and
Jørgen Villadsen (DTU Copenhagen).</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>Researchers in automated reasoning spend a significant portion of their work
time specifying logical calculi and proving metatheorems about them. These
proofs are typically carried out with pen and paper, which is error-prone and
can be tedious. As proof assistants are becoming easier to use, it makes
sense to employ them.</p>
        <p>In this spirit, we started an effort, called IsaFoL (Isabelle Formalization
of Logic), that aims at developing libraries and methodology for formalizing
modern research in the field, using the Isabelle/HOL proof assistant.<footnote id="uid36" id-text="2"><ref xlink:href="https://bitbucket.org/jasmin_blanchette/isafol/wiki/Home" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>bitbucket.<allowbreak/>org/<allowbreak/>jasmin_blanchette/<allowbreak/>isafol/<allowbreak/>wiki/<allowbreak/>Home</ref></footnote>
Our initial emphasis is on established results about propositional and
first-order logic. In particular, we are formalizing large parts of
Weidenbach's forthcoming textbook, tentatively called <i>Automated
Reasoning—The Art of Generic Problem Solving</i>.</p>
        <p>The objective of formalization work is not to eliminate paper proofs, but to
complement them with rich formal companions. Formalizations help catch
mistakes, whether superficial or deep, in specifications and theorems; they
make it easy to experiment with changes or variants of concepts; and they
help clarify concepts left vague on paper.</p>
        <p>The repository contains six completed entries and three entries that are
still in development. Notably:</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid37">
            <p noindent="true">Mathias Fleury formalized a SAT solver framework with learn, forget,
restart, and incrementality and published the result at a leading
conference, together with Jasmin Blanchette and Christoph Weidenbach
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid14" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid38">
            <p noindent="true">Anders Schlichtkrull, remotely co-supervised by Jasmin Blanchette,
formalized unordered first-order resolution in Isabelle and presented
the result at ITP 2016 <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid20" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid39">
            <p noindent="true">Together with an intern, Jasmin Blanchette, Uwe Waldmann, and Daniel Wand
formalized a generalization for the recursive path order and the
transfinite Knuth-Bendix order to higher-order terms without
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>λ</mi></math></formula>-abstractions. The result is published in the Isabelle
<i>Archive of Formal Proofs</i>.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid40" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Combination of Satisfiability Procedures</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with Christophe Ringeissen from the PESTO project-team at Inria
Nancy – Grand Est, and Paula Chocron at IIIA-CSIC, Bellaterra,
Catalonia, Spain.</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>A satisfiability problem is often expressed in a combination of theories, and
a natural approach consists in solving the problem by combining the
satisfiability procedures available for the component theories. This is the
purpose of the combination method introduced by Nelson and Oppen. However, in
its initial presentation, the Nelson-Oppen combination method requires the
theories to be signature-disjoint and stably infinite (to ensure the existence
of an infinite model). The design of a generic combination method for
non-disjoint unions of theories is clearly a hard task, but it is worth
exploring simple non-disjoint combinations that appear frequently in
verification. An example is the case of shared sets, where sets are
represented by unary predicates. Another example is the case of bridging
functions between data structures and a target theory (e.g., a fragment of
arithmetic).</p>
        <p>In 2015, we defined <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid21" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> a sound and complete
combination procedure à la Nelson-Oppen for the theory of absolutely free
data structures (including lists and trees) connected to another theory via
bridging functions. This combination procedure has also been refined for
standard interpretations. The resulting theory has a nice politeness
property, enabling combinations with arbitrary decidable theories of elements.
We also investigated <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid22" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> other theories amenable to
similar combinations: this class includes the theory of equality, the theory
of absolutely free data structures, and all the theories in between.</p>
        <p>More recently, we have been improving the framework and unified both results.
A new paper is in preparation.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid41" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Quantifier handling in SMT</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with Andrew J. Reynolds, Univ. of Iowa, USA.</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>SMT solvers generally rely on various instantiation techniques to handle
quantifiers. We are building a unifying framework for handling quantified
formulas with equality and uninterpreted functions, such that the major
instantiation techniques in SMT solving can be cast in that framework. It is
based on the problem of <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mi>E</mi></math></formula>-ground (dis)unification, a variation of the
classic Rigid <i>E</i>-unification problem. We introduced a sound and
complete calculus to solve this problem in practice: Congruence Closure with
Free Variables (CCFV). Experimental evaluations of implementations of CCFV in
the state-of-the-art solver CVC4 and in the solver veriT exhibit improvements
in the former and makes the latter competitive with state-of-the-art solvers
in several benchmark libraries stemming from verification efforts. A
publication is in preparation.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid42" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Non-linear arithmetic in SMT</bodyTitle>
        <p>In the context of the SMArT ANR-DFG (Satisfiability Modulo Arithmetic
Theories) and KANASA projects (cf. sections
<ref xlink:href="#uid64" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and
<ref xlink:href="#uid79" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>), we study the theory, design
techniques, and implement software to push forward the non-linear arithmetic
(NLA) reasoning capabilities in SMT. This year, we designed a framework to
combine interval constraint propagation with other decision procedures for
NLA, with promising results. We are also currently studying integration
of these procedures into combinations of theories. The ideas are validated
within the veriT solver, together with code from the raSAT solver (from
JAIST). An article is in preparation.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid43" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Encoding Set-Theoretic Formulas in First-Order Logic</bodyTitle>
        <p>Proof obligations that arise during the verification of high-level
specifications of algorithms in languages such as (Event-)B and TLA<sup>+</sup> mix
theories corresponding to sets, functions, arithmetic, tuples, and records.
Finding encodings of such formulas in the input languages of automatic
first-order provers (superposition-based provers or SMT solvers, which are
based on multi-sorted first-order logic) is paramount for obtaining
satisfactory levels of automation. We describe a method, based on a
combination of injection of unsorted expressions into sorted languages,
simplification by rewriting, and abstraction, that is the kernel of the SMT
backend of the TLA<sup>+</sup> proof system (section <ref xlink:href="#uid25" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>). A
paper describing our technique was presented at ABZ 2016
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid23" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and an extension of that article was invited for a
special issue of Science of Computer Programming.</p>
        <p>During the internship of Matthieu Lequesne, we experimented with an adaptation
of the technique for constructing models of formulas in set theory, which
could be useful for understanding why proof attempts fail. A prototype
generating input for the Nunchaku model finder (section
<ref xlink:href="#uid14" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) allowed us to validate the idea for a core
sublanguage of TLA<sup>+</sup>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid44" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Modal and Description Logics for Graph Transformations</bodyTitle>
        <p>Graph transformations are a research topic that is interesting in its own
right, but with many possible applications ranging from the modification of
pointer structures in imperative programs, through model transformations in
model-driven engineering, to schema-preserving transformations of graph
databases. Our particular focus is on verifying these transformations.</p>
        <p>Modal logics and variants (such as description logics that are the basis for
the web ontology language OWL) have turned out to be suitable specification
formalisms because graph structures can typically be perceived as models of
modal logics, but these logics suffer from some weaknesses when reasoning
about transformations. The first aim of our work was therefore to identify and
define sufficiently expressive modal logics, while retaining their pleasant
properties, in particular decidability <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid24" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        <p>Our next aim is to implement practically useful proof methods. We have first
concentrated on the more natural tableau proofs, with a verification of
meta-theoretic properties of the calculi (such as termination) in the Isabelle
proof assistant. We now turn to an investigation of encodings as
satisfiability problems that can be handled with SAT and SMT solvers, with
the hope to achieve a better performance.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid45" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Standard Models with Virtual Substitution</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with A. Dolzmann from Leibniz-Zentrum für Informatik in
Saarbrücken, Germany.</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>Extended quantifier elimination for the reals using virtual substitution
methods have been successfully applied to various problems in science and
engineering. Recently they have attracted attention also as theory solvers
within SMT. Such solvers typically ask also for models in the satisfiable
case. Models obtained with virtual substitution are in general obtained in
certain non-archimedian extension fields of the reals with a corresponding
expanded signature. Consequently, the obtained values for the variables
include non-standard symbols such as positive infinitesimals and infinite
values.</p>
        <p>We introduce a complete post-processing procedure to convert our models, for
fixed values of parameters, into real models <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid17" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. We furthermore
demonstrate the successful application of an implementation of our method
within Redlog to a number of extended quantifier elimination problems from the
scientific literature including computational geometry, motion planning,
bifurcation analysis for models of genetic circuits and for mass action, and
sizing of electrical networks. This solves a long-standing problem with the
virtual substitution method, which had been explicitly criticized in the
scientific literature.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid46" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Decidability of Fragments of Free First-Order Logic</bodyTitle>
        <p>We introduce a new decidable fragment of first-order logic with equality, the
<i>Separated Fragment</i> (SF). It strictly generalizes two already well-known
decidable fragments of first-order logic: the Bernays-Schönfinkel-Ramsey
(BSR) Fragment and the Monadic Fragment. The defining principle is that
universally and existentially quantified variables may not occur together in
atoms. Thus, our classification neither rests on restrictions of quantifier
prefixes (as in the BSR case) nor on restrictions on the arity of predicate
symbols (as in the monadic case).</p>
        <p>We show that SF exhibits the finite model property and derive a
non-elementary upper bound on the computing time required for deciding
satisfiability of SF sentences.
For the subfragment of prenex sentences with the quantifier prefix
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><msup><mo>∃</mo><mo>*</mo></msup><msup><mo>∀</mo><mo>*</mo></msup><msup><mo>∃</mo><mo>*</mo></msup></mrow></math></formula> the satisfiability problem is shown to be
NEXPTIME-complete. Furthermore, we discuss how automated reasoning procedures
can take advantage of our results <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid25" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
        <p>Continuing the work presented in the initial publication, we further
investigated the computational complexity of SF satisfiability. It nicely
scales across the nondeterministic standard complexity classes, depending on
joint occurrences of existentially quantified variables from
<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mo>∃</mo><mo>*</mo></msup></math></formula>-blocks that are separated by nonempty <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mo>∀</mo><mo>+</mo></msup></math></formula>-blocks.</p>
        <p>In another line of work, we relaxed the definition of SF, leading to an even
larger fragment for which satisfiability is still decidable. In this fragment,
variables of <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mo>∃</mo><mo>*</mo></msup></math></formula>-blocks and <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mo>∀</mo><mo>+</mo></msup></math></formula>-blocks may occur together in
some atom if the respective quantifiers obey a certain order.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid47" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Ordered resolution with dismatching constraints</bodyTitle>
        <p>The identification and algorithmic exploration of decidable logic fragments is
key to the automation of logics and to obtaining push-button verification
technologies. We extend a well-known decidable fragment, linear monadic
shallow Horn theories, with straight dismatching constraints, preserving
decidability. Furthermore, we show that the restriction to Horn clauses is
not needed. The fragment has various applications in security, automata theory
and theorem proving <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid26" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid48" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Undecidable combinations of first-order logic with background theories</bodyTitle>
        <p>We show that the universal fragment of Presburger arithmetic augmented with a
single uninterpreted predicate (or function) symbol is already undecidable.
The result has immediate consequences for verification techniques that combine
uninterpreted functions or predicate symbols with (fragments of) Presburger
arithmetic. For example, data structures such as arrays can be viewed as a
collection of uninterpreted functions that obey certain axioms.</p>
        <p>Our result is a sharpening of previously known results. In particular,
undecidability holds for a fragment with purely universal quantification: no
quantifier alternation is necessary. While in this case the set of
unsatisfiable sentences is still recursively enumerable, and in fact
hierarchic superposition constitutes a semi-decision procedure, allowing for
one quantifier alternation (<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mo>∃</mo><mo>∀</mo></mrow></math></formula> or <formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mrow><mo>∀</mo><mo>∃</mo></mrow></math></formula>) leads to a
fragment in which neither the satisfiable sentences nor the unsatisfiable ones
form a recursively-enumerable set. Hence, there cannot be any refutationally
complete calculus for such a combined theory.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid49" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Novel techniques for linear arithmetic constraint solving</bodyTitle>
        <p>In <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid27" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid28" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we investigate new
techniques for linear arithmetic constraint solving. They are based on the
linear cube transformation, which allows us to efficiently determine whether a
system of linear arithmetic constraints contains a hypercube of a given edge
length.</p>
        <p>Our first findings based on this transformation are two sound tests that find
integer solutions for linear arithmetic constraints. While many complete
methods search along the problem surface for a solution, these tests use cubes
to explore the interior of the problems. The tests are especially efficient
for constraints with a large number of integer solutions, e.g., those with
infinite lattice width. Inside the SMT-LIB benchmarks, we have found almost
one thousand problem instances with infinite lattice width. Experimental
results confirm that our tests are superior on these instances compared to
several state-of-the-art SMT solvers.</p>
        <p>We also discovered that the linear cube transformation can be used to
investigate the equalities implied by a system of linear arithmetic
constraints. For this purpose, we developed a method that computes a basis for
all implied equalities, i.e., a finite representation of all equalities
implied by the linear arithmetic constraints. The equality basis can
be used to decide whether a system of linear arithmetic constraints
implies a given equality.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid50" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Formal Methods for Developing and Analyzing Algorithms and Systems</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp75064">
          <firstname>Noran</firstname>
          <lastname>Azmy</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="algorille-2014-idp109184">
          <firstname>Gabriel</firstname>
          <lastname>Corona</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2016-idp184800">
          <firstname>Margaux</firstname>
          <lastname>Duroeulx</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp69864">
          <firstname>Marie</firstname>
          <lastname>Duflot-Kremer</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2015-idp89424">
          <firstname>Souad</firstname>
          <lastname>Kherroubi</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
          <firstname>Dominique</firstname>
          <lastname>Méry</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
          <firstname>Stephan</firstname>
          <lastname>Merz</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="madynes-2016-idp224432">
          <firstname>Nicolas</firstname>
          <lastname>Schnepf</lastname>
        </person>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
          <firstname>Christoph</firstname>
          <lastname>Weidenbach</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <subsection id="uid51" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Making explicit domain knowledge in formal system development</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with partners of the IMPEX project.</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>Modeling languages are concerned with providing techniques and tool support
for the design, synthesis and analysis of the models resulting from a given
modeling activity, and this activity is usually part of a system development
model or process. These languages quite successfully focus on the analysis of
the designed system, exploiting the semantic features of the underlying
modeling language. These semantics are well understood by the system designers
and/or the users of the modeling language, that is why we speak of implicit
semantics.</p>
        <p>In general, modeling languages are not equipped with resources,
concepts or entities handling explicitly domain engineering features
and characteristics (domain knowledge) in which the modeled systems
evolve.</p>
        <p>We posit that designers should explicitly handle the
knowledge resulting from an analysis of the application domain, i.e. explicit
semantics. As of today, making explicit the domain knowledge inside system
design models does not follow any methodological rule; instead, features of
domain knowledge are introduced in an ad-hoc way through types, constraints,
profiles, etc.</p>
        <p>Our claim <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid29" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> is that ontologies are good candidates
for handling explicit domain knowledge. They define domain theories and
provide resources for uniquely identifying concepts of domain knowledge.
Therefore, allowing models to make references to ontologies is a modular
solution for models to explicitly handle domain knowledge. Overcoming the
absence of explicit semantics expression in the modeling languages used to
specify systems models will increase the robustness of the designed system
models. Indeed, references to the axioms and theorems resulting from the
ontologies can be used to strengthen the properties of the designed models.
The objective is to offer rigorous mechanisms for handling domain knowledge in
design models. We also show how these mechanisms are set up in the cases of
formal system models, both for static and dynamic aspects.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid52" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Incremental Development of Systems and Algorithms</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with Andriamiarina, Manamiary Bruno, with Neeraj Kumar Singh from
IRIT, Toulouse, with Rosemary Monahan, NUI Maynooth, Ireland, and with Zheng
Cheng, LINA, Nantes.</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>The development of distributed algorithms and, more generally, of distributed
systems, is a complex, delicate, and challenging process. The approach based
on refinement applies a design methodology that starts from the most abstract
model and leads, in an incremental way, to a distributed solution. The use of
a proof assistant gives a formal guarantee on the conformance of each
refinement with the model preceding it.</p>
        <p>Our main results during 2016 are:</p>
        <simplelist>
          <li id="uid53">
            <p noindent="true">An extension <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid30" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> for handling the verification of
concurrent programs. In a second step, we show the importance of the concept
of refinement, and how it can be used to found a methodology for designing
concurrent programs using the coordination paradigm.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid54">
            <p noindent="true">A fully mechanized proof <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid31" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> of
correctness of self-<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><mo>*</mo></math></formula> systems along with an interesting case study
related to P2P-based self-healing protocols.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid55">
            <p noindent="true">We report on our progress in implementing a software development
environment that integrates two formal software engineering techniques:
program refinement as supported by Event-B, and program verification as
supported by the Spec# programming system. We improve the usability of
formal verification tools by providing a general framework for integrating
these two approaches to software verification. We show how the two
approaches, based respectively on correctness by construction and on
post-hoc verification, can be used in a productive way.
In <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid32" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, we focus on the final steps in this process
where the final concrete specification is transformed into an executable
algorithm. We present <span class="smallcap" align="left">EB2RC</span>, a plug-in for the <span class="smallcap" align="left">Rodin</span>
platform that reads in an Event-B model and uses the control framework
introduced during its refinement to generate a graphical representation of
the executable algorithm. <span class="smallcap" align="left">EB2RC</span> also generates a recursive
algorithm that is easily translated into executable code. We illustrate our
technique through case studies and their analysis.</p>
          </li>
        </simplelist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid56" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Verification of the Pastry routing protocol</bodyTitle>
        <p>In her PhD thesis, Noran Azmy develops a formal proof in TLA<sup>+</sup> of the
routing protocol used in the Pastry protocol <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid33" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> for
maintaining a distributed hash table over a peer-to-peer network. In a
previous thesis <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid34" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, Tianxiang Lu had found problems with all
published versions of the original protocol, introduced a variant of Pastry,
and given a first correctness proof of that protocol, assuming that no node
ever disconnects. Due to limitations of TLAPS at that time, Lu's proof relied
on many unchecked assumptions on arithmetic and on the underlying data
structures, and it was later discovered that several of these assumptions were
not valid.</p>
        <p>Noran Azmy simplified the proof by introducing intermediate abstractions that
allowed her to avoid low-level arithmetic reasoning in the main proof steps,
and she proved lemmas corresponding to those assumptions that were actually
used in the proof. As a result, she obtained a complete machine-checked proof
of Lu's variant of the Pastry protocol, still under the assumption that no
node leaves the network. Moreover, a close analysis of the invariant used in
her simplified proof revealed that the protocol could be simplified by leaving
out the final “lease exchange” protocol. The results were published at ABZ
2016 <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid19" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, and an extended article was invited for
publication in Science of Computer Programming.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid57" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Proof of Determinacy of PharOS</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with Selma Azaiez and Matthieu Lemerre (CEA Saclay), and Damien
Doligez (Inria Paris).</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>As the main contribution of our group to the ADN4SE project funded by PIA, in
cooperation with colleagues from CEA LIST, we wrote a high-level TLA<sup>+</sup> specification of the real-time operating system PharOS
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid35" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> and proved its executions to be
deterministic. Roughly speaking, determinacy means that the sequence of local
states of any process during a computation does not depend on the order in
which processes are scheduled. The proof assumes that no deadlines are missed
(which in practice is ensured by schedulability analysis of the particular
applications). This property greatly simplifies the analysis and verification
of programs that are executed within PharOS. The results were published at ABZ
2016 <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid18" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid58" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Formal Verification of Chains of Security Functions</bodyTitle>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with Rémi Badonnel and Abdelkader Lahmadi of the Madynes research
group of Inria Nancy.</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>During his Master's thesis, Nicolas Schnepf studied formal techniques for the
automatic verification of chains of security functions in a setting of
software-defined networks (SDN). Concretely, he defined an extension of the
Pyretic language <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid36" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> taking into account the data
plane of SDN controllers and implemented a translation of that extension to
the input languages of the nuXmv model checker and of SMT solvers. The
approach and its scalability was validated over crafted security chains, and a
conference paper describing the results is under preparation.
Nicolas Schnepf started a PhD thesis in October 2016, jointly supervised by
members of the Madynes and VeriDis groups.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid59" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Auditing hybrid systems for compliance</bodyTitle>
        <p>There is a huge gap in complexity between the actual analysis of a complex
hybrid system and the analysis of the eventual control needed for safe
operation. For example, for the combustion process of an engine there is not
even a closed formal model, but the eventual control can be represented in a
finite domain language. Such a language can then in particular be used for
run-time control of a system through an auditor, providing the detection of
faulty components or compliance violations. We have studied the consequences
of such an approach if applied to the overall life time process of a technical
system <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid37" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </resultats>
  <contrats id="uid60">
    <bodyTitle>Bilateral Contracts and Grants with Industry</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid61" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Modeling a Distributed File System</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <person key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
          <firstname>Stephan</firstname>
          <lastname>Merz</lastname>
        </person>
      </participants>
      <p>Our group was contacted by Huawei R&amp;D Silicon Valley for evaluating the
suitability of using the TLA<sup>+</sup> specification language for describing
high-level protocols used in Cloud systems. We provided a specification of
protocols used in the Ceph file system <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid38" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>. We also provided
on-site training for Huawei engineers in Chengdu, China.
</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid62" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Logic for Business</bodyTitle>
      <participants>
        <p>Christoph Weidenbach</p>
      </participants>
      <p>The group in Saarbrücken has established a master agreement with L4B (Logic
for Business) on the exchange of data and the creation of bilateral research
projects. L4B is involved in several consulting projects with the German car
industry on product specification strategies, including software.
</p>
    </subsection>
  </contrats>
  <partenariat id="uid63">
    <bodyTitle>Partnerships and Cooperations</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid64" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>National Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid65" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ANR-DFG Project SMArT</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idp76312">
            <firstname>Haniel</firstname>
            <lastname>Barbosa</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
            <firstname>Pascal</firstname>
            <lastname>Fontaine</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idp81320">
            <firstname>Marek</firstname>
            <lastname>Košta</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <firstname>Stephan</firstname>
            <lastname>Merz</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idm25184">
            <firstname>Thomas</firstname>
            <lastname>Sturm</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The SMArT (Satisfiability Modulo Arithmetic Theories) project is funded by
<i>ANR-DFG Programmes blancs 2013</i>, a program of the Agence Nationale de la
Recherche and the (German) Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft DFG. It started in
April 2014. The project gathers members of VeriDis in Nancy and Saarbrücken,
and the Systerel company. The objective of the SMArT project is to provide
advanced techniques for arithmetic reasoning beyond linear arithmetic for
formal system verification, and particularly for SMT. The results feed back
into the implementations of Redlog (section <ref xlink:href="#uid18" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>) and
veriT (section <ref xlink:href="#uid28" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>), which also serve as
experimentation platforms for theories, techniques and methods designed within
this project.</p>
        <p>More information on the project can be found on
<ref xlink:href="http://smart.gforge.inria.fr/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://smart.gforge.inria.fr/</ref>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid66" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>ANR Project IMPEX</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="veridis-2015-idp89424">
            <firstname>Souad</firstname>
            <lastname>Kherroubi</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <firstname>Dominique</firstname>
            <lastname>Méry</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>The ANR Project IMPEX, within the INS program, started in December
2013 for 4 years. It is coordinated by Dominique Méry, the other partners
are IRIT/ENSEIHT, Systerel, Supelec, and Telecom Sud Paris. The work
reported here also included a cooperation with Pierre Castéran from LaBRI
Bordeaux.</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>Modeling languages provide techniques and tool support for the design,
synthesis, and analysis of the models resulting from a given modeling
activity, as part of a system development process. These languages quite
successfully focused on the analysis of the designed system exploiting the
expressed semantic power of the underlying modeling language. The semantics
of this modeling languages are well understood by the system designers and
the users of the modeling language, i.e. the semantics is implicit in the
model. In general, modeling languages are not equipped with resources,
concepts or entities handling explicitly domain engineering features and
characteristics (domain knowledge) underlying the modeled systems. Indeed,
the designer has to explicitly handle the knowledge resulting from an
analysis of this application domain <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid39" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>, i.e. explicit
semantics. Nowadays, making explicit the domain knowledge inside system
design models does not obey any methodological rules validated by practice.
The users of modeling languages introduce these domain knowledge features
through types, constraints, profiles, etc. Our claim is that ontologies are
good candidates for handling explicit domain knowledge. They define domain
theories and provide resources for uniquely identifying domain knowledge
concepts. Therefore, allowing models to make references to ontologies is a
modular solution for models to explicitly handle domain knowledge. Overcoming
the absence of explicit semantics expression in the modeling languages used
to specify systems models will increase the robustness of the designed system
models. Indeed, the axioms and theorems resulting from the ontologies can be
used to strengthen the properties of the designed models. The objective
<ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid29" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> is to offer rigorous mechanisms for handling
domain knowledge in design models.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid67" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria IPL HAC SPECIS</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idp69864">
            <firstname>Marie</firstname>
            <lastname>Duflot-Kremer</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <firstname>Stephan</firstname>
            <lastname>Merz</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>The goal of the <ref xlink:href="http://hacspecis.gforge.inria.fr" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">HAC
SPECIS</ref> (High-performance Application and
Computers: Studying PErformance and Correctness In Simulation) project is to
answer methodological needs of HPC application and runtime developers and to
allow studying real HPC systems with respect to both correctness and
performance. To this end, this Inria Project Lab assembles experts from the
HPC, formal verification, and performance evaluation communities.</p>
        <p>HAC SPECIS started in 2016. VeriDis contributes through its expertise in
formal verification techniques. In particular, our goal is to extend the
functionalities of exhaustive and statistical model checking within the
SimGrid platform.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid68" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria Technological Development Action CUIC</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <firstname>Jasmin Christian</firstname>
            <lastname>Blanchette</lastname>
          </person>
          <person key="deducteam-2014-idp99360">
            <firstname>Simon</firstname>
            <lastname>Cruanes</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <p>Most “theorems” initially given to a proof assistant are incorrect, whether
because of a typo, a missing assumption, or a fundamental flaw. Novices and
experts alike can enter invalid formulas and find themselves wasting hours,
or even days, on an impossible proof. This project, funded by Inria and
running from 2015 to 2017, supports the development of a counterexample
generator for higher-order logic. This new tool, called Nunchaku (cf. section <ref xlink:href="#uid14" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>), will be
integrated in various proof assistants, including Isabelle, Coq, and the
TLA<sup>+</sup> Proof System. The project is coordinated by Jasmin Blanchette and
also involves Inria Saclay (Toccata group) and Inria Rennes (Celtique group),
among others. Simon Cruanes was hired in October 2015 and has started the
development of Nunchaku, whereas Blanchette has developed an Isabelle
frontend. Three releases have taken place so far, and the tool is an
integral part of the Isabelle2016-1 official release. Work has started on
Coq and TLAPS frontends.
The tool is described in a conference publication <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid40" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>
and was presented at a workshop <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid16" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid69" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria ADT PLM (2014-2016)</bodyTitle>
        <participants>
          <person key="algorille-2014-idp116736">
            <firstname>Matthieu</firstname>
            <lastname>Nicolas</lastname>
          </person>
        </participants>
        <moreinfo>
          <p>Joint work with Gérald Oster (project-team Coast, Inria Nancy – Grand Est)
and Martin Quinson (project-team Myriads, Inria Rennes – Bretagne Atlantique)</p>
        </moreinfo>
        <p>The goal of this project is to establish an experimental platform for
studying the didactics of informatics, specifically centered on
introductory programming courses.</p>
        <p>The project builds upon a pedagogical platform for supervising programming
exercises developed for our own teaching, and improves this base in several
ways. We want to provide more adapted feedback to the learners, and gather
more data to better understand how beginners learn programming.</p>
        <p>This year, we finalized the web version of our framework, and
submitted several project applications to pursue this work in the
future. Unfortunately, none of these applications have been accepted
so far. Martin Quinson invited Peter Hubwieser, professor of the
Technical University of Munich (TUM) and specialist of the didactics of
Computer Science, for two weeks in November. Developing the PLM and
exploiting the data already gathered were central elements of this
work meeting. A joint publication is currently prepared, targeting the
ItiCSE'17 conference.</p>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid70" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>European Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid71" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>FP7 &amp; H2020 Projects</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid72">
            <p noindent="true">Program: H2020-FETOPEN-2015-CSA</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid73">
            <p noindent="true">Project acronym: SC<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mrow/><mn>2</mn></msup></math></formula></p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid74">
            <p noindent="true">Project title: Satisfiability Checking and Symbolic Computation</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid75">
            <p noindent="true">Duration: July 2016 – September 2018</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid76">
            <p noindent="true">Coordinator: James H. Davenport (U. Bath, U.K.)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid77">
            <p noindent="true">Other partners:
RWTH Aachen (Germany),
Fondazione Bruno Kessler (Italy),
Università degli Studi di Genova (Italy),
Maplesoft Europe Ltd (Germany),
Coventry University (U.K.),
University of Oxford (U.K.),
Universität Kassel (Germany),
Max Planck Institut für Informatik (Germany),
Universität Linz (Austria)</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid78">
            <p noindent="true">Abstract:
Whereas symbolic computation is concerned with efficient algorithms
for determining exact solutions to complex mathematical problems, more
recent developments in the area of satisfiability checking tackle
similar problems with different algorithmic and technological
solutions. Both communities have made remarkable progress in the last
decades and address practical problems of rapidly increasing size and
complexity.
For example, satisfiability checking is an essential backend for assuring the
security and the safety of computer systems. Techniques and tools of symbolic
computation are used by different scientific communities for solving large
mathematical problems that are out of reach of pencil and paper developments.
Currently the two communities are largely disjoint and unaware of the
achievements of each other, despite strong reasons for them to discuss and
collaborate, as they share many central interests. Bridges between the
communities in the form of common platforms and roadmaps are necessary to
initiate an exchange, and to support and to direct their interaction. This
Coordination and Support Action within the FET-Open framework
will initiate a wide range of activities to bring the two communities together,
identify common challenges, offer global events and bilateral visits, propose
standards, and so on. Combining the knowledge, experience and the technologies
in these communities will lead to cross-fertilization and mutual improvements,
enabling the development of radically improved software tools.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid79" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Initiatives</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid80" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Inria International Partners</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid81" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>KANASA</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid82">
              <p noindent="true">Title: Kanazawa-Nancy for Satistifiability and Arithmetics</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid83">
              <p noindent="true">International Partner:
Japan Advanced Institute for Science and Technology
(Dept. Intelligent Robotics, Mizuhito Ogawa)</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid84">
              <p noindent="true">Starting year: 2016</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid85">
              <p noindent="true">During the last decade, there has been tremendous progress on symbolic
verification techniques, spurred in particular by the development of SMT
(satisfiability modulo theories) techniques and tools. Our first direction of
research will be to investigate the theoretical background and the practical
techniques to integrate Interval Constraint Propagation within a generic SMT
framework, including other decision procedures and quantifier handling
techniques. On the purely arithmetic side, we also want to study how to unite
the reasoning power of all arithmetic techniques developed in the team,
including simplex-based SMT-like reasoners, Virtual Substitution, and
Cylindrical Algebraic Decomposition. In particular, this includes developing
theory combination frameworks for linear and non-linear arithmetic. There is
a strong incentive for these kind of combinations since even non-linear SMT
problems contain a large proportion of linear constraints. The partnership is
supported by a Memorandum of Understanding between JAIST and LORIA.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid86" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>International Research Visitors</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid87" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Visits of International Scientists</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid88">
            <p noindent="true">Ilina Stoilkovska</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid89">
                <p noindent="true">Date: 1 September – 31 October</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid90">
                <p noindent="true">Institution: TU Wien (Austria)</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid91">
                <p noindent="true">Host: Stephan Merz</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
            <p>Ilina is a PhD student at TU Wien, Austria, and works on tailored
abstractions for the parameterized verification of fault-tolerant
distributed algorithms. During her stay in Nancy, she worked on a formal
soundness proof of her abstractions in the TLA<sup>+</sup> Proof System.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid92">
            <p noindent="true">Tung Vu Xuan</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid93">
                <p noindent="true">Date: 1 May 2016 – 30 April 2017</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid94">
                <p noindent="true">Institution: JAIST</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid95">
                <p noindent="true">Host: Pascal Fontaine</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
            <p>Tung Vu Xuan is a PhD student at JAIST, Japan. He is visiting VeriDis in
the context of the KANASA project. He works mainly on Interval Constraint
Propagation (ICP), a heuristic but powerful method for satisfiability
checking of non-linear arithmetic (NLA) constraints. During his stay, we
investigate techniques to combine ICP with decision procedures for NLA
within an SMT context.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid96" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Internships</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid97">
            <p noindent="true">Anders Olav Candasamy</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid98">
                <p noindent="true">Date: 1 March – 31 July</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid99">
                <p noindent="true">Institution: Université de Lorraine (Erasmus Mundus DESEM)</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid100">
                <p noindent="true">Host: Dominique Méry</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
            <p>Anders Candasamy analyzed a hemodialysis case study using Event-B. Besides
developing the formal model, he also reflected on the modeling process and
proposed several methodological improvements.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid101">
            <p noindent="true">Matthieu Lequesne</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid102">
                <p noindent="true">Date: 1 March – 31 July</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid103">
                <p noindent="true">Institution: École Polytechnique</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid104">
                <p noindent="true">Host: Stephan Merz</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
            <p>Matthieu Lequesne worked on translating formulas in a core
sublanguage of TLA<sup>+</sup> to the input format of Nunchaku (section
<ref xlink:href="#uid14" location="intern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/>), with the aim of producing (counter)models
for TLA<sup>+</sup> proof obligations.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid105">
            <p noindent="true">Weichung Shaw</p>
            <sanspuceslist>
              <li id="uid106">
                <p noindent="true">Date: 1 March – 31 August</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid107">
                <p noindent="true">Institution: Université de Lorraine (Erasmus Mundus DESEM)</p>
              </li>
              <li id="uid108">
                <p noindent="true">Host: Stephan Merz</p>
              </li>
            </sanspuceslist>
            <p>Weichung Shaw worked on formalizing a correctness proof of
the Raft consensus algorithm <ref xlink:href="#veridis-2016-bid41" location="biblio" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest"/> in TLA<sup>+</sup>. He proved
several fundamental lemmas and documented several methodological issues with
the use of TLAPS.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
  </partenariat>
  <diffusion id="uid109">
    <bodyTitle>Dissemination</bodyTitle>
    <subsection id="uid110" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Promoting Scientific Activities</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid111" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Organization of Scientific Events</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid112" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>General Chair, Scientific Chair</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid113">
              <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette and Stephan Merz, with the help of Anne-Lise Charbonnier
of Inria Nancy, organized the <i>7th International Conference on
Interactive Theorem Proving</i> (ITP 2016) and associated workshops in Nancy,
on August 22–27, 2016.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid114" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of the Organizing Committees</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid115">
              <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette co-organized the <i>Hammers for Type Theories</i> (HaTT 2016)
workshop at IJCAR 2016 in Coimbra, Portugal.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid116">
              <p noindent="true">Pascal Fontaine co-organized the
<i>First SC<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mrow/><mn>2</mn></msup></math></formula> workshop on Satisfiability Checking and Symbolic Computation</i>
with Erika Abraham (RWTH, Aachen).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid117">
              <p noindent="true">Pascal Fontaine co-organized the 5th Workshop on Practical Aspects of
Automated Reasoning (PAAR) with Stephan Schulz (DHBW Stuttgart) and Josef
Urban (Czech Technical University in Prague).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid118">
              <p noindent="true">Dominique Méry was a member of the organizing committees of the workshops
F-IDE, BWare, Impex, and Formose.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid119">
              <p noindent="true">Dominique Méry, together with Yamine Aït-Ameur (Toulouse) and Shin
Nakajima (Tokyo), organized a meeting on <i>Implicit and explicit
semantics integration in proof based developments of discrete systems</i> in
November within the series of NII Shonan meetings.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid120">
              <p noindent="true">The International Summer School on Verification Techniques, Systems, and
Applications (VTSA) has been organized since 2008 in the Greater Region
(Nancy, Saarbrücken, Luxembourg, Liège, and Koblenz), and Stephan Merz and
Christoph Weidenbach are co-organizers of VTSA. In 2016, VTSA took place
at the end of August in Liège, Belgium.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid121" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Selection of Scientific Events</bodyTitle>
        <subsection id="uid122" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Chair of Conference Program Committees</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid123">
              <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette and Stephan Merz chaired the program committee of the
<i>7th International Conference on Interactive Theorem Proving</i> (ITP 2016).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid124">
              <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz co-chaired the program committee of the Third International
Workshop on Formal Reasoning in Distributed Algorithms (FRiDA), organized in
May as a satellite of NETYS in Marrakech, Morocco.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="uid125" level="3">
          <bodyTitle>Member of Conference Program Committees</bodyTitle>
          <sanspuceslist>
            <li id="uid126">
              <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette served on the program committee of the
<i>International Conference on Tests and Proofs</i> (TAP).</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid127">
              <p noindent="true">Pascal Fontaine served on the program committee of the workshop SMT.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid128">
              <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz served on the program committees of the international
conferences ABZ, ICALP, and ICFEM, and of the workshops ARQNL, FMICS-AVoCS,
and GRSRD.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid129">
              <p noindent="true">Martin Strecker served on the program committees of ICTERI and ICGT.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid130">
              <p noindent="true">Thomas Sturm served on the program committees of CASC and of the
SC<formula type="inline"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" overflow="scroll"><msup><mrow/><mn>2</mn></msup></math></formula> workshop at SYNACS.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid131">
              <p noindent="true">Uwe Waldmann served on the program committee of the workshop PAAR,
colocated with IJCAR 2016.</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid132">
              <p noindent="true">Christoph Weidenbach served on the program committee of IJCAR.</p>
            </li>
          </sanspuceslist>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid133" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Journals</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid134">
            <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz, together with Jun Pang of the University of Luxembourg,
edited two volumes of a special issue on Formal Engineering Methods in the
journal <i>Formal Aspects of Computing</i>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid135">
            <p noindent="true">Thomas Sturm is a member of the editorial boards of the
<i>Journal of Symbolic Computation</i> (Elsevier) and
<i>Mathematics in Computer Science</i> (Springer).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid136">
            <p noindent="true">Christoph Weidenbach is an editor of the Journal of Automated Reasoning.
Together with Deepak Kapur and Stéphane Demri he edited a special issue of JAR
containing selected and extended papers of IJCAR 2014.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid137" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Invited Talks</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid138">
            <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette gave invited talks at the Semantic Representation of
Mathematical Knowledge Workshop organized by the Wolfram Foundation and the
Fields Institute in Toronto, Canada, at the Sino-German Frontiers of Science
Symposium (SINOGFOS) organized by the Humboldt Foundation and the Chinese
Academy of Science in Shenzhen, China, at the Workshop on Proofs,
Justifications, and Certificates in Toulouse, France, at the Universality
of Proof seminar at Schloss Dagstuhl in Wadern, Germany, and at the
Prague Inter-Reasonning Workshop (PIWo) in Prague, Czech Republic.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid139">
            <p noindent="true">Pascal Fontaine gave an invited talk at the AFSEC day of the GdR GPL, and
at GT-Verif day of the GdR IM.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid140">
            <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz gave invited talks at the TRS meeting and the JAIST-LORIA
workshop in Kanazawa, Japan, on <i>Satisfiability Checking for Modal Logics
via SMT Solving</i> and on <i>The Design of the TLA<sup>+</sup> Proof System</i>. He
also gave an invited talk at the <i>Cloud Reliability Workshop</i> in
Shenzhen, China, on <i>A Formal Analysis of Pastry</i>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid141">
            <p noindent="true">Thomas Sturm gave an invited talk at ACA 2016 titled <i>Real Problems
over the Reals</i>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid142">
            <p noindent="true">Christoph Weidenbach gave an invited lecture at the SMT Summer School in
Lisbon, Portugal.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid143" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Leadership within the Scientific Community</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid144">
            <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette served as editor of the newsletter of the Association
for Automated Reasoning (AAR) and as member of the AAR board.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid145">
            <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette and Christoph Weidenbach were elected on the
CADE (<i>Conference on Automated Deduction</i>) Inc. Board of Trustees.
Christoph Weidenbach was elected President of CADE Inc. by the
CADE Inc. Board of Trustees.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid146">
            <p noindent="true">Jasmin Blanchette is an ex officio member of the steering committee of the
conference series <i>Interactive Theorem Proving</i>.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid147">
            <p noindent="true">Pascal Fontaine is an SMT-LIB manager, together with Clark Barrett
(Stanford University) and Cesare Tinelli (University of Iowa). He is a member
of the FroCoS steering Committee. He has been an elected CADE trustee since
October 2014. He serves as member of the Association for Automated Reasoning
(AAR) board.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid148">
            <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz is a member of the IFIP Working Group 2.2 on <i>Formal
Description of Programming Concepts</i>. He is also a member of the steering
committee of the workshop on Automated Verification of Critical Systems
(AVoCS).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid149">
            <p noindent="true">Thomas Sturm is a member of the steering committee of the conference
series <i>Mathematical Aspects of Computer and Information Sciences</i>
(MACIS).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid150">
            <p noindent="true">Christoph Weidenbach is a member of the steering committee of IJCAR.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid151" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Scientific Expertise</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid152">
            <p noindent="true">Pascal Fontaine was a panel member for the CASC-25 competition of
first-order theorem prover.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid153">
            <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz served as an expert for the French Agence Nationale de la
Recherche (ANR), the Haut Conseil de l'Évaluation de la Recherche et de
l'Enseignement Supérieur (HCERES), and for the European Research Council (ERC).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid154">
            <p noindent="true">Christoph Weidenbach served as an expert for GIF (German Israel
Foundation), the FWF (Austrian Science Fund) and the DFG (German Science
Foundation).</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid155" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Research Administration</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid156">
            <p noindent="true">Dominique Méry is the head of the Doctoral School IAEM Lorraine for the
University of Lorraine.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid157">
            <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz is a member of the Scientific Directorate of the
International Computer Science Meeting Center in Schloss Dagstuhl. Until
August 2016, he was the head of the PhD committee for computer science of the
Doctoral School IAEM Lorraine. Since September 2016, he is the delegate for
scientific affairs at the Inria Nancy – Grand Est research center. He is also
the delegate for the organization of conferences at Inria Nancy and the
coordinator of the CPER <i>Sciences du Numérique</i> in Lorraine (2015–2020).
He was a member of the hiring committee of junior researchers at Inria Nancy
in 2016 and a member of the committee for the SIF thesis award (<i>Prix
Gilles Kahn</i>).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid158">
            <p noindent="true">Christoph Weidenbach is a member of the selection committee of the
Saarbrücken Graduate School in Computer Science.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid159" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Teaching - Supervision - Juries</bodyTitle>
      <subsection id="uid160" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Teaching</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid161">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Jasmin Blanchette, Computational Metaphysics (guest lecturer), 4
HETD, Freie Universität Berlin, Germany.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid162">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: Marie Duflot-Kremer, Algorithmique et Programmation 1, 80 HETD
L1 Mathématiques, Informatiques Sciences pour l'Ingénieur, Université de
Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid163">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: Marie Duflot-Kremer, Bases de données 1 et 2, 35 HETD, L2
informatique, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid164">
            <p noindent="true">Licence: Marie Duflot-Kremer, Projet personnel et communication, 50 HETD,
L2 informatique, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid165">
            <p noindent="true">Master : Marie Duflot-Kremer, Vérification de systèmes, 30 HETD, M1
Informatique, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid166">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Marie Duflot-Kremer and Stephan Merz, Vérification algorithmique,
30 HETD, M2 Informatique, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid167">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Marie Duflot-Kremer and Stephan Merz, Elements of Model Checking,
36 HETD, M2 Informatique and Master Erasmus Mundus DESEM, Université de
Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid168">
            <p noindent="true">Master : Marie Duflot-Kremer and Stephan Merz, Conception et architectures distribuées 24 HETD M1 informatique, Université de Lorraine</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid169">
            <p noindent="true">Licence : Pascal Fontaine, Structure des ordinateurs, 67 HETD, L2 MIASHS, parcours MIAGE, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid170">
            <p noindent="true">Licence : Pascal Fontaine, Logique des prédicats, 32 HETD, L2 MIASHS, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid171">
            <p noindent="true">Master : Pascal Fontaine, Réseaux, 50 HETD, M1 MIAGE, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid172">
            <p noindent="true">Master : Pascal Fontaine, Génie Logiciel, 30 HETD, M1 MIAGE, IGA Rabbat et Université de Lorraine, Maroc.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid173">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Dominique Méry, Models and algorithms, 60 HETD, M1, Telecom Nancy,
Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid174">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Dominique Méry, Formal model engineering, 24 HETD, M2, Telecom
Nancy, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid175">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Dominique Méry, Modeling Systems, 30 HETD, M2, Telecom Nancy,
Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid176">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Dominique Méry, Modeling Systems, 36 HETD, M2 informatique and
Master Erasmus Mundus DESEM, Université de Lorraine, France.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid177">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Dominique Méry, Event-B modeling, 8 HETD, NUI Maynooth.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid178">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Uwe Waldmann, Automated Reasoning I, 90 HETD, Universität des
Saarlandes, Germany.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid179">
            <p noindent="true">Master: Uwe Waldmann, Automated Reasoning II, 60 HETD, Universität des
Saarlandes, Germany. This lecture received the teaching award of the Computer
Science Students Association.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid180" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Supervision</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid181">
            <p noindent="true">PhD: Noran Azmy, An Automated Proof of Correctness for Pastry, Saarland
University and Université de Lorraine, defended on November 24, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid182">
            <p noindent="true">PhD: Marek Košta, Computational Logic, Universität des
Saarlandes. Defended on December 13, 2016.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid183">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Gabor Alági, Efficient Reasoning in Finite Domains, Saarland
University. Supervised by Christoph Weidenbach, since 11/2012.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid184">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Haniel Barbosa, Refutational Completeness in
Satisfiability Modulo Theories, Université de Lorraine and UFRN (Natal,
Brazil). Supervised by David Déharbe, Pascal Fontaine, and Stephan Merz, since
12/2013.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid185">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Martin Bromberger, Arithmetic Reasoning,
Saarland University. Supervised by Christoph Weidenbach, since 07/2014.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid186">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Mathias Fleury, Formalization of Logical Calculi,
Saarland University. Supervised by Christoph Weidenbach and Jasmin Blanchette,
since 09/2015.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid187">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Marco Voigt, Decidable Hierarchic Combinations,
Saarland University. Supervised by Christoph Weidenbach, since 11/2013.</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid188">
            <p noindent="true">PhD in progress: Daniel Wand, First-Order Extensions to Support Higher-Order Reasoning,
Saarland University. Supervised by Christoph Weidenbach and Jasmin Blanchette,
since 02/2011.</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="uid189" level="2">
        <bodyTitle>Thesis committees</bodyTitle>
        <sanspuceslist>
          <li id="uid190">
            <p noindent="true">Dominique Méry served on the committees for the PhD thesis of Pierre
Halmagrand (CNAM) and the habilitation thesis of Brahim Hamid (Université
Toulouse Jean Jaurès).</p>
          </li>
          <li id="uid191">
            <p noindent="true">Stephan Merz served as a reviewer for the PhD thesis of Yakoub Némouchi
(Université Paris Saclay) and as a PhD examiner for the PhD thesis of Alland
Blanchard (Université d'Orléans).</p>
          </li>
        </sanspuceslist>
      </subsection>
    </subsection>
    <subsection id="uid192" level="1">
      <bodyTitle>Science outreach</bodyTitle>
      <sanspuceslist>
        <li id="uid193">
          <p noindent="true">Marie Duflot-Kremer took part in various science outreach activities, with
a public ranging from primary school kids to golden agers, including high
school and potential university students. A selection of these activities is
given below:</p>
          <simplelist>
            <li id="uid194">
              <p noindent="true">two days at “Fête de la science” in Nancy (Faculté de Sciences et
Technologies and ARTEM);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid195">
              <p noindent="true">a course on Scratch for high school professors in charge of teaching
optional course ISN (Informatique et Sciences du Numérique);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid196">
              <p noindent="true">her explanations of three new unplugged activities (data bases, model
checking and text compression) have been recorded by Inria and will soon be
added to the Youtube channel of Interstice intended for promoting and
sharing such activities;</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid197">
              <p noindent="true">she is in charge of the scientific part of the second module in the
Class'Code project, aiming at training teachers and educators for carrying
out computer science activities with childrens aged 8 to 14 years;</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid198">
              <p noindent="true">she is a member of two groups including university and secondary school
teachers, dedicated to the training of math teachers who now teach computer
science to students of age 11 to 18. A day of training was given to high
school teachers;</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid199">
              <p noindent="true">“Journée femmes de Sciences”: one day dedicated to the promotion of
science towards 14 year-old girls;</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid200">
              <p noindent="true">she is a member of the steering committee preparing an itinerant
exposition intended for explaining computer science to the public, to be
released in December 2016;</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid201">
              <p noindent="true">she presented unplugged outreach activities to the staff at Cité des
Sciences (Paris);</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid202">
              <p noindent="true">she conducted during five months an experiment on the discovery of
programming for golden agers using Scratch;</p>
            </li>
            <li id="uid203">
              <p noindent="true">she took part in “Pépinière 4.0” and 4.1, explaining computer
science concepts to teachers.</p>
            </li>
          </simplelist>
        </li>
      </sanspuceslist>
    </subsection>
  </diffusion>
  <biblio id="bibliography" html="bibliography" numero="10" titre="Bibliography">
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid3" type="inproceedings" rend="refer" n="refercite:bouton:verit">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">veriT: an open, trustable and efficient SMT-solver</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Thomas</foreName>
            <surname>Bouton</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Diego Caminha B.</foreName>
            <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
            <initial>D. C. B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp94304">
            <foreName>David</foreName>
            <surname>Déharbe</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Fontaine</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Renate</foreName>
            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Proc. Conference on Automated Deduction (CADE)</title>
        <loc>Montreal, Canada</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">5663</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">151-156</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid8" type="incollection" rend="refer" n="refercite:cansell:event-b">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">The Event-B Modelling Method: Concepts and Case Studies</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Cansell</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Méry</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dines</foreName>
            <surname>Bjørner</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Martin C.</foreName>
            <surname>Henson</surname>
            <initial>M. C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Logics of Specification Languages</title>
        <loc>Berlin-Heidelberg</loc>
        <title level="s">Monographs in Theoretical Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">47-152</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid7" type="inproceedings" rend="refer" n="refercite:cousineau:hal-00726631">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">TLA+ Proofs</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Denis</foreName>
            <surname>Cousineau</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="gallium-2014-idm26976">
            <foreName>Damien</foreName>
            <surname>Doligez</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Leslie</foreName>
            <surname>Lamport</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Daniel</foreName>
            <surname>Ricketts</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp83832">
            <foreName>Hernán</foreName>
            <surname>Vanzetto</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dimitra</foreName>
            <surname>Giannakopoulou</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Méry</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">18th International Symposium On Formal Methods - FM 2012</title>
        <loc>Paris, France</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">7436</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">147-154</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid5" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:dolzmann:redlog">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Redlog: Computer algebra meets computer logic</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andreas</foreName>
            <surname>Dolzmann</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm25184">
            <foreName>Thomas</foreName>
            <surname>Sturm</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">ACM SIGSAM Bull.</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">31</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1997</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">2-9</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid49" type="inproceedings" rend="refer" n="refercite:deharbe:symmetry">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Exploiting Symmetry in SMT Problems</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp94304">
            <foreName>David</foreName>
            <surname>Déharbe</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Fontaine</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bruno</foreName>
            <surname>Woltzenlogel Paleo</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nikolaj</foreName>
            <surname>Bjørner</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Viorica</foreName>
            <surname>Sofronie-Stokkermans</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">23rd Intl. Conf. Automated Deduction (CADE 2011)</title>
        <loc>Wroclaw, Poland</loc>
        <title level="s">LNCS</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">6803</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2011</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">222-236</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid50" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:fietzke:timed-automata">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Superposition as a Decision Procedure for Timed Automata</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp80072">
            <foreName>Arnaud</foreName>
            <surname>Fietzke</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Mathematics in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">409-425</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid51" type="book" rend="refer" n="refercite:KROGER:2008:Inria-00274806:1">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="inria-00274806"/>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Temporal Logic and State Systems</title>
        <title level="s">Texts in Theoretical Computer Science</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Fred</foreName>
            <surname>Kröger</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">436</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00274806/en/" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>inria-00274806/<allowbreak/>en/</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid52" type="article" rend="refer" n="refercite:kruglov:ground-theories">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Superposition Decides the First-Order Logic Fragment Over Ground Theories</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Evgeny</foreName>
            <surname>Kruglov</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Mathematics in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">6</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">4</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">427-456</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid9" type="incollection" rend="refer" n="refercite:merz:tlabook">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">The Specification Language TLA<sup>+</sup></title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dines</foreName>
            <surname>Bjørner</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Martin C.</foreName>
            <surname>Henson</surname>
            <initial>M. C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Logics of Specification Languages</title>
        <loc>Berlin-Heidelberg</loc>
        <title level="s">Monographs in Theoretical Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2008</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">401-451</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid0" type="inproceedings" rend="refer" n="refercite:weidenbach:spass">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">SPASS Version 3.5</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dilyana</foreName>
            <surname>Dimova</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp80072">
            <foreName>Arnaud</foreName>
            <surname>Fietzke</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Martin</foreName>
            <surname>Suda</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Wischnewski</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Renate</foreName>
            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">22nd International Conference on Automated Deduction (CADE-22)</title>
        <loc>Montreal, Canada</loc>
        <title level="s">LNAI</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">5663</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">140-145</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid20" type="proceedings" rend="year" n="cite:blanchette:hal-01356464">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-43144-4"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01356464"/>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes">
        <title level="m">Interactive Theorem Proving: 7th International Conference, ITP 2016</title>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9807</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer<address><addrLine>Nancy, France</addrLine></address></orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01356464" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01356464</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid29" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:aitameur:hal-01245832">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.scico.2015.12.004"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01245832"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Making explicit domain knowledge in formal system development</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yamine</foreName>
            <surname>Ait Ameur</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Méry</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01754">
        <idno type="issn">0167-6423</idno>
        <title level="j">Science of Computer Programming</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">121</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">100–127</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>March</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01245832" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01245832</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid31" type="incollection" rend="year" n="cite:andriamiarina:hal-01246669">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01246669"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Incremental Proof-Based Development for Resilient Distributed Systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp73816">
            <foreName>Manamiary Bruno</foreName>
            <surname>Andriamiarina</surname>
            <initial>M. B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Méry</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Neeraj Kumar</foreName>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <initial>N. K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no">
        <title level="m">Trustworthy Cyber-Physical Systems Engineering</title>
        <title level="s">Trustworthy Cyber-Physical Systems Engineering</title>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Taylor and Francis Group</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01246669" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01246669</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid42" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:blanchette:hal-01211748">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s10817-015-9335-3"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01211748"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Semi-intelligible Isar Proofs from Machine-Generated Proofs</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sascha</foreName>
            <surname>Böhme</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idp86936">
            <foreName>Mathias</foreName>
            <surname>Fleury</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Steffen Juilf</foreName>
            <surname>Smolka</surname>
            <initial>S. J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Albert</foreName>
            <surname>Steckermeier</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01057">
        <idno type="issn">0168-7433</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Automated Reasoning</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01211748" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01211748</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid46" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:blanchette:hal-01386986">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s10817-016-9362-8"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01386986"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Learning-Based Fact Selector for Isabelle/HOL</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>David</foreName>
            <surname>Greenaway</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Cezary</foreName>
            <surname>Kaliszyk</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Daniel</foreName>
            <surname>Kühlwein</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Josef</foreName>
            <surname>Urban</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01057">
        <idno type="issn">0168-7433</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Automated Reasoning</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">57</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">219 - 244</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01386986" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01386986</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid47" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:blanchette:hal-01386988">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01386988"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Hammering towards QED</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Cezary</foreName>
            <surname>Kaliszyk</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Lawrence C.</foreName>
            <surname>Paulson</surname>
            <initial>L. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Josef</foreName>
            <surname>Urban</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01975">
        <idno type="issn">1972-5787</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Formalized Reasoning</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">1</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">101-148</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01386988" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01386988</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid17" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:kosta:hal-01388720">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1016/j.jsc.2015.07.002"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01388720"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Better answers to real questions</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp81320">
            <foreName>Marek</foreName>
            <surname>Košta</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm25184">
            <foreName>Thomas</foreName>
            <surname>Sturm</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andreas</foreName>
            <surname>Dolzmann</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid01272">
        <idno type="issn">0747-7171</idno>
        <title level="j">Journal of Symbolic Computation</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">74</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">255 - 275</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01388720" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01388720</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid44" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:merz:hal-01356470">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00165-016-0390-2"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01356470"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Editorial</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jun</foreName>
            <surname>Pang</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00601">
        <idno type="issn">0934-5043</idno>
        <title level="j">Formal Aspects of Computing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">28</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">343-344</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01356470" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01356470</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid45" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:merz:hal-01356471">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/s00165-016-0390-2"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01356471"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Editorial</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jun</foreName>
            <surname>Pang</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00601">
        <idno type="issn">0934-5043</idno>
        <title level="j">Formal Aspects of Computing</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">28</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">5</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">723-724</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01356471" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01356471</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid30" type="article" rend="year" n="cite:mery:hal-01316026">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01316026"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Playing with State-Based Models for Designing Better Algorithms</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Méry</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-editorial-board="yes" x-international-audience="yes" id="rid00622">
        <idno type="issn">0167-739X</idno>
        <title level="j">Future Generation Computer Systems</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">25</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01316026" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01316026</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid13" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:abraham:hal-01377655">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01377655"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">SC 2 : Satisfiability Checking meets Symbolic Computation (Project Paper)</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Eriká H</foreName>
            <surname>Abrahám</surname>
            <initial>E. H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>John</foreName>
            <surname>Abbott</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bernd</foreName>
            <surname>Becker</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anna M</foreName>
            <surname>Bigatti</surname>
            <initial>A. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Martin M</foreName>
            <surname>Brain</surname>
            <initial>M. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bruno</foreName>
            <surname>Buchberger</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alessandro</foreName>
            <surname>Cimatti</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>James H</foreName>
            <surname>Davenport</surname>
            <initial>J. H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Matthew M</foreName>
            <surname>England</surname>
            <initial>M. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Fontaine</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Stephen M</foreName>
            <surname>Forrest</surname>
            <initial>S. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alberto</foreName>
            <surname>Griggio</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Daniel</foreName>
            <surname>Kroening</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Werner M</foreName>
            <surname>Seiler</surname>
            <initial>W. M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm25184">
            <foreName>Thomas</foreName>
            <surname>Sturm</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Intelligent Computer Mathematics</title>
        <loc>Bialystok, Poland</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01377655" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01377655</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid511741">
          <title>Conference on Intelligent Computer Mathematics</title>
          <num>2012</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">CICM</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid18" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:azaiez:hal-01322335">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-33600-8_4"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01322335"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Proving Determinacy of the PharOS Real-Time Operating System</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Selma</foreName>
            <surname>Azaiez</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="gallium-2014-idm26976">
            <foreName>Damien</foreName>
            <surname>Doligez</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Matthieu</foreName>
            <surname>Lemerre</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="parsifal-2015-idp71224">
            <foreName>Tomer</foreName>
            <surname>Libal</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael J.</foreName>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <initial>M. J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Klaus-Dieter</foreName>
            <surname>Schewe</surname>
            <initial>K.-D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Atif</foreName>
            <surname>Mashkoor</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Miklós</foreName>
            <surname>Biró</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Abstract State Machines, Alloy, B, TLA, VDM, and Z - 5th International Conference, ABZ 2016</title>
        <loc>Linz, Austria</loc>
        <title level="s">LNCS - Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9675</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">70-85</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01322335" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01322335</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid387338">
          <title>Abstract State Machines, Alloy, B and Z</title>
          <num>5</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ABZ</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid19" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:azmy:hal-01322342">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-33600-8_5"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01322342"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Rigorous Correctness Proof for Pastry</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp75064">
            <foreName>Noran</foreName>
            <surname>Azmy</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael J.</foreName>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <initial>M. J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Klaus-Dieter</foreName>
            <surname>Schewe</surname>
            <initial>K.-D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Atif</foreName>
            <surname>Mashkoor</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Miklós</foreName>
            <surname>Biró</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Abstract State Machines, Alloy, B, TLA, VDM, and Z - 5th International Conference, ABZ 2016</title>
        <loc>Linz, Austria</loc>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9675</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">86-101</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01322342" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01322342</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid387338">
          <title>Abstract State Machines, Alloy, B and Z</title>
          <num>5</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ABZ</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid48" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:blanchette:hal-01401812">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401812"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Friends with Benefits: Implementing Foundational Corecursion in Isabelle/HOL (Extended Abstract)</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Aymeric</foreName>
            <surname>Bouzy</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andreas</foreName>
            <surname>Lochbihler</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andrei</foreName>
            <surname>Popescu</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Dmitriy</foreName>
            <surname>Traytel</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Isabelle Workshop 2016</title>
        <loc>Nancy, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401812" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401812</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid339751">
          <title>Isabelle Workshop</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISABELLE</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid43" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:blanchette:hal-01401807">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401807"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Verified SAT Solver Framework with Learn, Forget, Restart, and Incrementality (Extended Abstract)</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idp86936">
            <foreName>Mathias</foreName>
            <surname>Fleury</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Isabellle Workshop 2016</title>
        <loc>Nancy, France</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401807" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401807</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid339751">
          <title>Isabelle Workshop</title>
          <num>2016</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISABELLE</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid14" type="inproceedings" rend="best" n="cite:blanchette:hal-01336074">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-40229-1_4"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01336074"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Verified SAT Solver Framework with Learn, Forget, Restart, and Incrementality</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idp86936">
            <foreName>Mathias</foreName>
            <surname>Fleury</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">8th International Joint Conference on Automated Reasoning (IJCAR 2016)</title>
        <loc>Coimbra, Portugal</loc>
        <title level="s">Automated Reasoning - 8th International Joint Conference, IJCAR 2016, Coimbra, Portugal, June 27 - July 2, 2016, Proceedings</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01336074" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01336074</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid308113">
          <title>International Joint Conference on Automated Reasoning</title>
          <num>8</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IJCAR</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid27" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bromberger:hal-01403214">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403214"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Computing a Complete Basis for Equalities Implied by a System of LRA Constraints</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp77544">
            <foreName>Martin</foreName>
            <surname>Bromberger</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tim</foreName>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ruzica</foreName>
            <surname>Piskac</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">14th International Workshop on Satisfiability Modulo Theories</title>
        <loc>Coimbra, Portugal</loc>
        <title level="s">CEUR Workshop Proceedings</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">1617</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">15-30</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01403214" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403214</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid334698">
          <title>International Workshop on Satisfiability Modulo Theories</title>
          <num>14</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">SMT</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid28" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:bromberger:hal-01403200">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-40229-1_9"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403200"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Fast Cube Tests for LIA Constraint Solving</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp77544">
            <foreName>Martin</foreName>
            <surname>Bromberger</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nicola</foreName>
            <surname>Olivetti</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ashish</foreName>
            <surname>Tiwari</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Automated Reasoning - 8th International Joint Conference (IJCAR 2016)</title>
        <loc>Coimbra, Portugal</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9706</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">116-132</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01403200" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403200</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid308113">
          <title>International Joint Conference on Automated Reasoning</title>
          <num>8</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IJCAR</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid16" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:cruanes:hal-01401696">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.4204/EPTCS.210.3"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01401696"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Extending Nunchaku to Dependent Type Theory</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="deducteam-2014-idp99360">
            <foreName>Simon</foreName>
            <surname>Cruanes</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Hammers for Type Theories (HaTT 2016)</title>
        <loc>Coimbra, Portugal</loc>
        <title level="s">Proceedings First International Workshop on Hammers for Type Theories</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">210</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">3 - 12</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01401696" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01401696</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid625535">
          <title>Workshop on Hammers for Type Theories</title>
          <num>1</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">HaTT</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid37" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:fetzer:hal-01403190">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-47169-3_48"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403190"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Compliance, Functional Safety and Fault Detection by Formal Methods</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christof</foreName>
            <surname>Fetzer</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Patrick</foreName>
            <surname>Wischnewski</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tiziana</foreName>
            <surname>Margaria</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bernhard</foreName>
            <surname>Steffen</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Leveraging Applications of Formal Methods, Verification and Validation (ISOLA 2016)</title>
        <loc>Corfu, Greece</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9953</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">626 - 632</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01403190" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403190</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid315917">
          <title>International Symposium on Leveraging Applications of Formal Methods, Verification, and Validation</title>
          <num>7</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISOLA</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid24" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:haelbrenas:hal-01403585">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-46750-4_18"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403585"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Ensuring Correctness of Model Transformations While Remaining Decidable</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jon</foreName>
            <surname>Haël Brenas</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rachid</foreName>
            <surname>Echahed</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2016-idp162592">
            <foreName>Martin</foreName>
            <surname>Strecker</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">Theoretical Aspects of Computing - ICTAC</title>
        <loc>Taipei, Taiwan</loc>
        <title level="s">Theoretical Aspects of Computing – ICTAC 2016 13th International Colloquium, Taipei, Taiwan, ROC, October 24–31, 2016, Proceedings</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">315 - 332</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01403585" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>archives-ouvertes.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403585</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid106673">
          <title>International Colloquium on Theoretical Aspects of Computing</title>
          <num>13</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ICTAC</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid23" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:merz:hal-01322328">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-33600-8_3"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01322328"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Encoding TLA+ into Many-Sorted First-Order Logic</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm26664">
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Merz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp83832">
            <foreName>Hernán</foreName>
            <surname>Vanzetto</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael J.</foreName>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <initial>M. J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Klaus-Dieter</foreName>
            <surname>Schewe</surname>
            <initial>K.-D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Atif</foreName>
            <surname>Mashkoor</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Miklós</foreName>
            <surname>Biró</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Abstract State Machines, Alloy, B, TLA, VDM, and Z - 5th International Conference, ABZ 2016</title>
        <loc>Linz, Austria</loc>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9675</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">54-69</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01322328" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01322328</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid387338">
          <title>Abstract State Machines, Alloy, B and Z</title>
          <num>5</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ABZ</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid32" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:mery:hal-01369425">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-47166-2_57"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01369425"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">On two Friends for getting Correct ProgramsAutomatically Translating Event B Specifications to Recursive Algorithms in Rodin</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Méry</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rosemary</foreName>
            <surname>Monahan</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Cheng</foreName>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Bernhard</foreName>
            <surname>Steffen</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tiziana</foreName>
            <surname>Margaria</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">ISOLA 2016</title>
        <loc>CORFU, Greece</loc>
        <title level="s">Leveraging Applications of Formal Methods, Verification and Validation: Foundational Techniques</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">I</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">9952</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Bernhard Steffen and Tiziana Margaria</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>October</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">18</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01369425" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01369425</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid315917">
          <title>International Symposium on Leveraging Applications of Formal Methods, Verification, and Validation</title>
          <num>7</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">ISOLA</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid40" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:reynolds:hal-01336082">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-40229-1_10"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01336082"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Model Finding for Recursive Functions in SMT</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andrew</foreName>
            <surname>Reynolds</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="deducteam-2014-idp99360">
            <foreName>Simon</foreName>
            <surname>Cruanes</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Cesare</foreName>
            <surname>Tinelli</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">8th International Joint Conference on Automated Reasoning (IJCAR 2016)</title>
        <loc>Coimbra, Portugal</loc>
        <title level="s">Automated Reasoning - 8th International Joint Conference, IJCAR 2016, Coimbra, Portugal, June 27 - July 2, 2016, Proceedings</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>June</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01336082" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01336082</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid308113">
          <title>International Joint Conference on Automated Reasoning</title>
          <num>8</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IJCAR</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid15" type="inproceedings" rend="best" n="cite:reynolds:hal-01397082">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01397082"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Decision Procedure for (Co)datatypes in SMT Solvers</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andrew</foreName>
            <surname>Reynolds</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2015-idm28624">
            <foreName>Jasmin Christian</foreName>
            <surname>Blanchette</surname>
            <initial>J. C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="yes" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">IJCAI 2016</title>
        <loc>New York City, United States</loc>
        <title level="s">Proceedings of the Twenty-Fifth International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence, IJCAI 2016, New York, NY, USA, 9-15 July 2016</title>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01397082" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01397082</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid307932">
          <title>International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
          <num>25</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">IJCAI</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid25" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:sturm:hal-01389744">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1145/2933575.2934532"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01389744"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Deciding First-Order Satisfiability when Universal and Existential Variables are Separated</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idm25184">
            <foreName>Thomas</foreName>
            <surname>Sturm</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp85200">
            <foreName>Marco</foreName>
            <surname>Voigt</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <title level="m">LICS 2016</title>
        <loc>New York, United States</loc>
        <imprint>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">86 - 95</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01389744" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01389744</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid31229">
          <title>Annual IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science</title>
          <num>31</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">LICS</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid26" type="inproceedings" rend="year" n="cite:teucke:hal-01403206">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01403206"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Ordered Resolution with Straight Dismatching Constraints</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Andreas</foreName>
            <surname>Teucke</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp68312">
            <foreName>Christoph</foreName>
            <surname>Weidenbach</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Fontaine</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Stephan</foreName>
            <surname>Schulz</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Josef</foreName>
            <surname>Urban</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">5th Workshop on Practical Aspects of Automated Reasoning (PAAR 2016)</title>
        <loc>Coimbra, Portugal</loc>
        <title level="s">CEUR Workshop Proceedings</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">1635</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2016</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">95-109</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01403206" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01403206</ref>
        </imprint>
        <meeting id="cid405090">
          <title>Workshop on Practical Aspects of Automated Reasoning (PAAR)</title>
          <num>5</num>
          <abbr type="sigle">PAAR</abbr>
        </meeting>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid10" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:abrial:event-b">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Modeling in Event-B: System and Software Engineering</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jean-Raymond</foreName>
            <surname>Abrial</surname>
            <initial>J.-R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Cambridge University Press</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2010</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid1" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:bachmair:rewrite">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Rewrite-Based Equational Theorem Proving with Selection and Simplification</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Leo</foreName>
            <surname>Bachmair</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Harald</foreName>
            <surname>Ganzinger</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">Journal of Logic and Computation</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">3</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1994</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">217–247</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid11" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:back:refinement">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Refinement calculus—A systematic introduction</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>R.</foreName>
            <surname>Back</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>J.</foreName>
            <surname>von Wright</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer Verlag</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1998</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid4" type="incollection" rend="foot" n="footcite:barrett:smt">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Satisfiability Modulo Theories</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Clark</foreName>
            <surname>Barrett</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Roberto</foreName>
            <surname>Sebastiani</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sanjit A.</foreName>
            <surname>Seshia</surname>
            <initial>S. A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Cesare</foreName>
            <surname>Tinelli</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Armin</foreName>
            <surname>Biere</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Marijn J. H.</foreName>
            <surname>Heule</surname>
            <initial>Marijn J. H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Hans</foreName>
            <surname>van Maaren</surname>
            <initial>H.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Toby</foreName>
            <surname>Walsh</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Handbook of Satisfiability</title>
        <title level="s">Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence and Applications</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">185</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="chapter">26</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>IOS Press</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>February</month>
            <year>2009</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">825-885</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid21" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:chocron:hal-01157898">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-21401-6_29"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01157898"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Polite Non-Disjoint Combination Method: Theories with Bridging Functions Revisited</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Paula</foreName>
            <surname>Chocron</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Fontaine</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="cassis-2014-idp67000">
            <foreName>Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Ringeissen</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName key="marelle-2014-idp84232">
            <foreName>Amy P.</foreName>
            <surname>Felty</surname>
            <initial>A. P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Aart</foreName>
            <surname>Middeldorp</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">25th International Conference on Automated Deduction, CADE-25</title>
        <loc>Berlin, Germany</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9195</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="organisation">Christoph Benzmueller</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>August</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">419-433</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01157898" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01157898</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid22" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:chocron:hal-01206187">
      <identifiant type="doi" value="10.1007/978-3-319-24246-0_17"/>
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01206187"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Rewriting Approach to the Combination of Data Structures with Bridging Theories</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Paula</foreName>
            <surname>Chocron</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp71104">
            <foreName>Pascal</foreName>
            <surname>Fontaine</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName key="cassis-2014-idp67000">
            <foreName>Christophe</foreName>
            <surname>Ringeissen</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr x-scientific-popularization="no" x-international-audience="yes" x-proceedings="yes" x-invited-conference="no" x-editorial-board="yes">
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Carsten</foreName>
            <surname>Lutz</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Silvio</foreName>
            <surname>Ranise</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Frontiers of Combining Systems - 10th International Symposium, FroCoS 2015</title>
        <loc>Wroclaw, Poland</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9322</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <month>September</month>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">275–290</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01206187" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01206187</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid36" type="article" rend="foot" n="footcite:foster:languages">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Languages for software-defined networks</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nate</foreName>
            <surname>Foster</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Arjun</foreName>
            <surname>Guha</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Mark</foreName>
            <surname>Reitblatt</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Alec</foreName>
            <surname>Story</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Michael J.</foreName>
            <surname>Freedman</surname>
            <initial>M. J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Naga</foreName>
            <surname>Praveen Katta</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Christopher</foreName>
            <surname>Monsanto</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Joshua</foreName>
            <surname>Reich</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Jennifer</foreName>
            <surname>Rexford</surname>
            <initial>J.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Cole</foreName>
            <surname>Schlesinger</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>David</foreName>
            <surname>Walker</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rob</foreName>
            <surname>Harrison</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="j">IEEE Communications Magazine</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">51</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="number">2</biblScope>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">128-134</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid6" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:lamport:tlabook">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Specifying Systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Leslie</foreName>
            <surname>Lamport</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Addison-Wesley<address><addrLine>Boston, Mass.</addrLine></address></orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2002</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid35" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:lemerre:deterministic">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">A Model of Parallel Deterministic Real-Time Computation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Matthieu</foreName>
            <surname>Lemerre</surname>
            <initial>M.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Emmanuel</foreName>
            <surname>Ohayon</surname>
            <initial>E.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Proc. 33rd IEEE Real-Time Systems Symposium (RTSS 2012)</title>
        <loc>San Juan, PR, U.S.A.</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>IEEE Comp. Soc.</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2012</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">273-282</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid34" type="phdthesis" rend="foot" n="footcite:lu:thesis">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Formal Verification of the Pastry Protocol</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Tianxiang</foreName>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <initial>T.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName type="school">Universität des Saarlandes and Université de Lorraine</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2013</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="typdoc">Ph. D. Thesis</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid12" type="book" rend="foot" n="footcite:morgan:programming">
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">Programming from Specifications</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Carroll</foreName>
            <surname>Morgan</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Prentice Hall</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>1998</year>
          </dateStruct>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">2nd edition</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid39" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:mery:hal-01245991">
      <identifiant type="hal" value="hal-01245991"/>
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Integrating Domain-Based Features into Event-B: a Nose Gear Velocity Case Study</title>
        <author>
          <persName key="veridis-2014-idp72368">
            <foreName>Dominique</foreName>
            <surname>Méry</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sawant</foreName>
            <surname>Rushikesh</surname>
            <initial>S.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anton</foreName>
            <surname>Tarasyuk</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ladjel</foreName>
            <surname>Bellatreche</surname>
            <initial>L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Yannis</foreName>
            <surname>Manolopoulos</surname>
            <initial>Y.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Model and Data Engineering - 5th International Conference, MEDI 2015</title>
        <loc>Rhodos, Greece</loc>
        <title level="s">LNCS</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">9344</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2015</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">89-102</biblScope>
          <ref xlink:href="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01245991" location="extern" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://<allowbreak/>hal.<allowbreak/>inria.<allowbreak/>fr/<allowbreak/>hal-01245991</ref>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid41" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:ongaro:raft">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">In Search of an Understandable Consensus Algorithm</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Diego</foreName>
            <surname>Ongaro</surname>
            <initial>D.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>John K.</foreName>
            <surname>Ousterhout</surname>
            <initial>J. K.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Garth</foreName>
            <surname>Gibson</surname>
            <initial>G.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Nickolai</foreName>
            <surname>Zeldovich</surname>
            <initial>N.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">USENIX Annual Technical Conference 2014</title>
        <loc>Philadelphia, PA</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Usenix Association</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2014</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">305-319</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid33" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:rowstron:pastry">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Pastry: Scalable, Decentralized Object Location, and Routing for Large-Scale Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Anthony</foreName>
            <surname>Rowstron</surname>
            <initial>A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Peter</foreName>
            <surname>Druschel</surname>
            <initial>P.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Rachid</foreName>
            <surname>Guerraoui</surname>
            <initial>R.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">IFIP/ACM International Conference on Distributed Systems Platforms (Middleware 2001)</title>
        <loc>Heidelberg, Germany</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">2218</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2001</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">329-350</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid2" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:sofronie:hierarchical">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Hierarchical and modular reasoning in complex theories: The case of local theory extensions</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Viorica</foreName>
            <surname>Sofronie-Stokkermans</surname>
            <initial>V.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <editor role="editor">
          <persName>
            <foreName>Boris</foreName>
            <surname>Konev</surname>
            <initial>B.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Frank</foreName>
            <surname>Wolter</surname>
            <initial>F.</initial>
          </persName>
        </editor>
        <title level="m">Frontiers of Combining Systems. 6th International Symposium FroCos 2007, Proceedings</title>
        <loc>Liverpool, UK</loc>
        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
        <imprint>
          <biblScope type="volume">4720</biblScope>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Springer</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2007</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">47-71</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
      <note type="bnote">Invited paper</note>
    </biblStruct>
    
    <biblStruct id="veridis-2016-bid38" type="inproceedings" rend="foot" n="footcite:weil:ceph">
      <analytic>
        <title level="a">Ceph: A Scalable, High-Performance Distributed File System</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Sage A.</foreName>
            <surname>Weil</surname>
            <initial>S. A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Scott A.</foreName>
            <surname>Brandt</surname>
            <initial>S. A.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Ethan L.</foreName>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <initial>E. L.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Darrell D. E.</foreName>
            <surname>Long</surname>
            <initial>D. D. E.</initial>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <foreName>Carlos</foreName>
            <surname>Maltzahn</surname>
            <initial>C.</initial>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </analytic>
      <monogr>
        <title level="m">7th Symp. Operating Systems Design and Implementation (OSDI '06)</title>
        <loc>Seattle, WA</loc>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>
            <orgName>Usenix Association</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <dateStruct>
            <year>2006</year>
          </dateStruct>
          <biblScope type="pages">307-320</biblScope>
        </imprint>
      </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
  </biblio>
</raweb>
